<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>anxiety on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/tags/anxiety/</link>
    <description>Recent content in anxiety on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda-email.netlify.app/tags/anxiety/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Anxiety</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/overcoming-anxiety/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/overcoming-anxiety/</guid>
      <description>Anxiety is one of the diseases of our age, affecting almost two-thirds of the population, with nearly a third finding it debilitating.
Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The main causes of nervousness are 1) long-continued overactivity, 2) excessive stimulation of the senses from physical overindulgence, and 3) mental overstimulation from chronic fear, anger, sorrow, hatred, jealousy, discontent, or similar harmful emotions.
“Any violent or prolonged excitement disturbs the flow of life force through the nervous system.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Anxiety is one of the diseases of our age, affecting almost two-thirds of the population, with nearly a third finding it debilitating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The main causes of nervousness are 1) long-continued overactivity, 2) excessive stimulation of the senses from physical overindulgence, and 3) mental overstimulation from chronic fear, anger, sorrow, hatred, jealousy, discontent, or similar harmful emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any violent or prolonged excitement disturbs the flow of life force through the nervous system. If you put a two-thousand-volt current through a fifty-watt lamp, it will burn out the lamp. In the same way, excessive stimulation burns the nerves, cutting off the supply of energy and upsetting the functioning of the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most damaging emotions are anger and fear. Anger burns the nerves in the brain and causes poisons to be secreted throughout the body. Fear burns the nerves that supply the heart and can cause heart trouble. Feelings of timidity destroy the nerve endings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety, therefore, can be seen as a disease of the nerves, and the following physical methods can help cool our system and alleviate symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, water is an excellent nerve tonic, so bathing, swimming, or even taking a cold shower can help. Yogananda taught that lime juice in water sweetened to neither sweet nor sour can soothe the nerves. Satwic foods, particularly fruit, will cool the nerves, while tamasic foods, excessive spices, or overeating will be harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, exercise and walking, especially in nature, can help reset the entire system. Hippocrates is reported to have said, “If you are in a bad mood go for a walk. If you are still in a bad mood go for another walk.” Yogananda’s Energization Exercises, yoga postures, and the affirmations of the Ananda Yoga system are specifically designed to strengthen and realign the flow of prana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, sleep is very healing. If you have trouble falling asleep, try this: First relax your entire face including the tongue; next, drop your shoulders and let your hands drop to your sides. Then exhale, relaxing your chest, and focus on the breath; let your lower body and limbs relax, succumbing to the pull of gravity. Finally, clear your mind of all thoughts for ten seconds. The US military teaches this system (it sounds like it is straight out of a yoga class) and reports that a vast majority of people can learn to fall asleep within two minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/overcoming-anxiety.png&#34;  alt=&#34;overcoming anxiety&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since the most damaging emotions are anger and fear, it’s essential to control these sentiments actively. Accept that anxiety is an emotional condition and not amenable to logic. News and media, especially opinions, are designed to evoke fear and anger, so avoid that mental poison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t control the uncontrollable, especially world situations that have little direct influence on our daily lives. Focus on changing yourself, since this is all you can actually control, and even that is a Herculean task. “Do your best and forget tomorrow” is Yogananda’s advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;meditation-and-faith&#34;&gt;Meditation and Faith&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation is a powerful tool for calming the mind and reducing stress. It allows us to step back from the constant chatter of our thoughts and emotions, and to connect with a deeper sense of peace and stillness within ourselves. Regular meditation and breathing techniques will rewire the brain, making us less vulnerable to stress and anxiety. Serving others will break the tendency to think about our own worries and fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most powerful antidote to anxiety is faith. Yogananda said, “The cure for soul nervousness lies in transferring your attention from this little cage of the body to the perception of the Infinite. As a child of the Infinite, you must learn to reflect the image of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety is a physical, mental, and spiritual disease. Overcome it by giving your hopes and fears to God. Pray in this manner: “Divine Mother, I accept everything that happens as coming from Thee. Please bless me and those I love. Let Thy will be my will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In peace,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
