<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dharma on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/dharma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in dharma on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/dharma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Finding Your Dharma</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-your-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-your-dharma/</guid>
      <description>This week we’ve been having a wonderful gathering for Inner Renewal Retreat, whose theme has been “Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation.” The Temple of Light here at Ananda’s Expanding Light Retreat has been packed with several hundred residents and guests; another three thousand five hundred people are enrolled online. (If you’re interested in watching the classes and other events, you can still receive a free link.)
One of the most frequently asked questions on this topic is “How do I know what my dharma is?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This week we’ve been having a wonderful gathering for Inner Renewal Retreat, whose theme has been “Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation.” The Temple of Light here at Ananda’s Expanding Light Retreat has been packed with several hundred residents and guests; another three thousand five hundred people are enrolled online. (If you’re interested in watching the classes and other events, you can still receive a free link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most frequently asked questions on this topic is “How do I know what my dharma is?” Let’s talk about two different aspects of this: the longer rhythms or patterns that govern our lifetime as a whole, and the situations that arise from moment to moment as our life unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While our ultimate destiny is Self-realization, there is also the dharma of any particular life as determined by our past karma. Swami Kriyananda wrote: “The duty [dharma] of every man is that which is particularly his own, ordained for him by karmic bonds he himself has forged, and must untie to release himself from attachment to ego.” Each one of us has a unique journey to soul freedom through the maze of our past karma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once many years ago after a Kriya Initiation, Swamiji shared with a small group an amazing experience he had had during the ceremony. “As each person came up for the blessing,” he told us, “I could feel his unique path to liberation.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/finding-your-dharma.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;finding-your-dharma&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For devotees, the dharmic life pattern is something we should patiently allow to unfold, without forcing the circumstances and without undo anxiety. I had a good friend who was torn over the issue of whether she should marry or become a monastic. After a year of stressing over this, she finally asked Swamiji what he felt her dharma was. His response was: “Your karma could go either way. Let’s see what happens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So she waited. After five years, she had become unattached on a deep level. By that point, she was ready to accept her dharma (whatever it might be), and get on with her life. Again, she asked Swamiji what her dharma was, and this time he answered, “You should marry.” Circumstances were such that she was happily married within a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Master’s disciples said, “Your own will surely come to you. In fact, you cannot avoid it.” Our dharma for a lifetime—especially the outward role we are to play—is most often determined by past karmic forces that we cannot control, and often are not even aware of consciously. But if we give our life to God in discipleship, service, and devotion, and wait patiently for His guidance, the right life path will open before us. The challenge is in following our dharma once it becomes clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For there is the problem of discerning dharmic responses to the myriad of questions that arise in daily life: What, in each case, is the right action to take? The best place to start is to tackle the problems closest at hand using these criteria: 1) address the situation with the best energy you have; 2) do it without attachment to the results; and 3) ask for the inner guidance of the guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master gave us this marvelous prayer: “I will reason, I will will, I will act, but guide Thou my reason, will, and activity to the right path in everything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with the battles you are confident of winning. For example, if you are a lazy person, it would be unwise to decide, “I’m going to run a marathon and will get up every day at 6:00 a.m. to run for an hour.” It would be much better to start with a smaller goal that you can accomplish: “I’m going to walk for thirty minutes three days a week.” Conquer the negative habit of laziness by taking doable steps, and keep building on your strengths, until one day you may run that marathon. This is the way of victory over past karma by practicing right action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna says: “To do one’s own duty even unsuccessfully is better than to do someone else’s successfully.” (3:35) It is important, therefore, if we are to discover and follow our unique path of dharma, that we not be attached to the results of our actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad karma is merely energy that has been misdirected. Through meditation, right action, and divine grace, we can follow our dharma, break the bondage of karma, and achieve freedom in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With enthusiasm and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embrace Your Dharma</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/embrace-your-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/embrace-your-dharma/</guid>
      <description>This year’s Inner Renewal Retreat theme is Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation. We’re delighted to announce that for the first time we will be streaming all of the classes free of charge. Over 2,000 people have already registered. We hope that you too will join us.
Throughout the week, Devi and I will be exploring the profound and multifaceted concept of dharma, which has various shades of meaning:
It is the eternal and inherent nature of reality.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This year’s Inner Renewal Retreat theme is Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation. We’re delighted to announce that for the first time we will be streaming all of the classes free of charge. Over 2,000 people have already registered. We hope that you too will join us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, Devi and I will be exploring the profound and multifaceted concept of dharma, which has various shades of meaning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is the eternal and inherent nature of reality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is the cosmic law underpinning order in the universe and in human society.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is the right duties and behavior for each individual according to his role and station in life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda often captured the essence of Sanaatan Dharma in this way: “We were created by God as an extension of His consciousness. And it is our destiny to return to Him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people ask, “What is my dharma?” they generally mean, what is good for me personally. What choices should I make regarding career, marriage, and parenthood? Should I move to this place or that? While these are significant life decisions, we shouldn’t start here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to recognize that we have two dharmas: the timeless dharma of the soul aiming to reunite with God, and the dharma of our current life. Happiness and success will follow only if we align the actions of this life with the eternal dharma of our soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we experience the progressive development of successive lives, our dharma shifts. Spiritual awareness, or “specific gravity,” advances from being “heavy”—dull and indifferent—to “ego-active”—self-absorbed and reward oriented—to finally becoming “light”—spontaneously drawn to higher truth and unselfishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although most readers of this blog fall into the “light” stage, we occasionally face lapses in judgment when our energy drops. It is then that we stray from our higher dharma and make choices that get us in trouble. We could save ourselves endless trouble and heartache if, before any important choice, we would ask, “Will this help my spiritual evolution?”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/embrace-your-dharma.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;embrace-your-dharma&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a larger issue also. When we act dharmically, we bring light into the world. As Yogananda put it, “The ills attributed to an anthropomorphic abstraction called ‘society’ may be laid more realistically at the door of Everyman. Utopia must spring in the private bosom before it can flower in civic virtue. Man is a soul, not an institution; his inner reforms alone can lend permanence to outer ones.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To act dharmically, consider these three practical steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get Centered Before You Decide:&lt;/strong&gt; Meditate deeply before making important decisions. A calm mind and heart activates our inborn intuition. For life-defining choices it is helpful to get away from our daily routines and spend time in a calm, spiritually uplifted environment. For everyday decisions, a few deep breaths to center yourself can make a big difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seek Guidance:&lt;/strong&gt; Pray to God and Gurus for direction. Their guidance is there when we listen sensitively. It also helps to consult with trusted spiritual guides and friends. Ask with openness and trust. Paramhansa Yogananda has a beautiful affirmation: “I go forth in perfect faith in the power of omnipresent Good to bring me what I need, when I need it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust as Necessary:&lt;/strong&gt; After arriving at a decision, it is important to reevaluate your course from time to time and make adjustments as needed. I’m reminded of a cartoon of a man and woman in a car that has stopped in front of an iceberg with a polar bear on it. The caption reads, “When they told us to turn north, maybe we should have asked them how far.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember that as long as we try to act dharmically, we can’t really go too far astray. After all, we are extensions of God, and it is our destiny to return to Him. Let’s relax and fill the journey with joy and delight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of dharma,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
