<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>harmony on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/harmony/</link>
    <description>Recent content in harmony on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/harmony/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to Pray</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/how-to-pray/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/how-to-pray/</guid>
      <description>Paramhansa Yogananda came to the West with a God-ordained mission: to bring teachings and techniques to help people attain higher consciousness. With wisdom and foresight, Master and the others in our line of gurus saw that a time of global upheaval was coming to the world. Out of compassion, Yoganandaji brought twofold gifts to help us deal with the impending suffering: 1) spiritual tools to achieve God contact, and 2) divine blessings to help us find the courage, faith, and strength to face what lies ahead.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda came to the West with a God-ordained mission: to bring teachings and techniques to help people attain higher consciousness. With wisdom and foresight, Master and the others in our line of gurus saw that a time of global upheaval was coming to the world. Out of compassion, Yoganandaji brought twofold gifts to help us deal with the impending suffering: 1) spiritual tools to achieve God contact, and 2) divine blessings to help us find the courage, faith, and strength to face what lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends, global upheaval is no longer only a vision of the future; it is already upon us. Hatred, violence, destruction, and warfare are rife. What can we do to help bring light into the world and reestablish peace and harmony in human hearts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power of prayer is one of the greatest instruments for positive change. And so I want to share what Yoganandaji taught about making our prayers more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/how-to-pray.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;how-to-pray&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;pray-from-your-heart&#34;&gt;Pray from Your Heart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to speak the inner language of prayer with calm, sincere words that spring from your heart. This is not an emotionally wrought state of mind, but one that has the quiet, open trust of a child lovingly asking his mother for help. This kind of intimate conversation with God unfailingly draws His response. Yogananda said, “When you pray to God, pray from your heart. Heartfelt prayer lends power to your thoughts. It focuses them, and centers them in God. Without sincerity, that focus will be lacking.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pray-with-confidence&#34;&gt;Pray with Confidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you pray, cast aside doubts and limiting thoughts. Offer your prayers, not with a sense of entitlement, but with quiet confidence and faith that God wants to help you. Yoganandaji told us, “Never pray with the attitude of a beggar. You are God’s child. Pray with utter confidence that He is listening. Utter faith, and love: these are the most important elements in prayer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pray-with-concentration&#34;&gt;Pray with Concentration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before praying, calm the heart and quiet the mind through meditation. Then, when your thoughts are still, concentrate at the spiritual eye and project your prayers with a laser-like focus. Don’t become tense, but with relaxed, one-pointed energy keep holding your prayer up to God. Do it repeatedly, until you begin to feel His presence. Master said, “God answers all prayers, but restless prayers He answers only a little bit. Get control over your mind. When you can pray with concentration, the Lord will know that you mean what you are saying. Then, He will answer you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-peace-and-harmony-prayer&#34;&gt;The Peace and Harmony Prayer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master gave one of his direct disciples the inspiration for a powerful tool for healing conflict: what we’ve come to call “The Peace and Harmony Prayer.” It can be used to heal discord between individuals and between nations. In this context, we encourage you to use it for global healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prayer is quite simple. Visualize the world bathed in light, and for one minute repeat the words: “Lord, fill this world with peace and harmony, peace and harmony.” Then visualize yourself in light, and pray for fifteen seconds: “Lord, fill me with peace and harmony, peace and harmony.” You can use this prayer, or any other that resonates with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friend, we invite you to join in prayer with your brothers and sisters in God throughout the world. With devotion, confidence, and concentration, let’s offer our united prayers for world peace. As Christ says in the Bible, “Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you. . . . And all things, whatsoever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye shall receive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and hope,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All the World is My Friend</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/all-the-world-is-my-friend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/all-the-world-is-my-friend/</guid>
      <description>We have two dear friends in Australia who are helping to lead Ananda’s growing work there. The man is a person with great openness of heart. When we spoke with them recently, his wife shared that when they’re in public, often a stranger will come up to him and ask, “Do I know you? It seems like we’ve met before.” In most cases they’ve never met, but there’s a quality about our friend that makes him feel familiar, even to strangers.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We have two dear friends in Australia who are helping to lead Ananda’s growing work there. The man is a person with great openness of heart. When we spoke with them recently, his wife shared that when they’re in public, often a stranger will come up to him and ask, “Do I know you? It seems like we’ve met before.” In most cases they’ve never met, but there’s a quality about our friend that makes him feel familiar, even to strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observed the same phenomenon when traveling with Swami Kriyananda. People would often approach him, not having a clue about who he was, and ask if they might sit with him and talk. If it was possible, Swamiji would listen to them as they shared their problems, and offer what advice he could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that people can feel so close and trusting with a stranger? There are several factors at play. First, as I mentioned about our Australian friend, his expansive heart quality touches people on some level. Through the practice of meditation and devotion, we naturally begin to project our love to everyone and everything around us. Others sense this love, and although it isn’t directed towards them personally, they are drawn to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A remarkable statement is attributed to Buddha: “We should try to love everyone we meet, because during the long journey of countless past incarnations, we have, indeed, known and loved each one.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/all-the-world-is-my-friend.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;all the world is my friend&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Strangers are also drawn to us when we radiate peace, a quality which develops naturally as we learn to be more centered in ourselves. Once in India with Swami Kriyananda, we were traveling together on a crowded plane. Every seat was taken, so Swamiji sat a few rows behind us. Upon landing, as we prepared to disembark through the front of the plane, we were instructed to allow those in the back rows to exit first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Swamiji passed by us in the aisle, he smiled and nodded. Though he was dressed in Western clothes, rather than his customary ochre robes, an aura of tranquility radiated from him. Two Indian gentlemen standing behind us had watched him greet us and asked who he was. After we explained, one of them commented, “India needs more men like that today.” Swamiji hadn’t spoken a single word, but they could feel the peace and joy of his consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the regular practice of meditation, we begin to change in ways of which we perhaps aren’t even aware. A greater capacity to love, unshakable peace, and deep joy under all circumstances—these qualities and many others become a part of who we are. Others may not know us or be aware of what is causing it, but they feel better in our presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American philosopher and writer, Ralph Waldo Emerson, said, “Who you are speaks so loudly, I can’t hear what you are saying.” The greatest good we can do in the world is to fill ourselves with those qualities—love, peace, harmony, acceptance—which humanity needs so deeply now. Though we need never speak a word, our God-attuned consciousness has a great power to uplift those around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a wonderful practice also to actively share love with everyone, whether you know them are not. Look for the discouraged face, or the lonely heart, and help them to feel that someone cares. The more we serve as channels for God’s love, the more we feel that love flowing through us. As Master said, “The channel is blessed by that which flows through it.” Let divine love flow through you unimpeded, and you will begin to awaken to your oneness with all life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda wrote a song for children that carries this message beautifully. The words are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;All the world is my friend
   When I learn how to share my love—
When I stretch out my hand and smile,
   When I live from above.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
