<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>light on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/light/</link>
    <description>Recent content in light on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/light/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Inner Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-inner-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-inner-light/</guid>
      <description>When Swami Kriyananda gave me the spiritual name, Jyotish, he said that it means “Inner Light.” Seeing light in the forehead during meditation has always been a cornerstone of my practice, which is probably why he chose this name for me.
Yogananda explains that one of the hidden teachings of the Bhagavad Gita is that each character, good and bad, symbolizes a different psychological trait within our psyche. Each quality we express in this life has been trained by the same teacher—Dronacharya (past habit).</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;When Swami Kriyananda gave me the spiritual name, Jyotish, he said that it means “Inner Light.” Seeing light in the forehead during meditation has always been a cornerstone of my practice, which is probably why he chose this name for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda explains that one of the hidden teachings of the Bhagavad Gita is that each character, good and bad, symbolizes a different psychological trait within our psyche. Each quality we express in this life has been trained by the same teacher—Dronacharya (past habit). Yogananda says, “No matter how many times a man suffers from very powerful attacks of sense-habits and restlessness-producing material desires, he finds that the meditation-born, occult soldiers of this life and past lives still come to his aid.” One of the greatest generals in the spiritual battle is Dhumata (Calm Inner Light), who arranges our pure discriminative faculties for spiritual battle. Though the Gita appears on its surface to be a mere philosophical discourse, when we meditate we can actually experience the realities it describes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people, even beginners, are able to see some kind of light in the forehead during meditation. This is because light is an innate aspect of our spiritual essence and is reawakened by any spiritual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When his mind becomes very calm and focused, the meditator can see the spiritual eye as a golden ring enclosing a deep-blue field with a silvery-white five-pointed star at its center. Seeing the spiritual eye clearly is challenging, and many people get disheartened if they can’t. Don’t get discouraged. Any perception of the inner light, even as only a kind of ephemeral opalescence, is extremely beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-inner-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the inner light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The inner light can deepen our meditation in many ways. Typically, we begin our meditation by praying to God and our line of gurus. Unfortunately, this is often done absentmindedly. It will be much more effective if you first take a few moments to center yourself and connect to the light and energy in the spiritual eye. Then, as you pray, clearly visualize each of the masters, especially their eyes. It adds even more power if you also feel and direct devotional gratitude to each of them from the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After your prayer, move on to the practice of watching the breath. First, feel the cool and warm currents of the inhalation and exhalation high in the nasal area. As you get calmer and more focused, feel that each breath is awakening and energizing the inner light in your forehead and prefrontal cortex of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the inner light has been awakened, it can become a kind of “home base.” When your mind wanders, bring it back to the inner light. For me, this is the best and fastest cure for restless thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When practicing other techniques, especially Kriya Yoga, use the inner light as a reference point, continually returning to it and strengthening its power. At the end of all techniques, focus there as deeply as possible. The spiritual eye is the gateway through which the deep meditator exits the body and enters Christ consciousness, experiencing his unity with everything in existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner light is useful also throughout the day. Swami Kriyananda advised that when relating to others, especially if giving advice, we should feel love and goodwill arising in the heart and being projected from our forehead to the spiritual eye of the other person. This will connect us soul-to-soul and make possible much deeper communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner light is, indeed, one of our greatest allies in our spiritual journey. In his great book of prayers, Whispers from Eternity, Yogananda wrote the following: “My eyes are enthralled, O Father, with the beauty of earthly flowers, with life’s passing scenes, and with the sailing, silent clouds. Everywhere, all I see hints at Thy hidden presence. Open that eye in me which sees only Thee. With that gaze may I behold Thee above, beneath, all around, within, and outside me. Teach me in all things to see only Thee. Open in me that eye which beholds everywhere Thy hidden but ever subtly reigning wonder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He further suggests, “This demand, especially, should be repeated mentally with deep concentration until the prayer-thought becomes fixed in your superconsciousness by the conviction born of deep faith.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May the inner light guide each of us back to our one true home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whose Dream is This?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/whose-dream-is-this/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/whose-dream-is-this/</guid>
      <description>A farmer was standing completely still amidst the wind-blown wheat in his field, deep in thought. His wife came rushing up, beside herself with grief, crying that their only son had just been killed by a cobra. When her husband made no reply, she blurted out, “You are heartless!”
“Forgive me, but you don’t understand,” the farmer replied. “Last night I dreamt that I was a king with seven sons, who all were bitten by cobras and died.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A farmer was standing completely still amidst the wind-blown wheat in his field, deep in thought. His wife came rushing up, beside herself with grief, crying that their only son had just been killed by a cobra. When her husband made no reply, she blurted out, “You are heartless!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Forgive me, but you don’t understand,” the farmer replied. “Last night I dreamt that I was a king with seven sons, who all were bitten by cobras and died. Now I am wondering whether I should grieve for my seven dead sons in that dream, or for my one son who has died in this dream we are dreaming now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our life’s experiences, with all their joys and sorrows, mesmerize us with a sense of their undeniable reality. Yet, in truth, everything is only a thought in the mind of God. Paramhansa Yogananda (who related the story above) explains it this way: “This world seems real to you only because God dreamed you into existence along with His cosmic dream. You are a part of His dream. If, at night, you dream that you bump your head against a wall, you may get an imaginary pain in your head. The moment you awake, however, you realize that there was no wall there to hurt you. The pain you experienced was in your mind, but not in your head!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/whose-dream-is-this.png&#34;  alt=&#34;whose dream is this&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“The same is true of this dream you are dreaming now. Wake up to the one Reality, God, and you will see that this earth life is just a show. It is nothing but shadows and light!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was a high school student, I was fortunate to have a wise teacher, Mrs. Gottlieb, for an English literature class. During the second semester, after she had gotten to know us better, she did a remarkable thing. Each of the thirty students in the class received a unique reading list of books for our individual growth and enjoyment. How we delighted in comparing one another’s lists and trying to figure out the particular message for us in every book!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a small way, this reflects Master’s statement that all of life’s experiences are for our “education and entertainment.” God dreams a particular dream for each of us, and arranges the events in life for our benefit. Though it’s often hard to see in the midst of suffering, His only motive is the deepest love and concern for our welfare and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we get caught up in the pleasure or pain in life, it’s good to remember that we’re not really in charge of our circumstances. We’re only playing our part in God’s dream—be it one of success or failure; health or sickness; love or rejection. With compassion and wisdom God gives to us the roles we are to play, perfectly designed for what we need to learn in this lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So try to release the anxiety over what has happened in the past, what choices you need to make now, and what the future holds. Let God take charge of your life, for, in fact, He already has. Try to see, in every person and every event in your life, the Dreamer behind the dream. Behind the light and shadows of life is only one reality: God’s joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with a selection from one of Master’s most beautiful poems, “When I Am Only a Dream”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I come to tell you all of Him,
And the way to encase Him in your bosom,
And of the discipline that brings His grace. . . .
And yet when I am only a dream to you,
I will come to remind you that you too are naught
But a dream of my Heavenly Beloved;
And when you know you are a dream,
As I know now,
We will be ever awake in Him.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;With love and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Return of the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-return-of-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-return-of-the-light/</guid>
      <description>“They’re coming! Our king and queen are coming! Ram, our beloved God, and Sita, our beautiful queen, are finally coming home!” Thus rejoiced the happy citizens of Ayodhya centuries ago when Ram and Sita returned. After long years away, the living light was returning to Ayodhya, and the people were placing lamps along the road to celebrate the occasion.
This event, central to the Ramayana (one of two great spiritual epics of India), has inspired people for thousands of years.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“They’re coming! Our king and queen are coming! Ram, our beloved God, and Sita, our beautiful queen, are finally coming home!” Thus rejoiced the happy citizens of Ayodhya centuries ago when Ram and Sita returned. After long years away, the living light was returning to Ayodhya, and the people were placing lamps along the road to celebrate the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event, central to the Ramayana (one of two great spiritual epics of India), has inspired people for thousands of years. Even today the victory of light over darkness fills a deep soul-longing in the heart of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diwali, the Festival of Light, is celebrated throughout India. Lights can be seen everywhere: strings of it decorating balconies and windows, candles placed in doorways and windows and on the altars of homes, and fireworks bursting like stars in the night sky. It’s not only in India that Diwali is celebrated. In New York City it is an official public holiday, given that there are over 200,000 people of Indian origin living there. Diwali is celebrated in the White House and, of course, in the U.K., which now has the first prime minister of Indian origin. The light of Diwali is, indeed, spreading around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, these outward displays are what might be called “social Diwali.” Spiritual Diwali is our daily return to the light in the spiritual eye, which can be experienced in every meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout long cycles of time, this theme—the triumph of light over darkness—has recurred in many different forms. For much of the Western world, it is celebrated at Christmas time, when the Christ was born. Each race and culture recognizes and celebrates light in its own special way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-return-of-the-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the return of the light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This holy season is a good time to open our hearts, to recognize and give thanks to the people and events that have been channels for God’s light and love to us. For many of our readers, our “Diwali” is the coming of Paramhansa Yogananda, often experienced when we first read Autobiography of a Yogi. Take a moment to reflect on how God has come into your life, and offer prayers of gratitude. Meditate for a while on all the people—family, friends, and teachers—who have been channels of Divine Mother’s love to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that Devi and I try to do in these weekly essays is to share little moments of inspiration that occur in our lives. As a Diwali gift we were given a small book, 365 Quotes by Gandhi, and I thought it would be nice to share with you a few rays of Gandhi’s light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You may never know what results come of your actions, but if you do nothing there will be no results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whenever you are confronted with an opponent, conquer him with love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The day the power of love overrules the love of power, the world will know peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Diwali talk that Swami Kriyananda gave in India in 2004, he urged everyone to fully open themselves to God’s light. That, however, is not enough. He went on to say that we should also strive to see the light of God in everyone we meet, and that we must actively spread God’s love to a world that desperately needs it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let each of us be a channel of light and live every day as if it were Diwali, a new dawning of the divine light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let It Shine</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-it-shine/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-it-shine/</guid>
      <description>Today is our last day in the Ananda community near Assisi. In a few days we’ll be flying to India to greet friends whom we haven’t seen for three years and to experience the expansion of Ananda’s work there. Our time in Assisi has been filled with blessings as we’ve shared together with our gurubhais the joy of a life in God.
It’s especially heartening to see the dedicated young people and families who are moving here.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Today is our last day in the Ananda community near Assisi. In a few days we’ll be flying to India to greet friends whom we haven’t seen for three years and to experience the expansion of Ananda’s work there. Our time in Assisi has been filled with blessings as we’ve shared together with our gurubhais the joy of a life in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s especially heartening to see the dedicated young people and families who are moving here. There seems to be a new generation of spiritually advanced souls being born who aren’t impressed with the razzle-dazzle of the world, but are seeking higher values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours was telling us about a group of children whose families have recently moved to Assisi and who have asked him to teach them meditation. One twelve-year-old girl told him that she’d been reading Swami Kriyananda’s &lt;em&gt;Art and Science of Raja Yoga&lt;/em&gt;, and had written a school paper on Patanjali’s &lt;em&gt;Yoga Sutras&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m very interested in the yamas and niyamas,” the girl told our friend, “and especially in the principle of non-lying. Before we moved here, when I was with my friends at school, I would pretend to be interested in clothes so that they would accept me. Now I realize after coming to Ananda that I was lying to myself, because that isn’t really who I am.” What a profound insight, something that most people never realize!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hearing this story reminded me of an experience I myself had had shortly after coming to Ananda Village in 1969. In the first days after arriving, I felt a great sense of freedom that I didn’t quite understand. Then one day the words clarified in my mind: “I don’t have to play games anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understood that I could be myself without trying to impress others according to their standards—ones that I didn’t share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a gift of the spiritual path: to discover and accept our own uniqueness, and let it determine the course of our life.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-it-shine.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let it shine&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a gift of the spiritual path: to discover and accept our own uniqueness, and let it determine the course of our life. As the young girl who was exploring non-lying discovered, self-honesty requires courage, but only then are we able to live our life with authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were speaking with another friend at Assisi, and told her about the man at Frankfurt airport that I wrote about in an earlier blog. He had looked very penetratingly at Jyotish and me and said, “You have to accept your own light so that other people have the courage to accept theirs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After hearing this story, Sahaja got a surprised look in her eyes, and got up and left the room. She soon returned holding a small carved wooden angel that she’d had on her altar for many years. It contained an excerpt from the writings of Marianne Williamson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our deepest fear is not that we are inadequate. Our deepest fear is that we are powerful beyond measure. It is our light, not our darkness, that most frightens us. We ask ourselves, “Who am I to be brilliant, gorgeous, talented, fabulous?” Actually, who are you not to be? You are a child of God. Your playing small does not serve the world. There is nothing enlightening about shrinking so that other people won’t feel insecure around you. We are all meant to shine, as children do. We were born to make manifest the glory of God that is within us. It’s not just in some of us; it’s in everyone. &lt;strong&gt;And as we let our own light shine, we unconsciously give other people permission to do the same&lt;/strong&gt;. As we are liberated from our own fear, our presence automatically liberates others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember that it isn’t for our own aggrandizement that we accept the divine light within us. As Christ told his followers: “Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father who is in heaven.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we can stand in humility, bathed in God’s light within and without, then we experience the truth of who we really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing you the joy of Self-discovery,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
