<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>self-discipline on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/self-discipline/</link>
    <description>Recent content in self-discipline on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/self-discipline/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is Essential</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-is-essential/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-is-essential/</guid>
      <description>When a famous Hollywood actor, Herb Jeffries, met Paramhansa Yogananda for the first time, he asked a question that resonates with many, though few have the courage to voice it:
“Religion seems to tell me you shan’t do this, and you must not do that. I’m not interested in what I can’t do. What I want to know is what I can do.”
Master’s reply was simple, profound, and fun. “Do you smoke?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;When a famous Hollywood actor, Herb Jeffries, met Paramhansa Yogananda for the first time, he asked a question that resonates with many, though few have the courage to voice it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Religion seems to tell me you shan’t do this, and you must not do that. I’m not interested in what I can’t do. What I want to know is what I can do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master’s reply was simple, profound, and fun. “Do you smoke?” he asked. “Yes,” came the reply. Master’s response surprised him: “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was, “Do you drink alcohol?” “Yes,” was the reply. Again Master said, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, “Do you enjoy the company of women?” “YES!” “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master ended by saying, “You may continue with all of these activities. But I must warn you, that if you take up this path, the desire to do them will fall away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji taught that it is what we do that makes us holy, not what we don’t do. His guru, Sri Yukteswar, said, “The vanished lives of all men are dark with many shames. . . . Everything in future will improve if you are making a spiritual effort now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only three things are absolutely essential: First is the desire to improve; second, the self-discipline to practice consistently; and finally, being open to help from a guide. Other qualities are important, but if these three are in place, the rest will follow naturally in its own time, just as the flowers of spring develop naturally into the fruits of fall.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-is-essential.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what is essential&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We are currently staying in an apartment in Delhi that we share with our dear friend Nayaswami Dhyana. She has recently taken up playing the esraj, a bowed Indian instrument. A person of great enthusiasm and energy, she personifies these three qualities. She has a strong desire to learn to play the esraj, partly for the sheer joy of playing music, but also so she can play the chants and songs of Paramhansa Yogananda and Swami Kriyananda as an aid to her attunement. Next, she practices two hours a day without fail. And, finally, she takes regular lessons from a teacher, Kashif, a master musician who himself started playing Indian classical music at age five and has practiced for hours each day for over forty years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, unbeknownst to Dhyana till now, we learned that Kashif’s father was a world-renowned musician who played for Yogananda when he was just fourteen years old. How strange are the graces of the guru and the threads of karma that weave together the tapestry of our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has either the time or inclination to make such a dedicated effort. Consistency is more important than quantity, especially when we are just beginning a new endeavor. Swami Kriyananda would sometimes tell people, “Just try to meditate five minutes each day. You spend that much time on your dental hygiene. You can certainly do the same for your mental and spiritual hygiene.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a teacher or guru is vital, he or she cannot and will not do the work for us. Our spiritual search will evolve so long as we make the effort. Day by day, year by year, a steady desire to improve plus consistent practice will produce magical results. Ultimately, all is accomplished by God’s grace, but it is our soul’s yearning accompanied by self-effort that draws that grace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda wrote, “Suppose you want riches. Will you sit in a room and wait for God to give them to you simply because you believe in Him? Hardly! You’ll work very hard to earn them. Why, then, expect salvation to come to you effortlessly, just because you believe?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we embark on the spiritual adventure to discover the endless potential within us, there is no magic wand that can substitute for our own effort. As Swami Kriyananda said, “Sometimes we just have to roll up our sleeves and get to work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steps to Happiness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for The Times of India, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called The Speaking Tree, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt;, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called &lt;em&gt;The Speaking Tree&lt;/em&gt;, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016. Friends encouraged me to share it once again. I, too, thought you might enjoy seeing it, even if for a second time. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;five-essential-steps-to-happiness&#34;&gt;Five Essential Steps to Happiness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “I once met a very successful and wealthy man, who said to me, ‘I’m disgustingly healthy, and disgustingly wealthy.’ ‘However,’ I replied, ‘you are not “disgustingly happy,” are you?’ He admitted he was not. Soon afterward, he became a student of this path.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness is something that everyone searches for but very few are able to find. Here are five key steps that lead to permanent happiness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must want to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to accept guidance to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to apply self-discipline in order to follow the guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to shift the focus to making inner, not outer, changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need truly to accept that both happiness and unhappiness are choices we make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look more closely at these five steps.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/steps-to-happiness.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;steps to happiness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t everyone want to be happy? Yes, and no. On a deep level, of course, everyone wants happiness. Paramhansa Yogananda said, in fact, that this desire is the fundamental motivation of every living thing. But on a conscious level, very few people seek happiness. Rather, they seek those things they think will make them happy: money, possessions, relationships, power, fame, etc. The problem with this way of thinking is that nothing outside ourself can ever make us happy. Only we have that power. Why not, then, seek happiness itself, rather than the will-o’-the-wisps that society dangles before us? Happiness lies within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to look for happiness in the right way. At first, many of the ingredients seem counterintuitive, or even counterproductive: non-attachment; serving others; letting go of instinctive patterns such as judgmental reactions, anger, jealousy, and the like. Finding happiness requires, in fact, that we transcend the very self that is doing the seeking. We need a guide who is more advanced to lead us along the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for self-discipline is obvious, but actually to train our will is not easy. Paramhansa Yogananda said, “True freedom is the ability to do what is good and right.” Swami Kriyananda’s mother once described a self-indulgent relative as having a “whim of steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to change ourself, again, should be obvious, but most people put much more energy into trying to change others or change their environment than into making inner changes. You will begin to improve only after you accept that the improvement you seek starts within. And that there, too, is where it ends. You can exert at most a gentle influence on others. Remember, they have the God-given right to their own free will. Never make your own happiness dependent upon the behavior of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a joy appropriate to every situation, even those we think of as unpleasant or disastrous. If you can once really grasp that happiness is a choice, you will have learned one of the most important lessons of all existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, true happiness is a spiritual quest, and comes from the expansion of consciousness. We must expand heart and mind until we break the chains of ego. These shackles keep us bound, and doom us to the vacillating waves of delusion that keep true happiness forever beyond our reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine happiness,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
