<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gratitude on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/gratitude/</link>
    <description>Recent content in gratitude on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/gratitude/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Art of Giving and Receiving</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-art-of-giving-and-receiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-art-of-giving-and-receiving/</guid>
      <description>Unpacking bulging suitcases after a long trip is something that most of us don’t approach with enthusiasm. As you probably know, Jyotish and I recently returned from nearly four months of traveling and sharing throughout Ananda centers in Europe and India. Upon arriving back home at Ananda Village, we were accompanied by our faithful traveling companions: two very large suitcases, two small suitcases, and a duffel bag.
As we began opening them and digging down layer upon layer like a pair of archeologists, we actually had a wonderful experience of “unearthing” beautiful presents given to us by friends along our journey.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Unpacking bulging suitcases after a long trip is something that most of us don’t approach with enthusiasm. As you probably know, Jyotish and I recently returned from nearly four months of traveling and sharing throughout Ananda centers in Europe and India. Upon arriving back home at Ananda Village, we were accompanied by our faithful traveling companions: two very large suitcases, two small suitcases, and a duffel bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we began opening them and digging down layer upon layer like a pair of archeologists, we actually had a wonderful experience of “unearthing” beautiful presents given to us by friends along our journey. Holding each gift, whether large or small, we tried to feel the love that was being expressed to us by the giver, and to send love back to each one of them in return. It was quite an uplifting experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Western world the holiday season has now begun, with people excitedly (and sometimes frantically) shopping for gifts and eagerly anticipating what they themselves might be receiving. Thus it seems like a good time to remind ourselves of the deeper aspect of giving and receiving. Ultimately, gifts are only symbols of love: sharing our heart’s love is the true essence of gift giving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember a difficult time in our life in 1976 during the first winter after the forest fire which had burnt Ananda to the ground. We hadn’t yet begun rebuilding, so we were all living in whatever dwellings we could find. Money was very tight for everyone. Jyotish and I had saved a little and had one hundred dollars in our checkbook with which to buy gifts for friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had planned our shopping outing, but when the day arrived, I realized that I’d made an error in the checkbook. Instead of one hundred, we had only ten dollars with which to buy presents. Rather than getting discouraged, we stayed positive and realized that we could buy the ingredients for chocolate chip cookies to give to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With love we made the cookies, and with love we placed two for each person in little plastic bags tied with ribbons. We felt happy in doing what we could, and in doing it with love. This was true for the whole community, and it was one of the best Christmases we’d ever had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda taught us another aspect of the art of giving. Being of an extremely generous nature, he was always gifting others for their birthdays, or weddings, or just because he wanted to share something beautiful. He told us, “When I’m choosing a gift for someone, I ask myself two questions: ‘Would it make the person happy to receive it?’ and ‘Would it make me happy to give it?’ If the answer is ‘Yes’ to both of these questions, then I’ll buy it and give it to them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji also said: “Whenever I find something especially beautiful or unusual, rather than thinking, ‘I must have this for myself,’ I buy it with the thought of giving it to someone else. This reduces any tendency towards attachment or greed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there is the art of receiving gifts. If we focus on ourselves and our own likes and dislikes, when we open a gift it’s easy to think, “It’s the wrong size,” or “I already have one,” or, “It’s not the color I wanted.” Instead, try to pause before opening a present, and feel the love and care that went into buying and wrapping it. Be grateful for the love that someone is offering you.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-art-of-giving-and-receiving.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the-art-of-giving-and-receiving&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On an even deeper level, try to see beyond the individual’s love to feel God’s love coming to you through your friend in the form of their present. Swamiji has given us a beautiful affirmation: “I give thanks to the giver behind each gift, and to the one Giver behind all that I receive. My gratitude rises with devotion’s incense to the throne of Omnipresence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, give with love and receive with gratitude, but also give with gratitude and receive with love. Experience this season of gift giving as an opportunity to go deeper in your awareness of God’s unifying love, which brings all things—giver and receiver—together as one. In a beautiful prayer, Swamiji says, “I thank Thee, Lord, for all Thy blessings. But most of all, I thank Thee for Thy love.” This is the greatest gift any of us can ever receive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and blessings in God, Christ, and Guru,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Steps to Happiness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/simple-steps-to-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/simple-steps-to-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Paramhansa Yogananda said that everyone in the world is motivated by the same twin desires: “to be happy and avoid pain.” Each of us can take some simple, and yet surprisingly effective strides toward that goal. Even a series of little steps can produce great changes if we apply them consistently.
The road to happiness starts by replacing bad habits with good ones. Many people have a tendency to focus primarily on physical habits such as diet and exercise.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said that everyone in the world is motivated by the same twin desires: “to be happy and avoid pain.” Each of us can take some simple, and yet surprisingly effective strides toward that goal. Even a series of little steps can produce great changes if we apply them consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road to happiness starts by replacing bad habits with good ones. Many people have a tendency to focus primarily on physical habits such as diet and exercise. But since we have a body, mind, and soul, we need to address all three aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda wrote, “During an interview with newspapermen Master prescribed the following rules as a good daily regimen for all: ‘Morning and evening sit in introspective silence thinking of your most important engagement with the soul within. Exercise fifteen minutes. Walk thirty minutes. Study one hour. Meditate one hour and a half. Smile from within all hours.’”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/simple-steps-to-happiness.png&#34;  alt=&#34;simple-steps-to-happiness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A recent study at the University of California at Berkeley revealed some very helpful and hopeful information. Working with more than 70,000 people involved with an initiative called “The Big Joy Project,” scientists found that you can quickly gain a 25% boost in your happiness level by consciously doing “micro-acts of joy.” The study shows that these “micro-acts” led to increased feelings of hope, optimism, and happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works this way: Every day for seven consecutive days, do a small act to boost your emotional well-being. For example, make a gratitude list or keep a gratitude journal. Another practice would be to visit a sick friend or do a nice gesture for someone you know, or even better, for a stranger. Yet another micro-act would be to reframe something you think of as negative into a positive perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the benefit of this practice comes from the conscious decision to make a plan for the week, and then to carry out your daily act of “micro-joy.” What better time to start this than the day after Thanksgiving? Take a few moments right now to think about those things for which you are grateful. Write a few notes of gratitude to those who have helped or uplifted you during the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now make a plan for next week of seven daily acts of micro-joy. Doing this will help us reprogram our mental habits. Paramhansa Yogananda said, “Don’t expect to go to heaven unless you carry a portable heaven within your heart every day.” He also gave this counsel: “If you find your thoughts carried away, little by little, as prisoners of temptation, then you should train your armies of self-control. Seek good company, take right care of the body, and keep your thoughts busy with wonder and bliss of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most important, is a daily practice of deep meditation. Sometimes meditators can become discouraged by a lack of experiences. But Master said, “Do not grieve because you do not see light or images in meditation. If you go deep into the perception of bliss you will find there the actual presence of God. Seek the Whole, not a part.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we do our part and make an effort, God will reach out to help us. One time Master blessed a disciple who was having a hard time financially. The anxiety-ridden student asked Master how he could stay so calm in the face of troubles. The Master looked at him intently and said, “Remember, the same Father who protects me, protects you. He is our common Father.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replacing bad habits with good ones is important, but the greatest thing we can do to improve happiness is to bring God into every aspect of life, and offer everything we have and are into His light. Faith and gratitude are the cures for all our ills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joyful gratitude,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Matters in the End</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-matters-in-the-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-matters-in-the-end/</guid>
      <description>A poignant quote from Buddha came to us recently: “In the end only three things matter. How much you loved, how gently you lived, and how gracefully you let go of things not meant for you.”
Often we live locked up in self-focused goals and desires. Yet, as we depart from this incarnation, goals must be relinquished and desires discarded. Those desires we fail to abandon will inevitably pull us back into another incarnation, and another, and another.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A poignant quote from Buddha came to us recently: “In the end only three things matter. How much you loved, how gently you lived, and how gracefully you let go of things not meant for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we live locked up in self-focused goals and desires. Yet, as we depart from this incarnation, goals must be relinquished and desires discarded. Those desires we fail to abandon will inevitably pull us back into another incarnation, and another, and another. The solution is disarmingly simple: Expand our heart’s energy by directing it toward God and the benefit of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda explained that the heart is the center of the primordial feeling element (chitta). He added that we perceive and respond to the world primarily through feeling rather than intellect. Ultimately, to find liberation we must still the mind and, especially, neutralize the whirlpools of likes and dislikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy in the “switching station” of the heart is constantly seeking fulfillment. This quest can lead us toward worldly attachments and sensory experiences, or towards the divine joy of God. When our energy is funneled downward and outward, we set ourselves up for anxiety and disappointment. As Yogananda put it, “Delusion always breaks its promises.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best strategies to channel the energy positively is to think of the welfare of others. When we embarked on Ananda’s work in San Francisco, we started a small restaurant/bookstore. The manager, a single woman, had to close the store late at night and then take a bus through a very run-down area of town. Often sharing the bus with drunks and drug addicts, she dreaded the nightly ride home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As she explained her dilemma to Swami Kriyananda, he first explored the standard solutions: Could she drive home? Could she take a taxi? Could someone else drive her? All of these proved either impractical or too expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami said, “All right, then, I suggest that you do this: When you get on the bus, pick out one person who appears to need help and pray for him the whole way home. If that person gets off, choose another.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later she told Swamiji that the bus ride home had transformed into her favorite part of the day. Her prayers for others had shifted her heart’s energy from isolation and fear to connection and joy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-matters-in-the-end.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what matters in the end&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Love is fundamental, but almost as important is gratitude. By being grateful for the circumstances and people in our lives, we open a positive flow of energy from the heart up to the spiritual eye. It’s virtually impossible to harbor negativity when we’re feeling grateful. We don’t have to express it outwardly—we can just silently allow the feeling of thankfulness to reverberate in the heart. Begin by being grateful for things that are easy to accept. Then train yourself also to feel appreciation for challenging situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda wrote, “Teach me to look upon all that happens in my life with a pleased, interested attitude, that at the end of each episode, no matter how sad or difficult, I may exclaim: “Ah, that was a good show, full of thrills, suspense, and excitement! I am happy to have seen it, and I have learned much from it for my own benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we find it challenging to hold such a high attitude, we can at least strive toward it. Some years ago, while experiencing a difficult period, I wrote an affirmation to help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I am grateful for my life exactly as it is.
I am thankful for this day;
I welcome every hour.
Thank you, God. Thank you, God.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have the potential to expand our heart and let it become a channel for the infinite love of God. If we do our best, we can face our final review and say, “I loved greatly, lived gently, and gracefully let go of those things that kept me from Thee, Lord.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In love and gratitude,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
