<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>joy on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/joy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in joy on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/joy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>In Joy I Live</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/in-joy-i-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/in-joy-i-live/</guid>
      <description>Anyone who has tried to have a regular practice of meditation knows that it’s no easy thing. Creating time in the midst of daily demands, leaving behind worries and preoccupations, summoning up enthusiasm every day: All of these and more are challenges we all face.
What I’d like to do is to walk you through a three-step process that may help you find renewed focus, energy, and enthusiasm for meditation.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has tried to have a regular practice of meditation knows that it’s no easy thing. Creating time in the midst of daily demands, leaving behind worries and preoccupations, summoning up enthusiasm every day: All of these and more are challenges we all face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’d like to do is to walk you through a three-step process that may help you find renewed focus, energy, and enthusiasm for meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step One:&lt;/strong&gt; Before sitting down to meditate, become aware of the thoughts and feelings that are running through your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Are you feeling rushed, and thinking, “I’ll get this over quickly”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Decide how much time you have, and be fully present for each moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Is your body feeling tense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Try doing some pranayamas or a few yoga asanas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Are you feeling discouraged, or that you’ll never be able to meditate deeply?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: This feeling of failure is probably present in everyone who takes up meditation. In the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna says to Arjuna: “But if you cannot think of Me, then give Me your intention.” Begin each meditation with the thought, “Today I give You the best effort of which I am capable.” Don’t look back or forward, but just offer God your intention to try your best today.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/in-joy-i-live.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;in joy i live&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step Two:&lt;/strong&gt; As you begin to meditate, immediately bring your full, focused energy to the spiritual eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Does your mind quickly revert to daily activities and problems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Start with repeating or chanting with concentration the words from Master’s poem, “Samadhi”: “From joy I came, for joy I live, in sacred joy I melt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Do you find that when you make an intense effort your body gets tense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t look for results; remember, simply, that this is your time with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Become aware of where you’re holding tension, then inhale, tense, and consciously relax those body parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Do you hold the subconscious thought that you’ll never achieve your goals for meditation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Don’t look for results; remember, simply, that this is your time with God. In his book Secrets of Meditation, Swami Kriyananda writes: “The secret of meditation is to pray with deep faith—not as an outsider to heaven, but as one whose true, eternal home is heaven.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also writes: “The secret of meditation is affirming that you already are those high truths towards which you aspire: inner peace, divine love, and perfect joy.” Try to feel that everything you are seeking is already within you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step Three:&lt;/strong&gt; After you finish meditation, throughout the day try to hold on to the feelings of peace that you experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Do you leap into activities as soon as you finish meditation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Build a bridge between meditation and activity. Consciously do simple activities, such as making your bed, during which you keep your mind calm and centered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: As challenges arise during the day, do you fall into negative emotions and reactions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Keep the peace of meditation as a constant reference point throughout the day. If you feel yourself getting agitated, immediately try to direct your energy to the spiritual eye until you feel calmness restored. You can also bring to mind again Master’s words: “From joy I came, for joy I live, in sacred joy I melt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we walk the spiritual path, it’s hard to see changes in ourselves, but that doesn’t mean we aren’t growing. Once Swamiji was discussing the progress that various Ananda members had made. Almost unaware of what I was saying, I blurted out, “I don’t see that I’ve changed all that much.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With great intensity, he said, “How can you say that? You’re an entirely different person than when you came.” This is true of anyone who sincerely tries their best to meditate and follow the spiritual path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s meditate with joy, live in joy, and eagerly anticipate the day when we melt in joy once more. And in our love for God, offer to Him the fruits of our efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behind the Stern Facade</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/behind-the-stern-facade/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/behind-the-stern-facade/</guid>
      <description>We recently heard a remarkable story about Sri Yukteswar. Many devotees have a little difficulty relating to him, since he seems a bit forbidding. Perhaps it is because in Autobiography of a Yogi, Paramhansa Yogananda writes about him in his role as both teacher and disciplinarian, a job he took very seriously, especially knowing that he was preparing Master for a world-changing role.
But the grandson of Tulsi Bose, Master’s close friend, told us that when Sri Yukteswar visited their home he was completely different.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We recently heard a remarkable story about Sri Yukteswar. Many devotees have a little difficulty relating to him, since he seems a bit forbidding. Perhaps it is because in Autobiography of a Yogi, Paramhansa Yogananda writes about him in his role as both teacher and disciplinarian, a job he took very seriously, especially knowing that he was preparing Master for a world-changing role.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/behind-the-stern-facade.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;behind the stern facade&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the grandson of Tulsi Bose, Master’s close friend, told us that when Sri Yukteswar visited their home he was completely different. He was a kind, lovable, grandfatherly figure who usually had sweets to offer to the many children who gathered around him. I, myself, had an experience where I felt his sweetness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were about to begin a Kriya Initiation in Chennai, India, and the pictures on the altar were all garlanded. As I was bowing to each of our Masters, I mentally prayed to Sri Yukteswar to help me relate to him more deeply. The instant the prayer formed in my mind, the garland around his photo fell off, and I was given the opportunity to lovingly re-garland him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is the remarkable story related to us by Nayaswami Aditya, our center leader in Pune:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bhuvan Pal Singh joined the online classes in Pune during the first wave of Covid and became a Kriyaban. I immediately recognized him as someone who felt like an old friend. He was sincere, with deep yearning and humility, and asked many questions to refine his spiritual practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bhuvan’s lifelong yearning had been to leave everything and go to the Himalayas, but he found himself supporting his entire extended family of thirty-five people, something he did quite happily and very well. During the first wave of the pandemic he took retirement from his successful corporate career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Bhuvan began his Kriya practice, he was diagnosed with a rare malignant cancer of the muscles of his right forearm. Expert advice from the best doctors in the country informed him that little could be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With tears in his eyes Bhuvan related this story: “One day I was undergoing a PET scan to assess the spread of the tumor in my body and found myself alone in a hospital room. As I sat there I prayed to the Masters, “I am feeling very alone.” I instantly had a vision of the form of Sri Yukteswarji in front of me. As his life-size form slowly moved towards me, it shrunk in size until he became very small and entered into my body through my spiritual eye. From within I heard Swami Sri Yukteswarji say, ‘Bhuvan, don’t feel alone or afraid, for I am in every cell of your body.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bhuvanji continued his daily Kriya practice, and although he followed the suggested treatments, his health deteriorated over the months and on 26 January 2022 he left his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days later, his wife, Anupama, had the following experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was awakened early one morning by the sound of the main door of our house being unfastened. As I opened my eyes, I saw a bright yellow light falling on the door, and curious to see what this light was, I moved towards it. Just then I heard and saw my husband, in physical form, seated in the living room in meditative pose, his gaze uplifted. He said to me, ‘Anupama, don’t move. I’m exiting now.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I stood still, and watched my husband exit into that light. A couple of hours after this experience I got a call from my niece in New Delhi. She told me that the previous night she had dreamt that she saw a bright yellow light fall on our house, especially on the main door. In the dream she saw her uncle Bhuvan enter that light.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anupama has kindly given Nayaswami Aditya permission, and we thank her for allowing us to share this sacred experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Swamiji’s passing Devi and I had a “Nadi” reading from an ancient book of prophecy. During that reading we were told that Yogananda was watching out for us minute by minute and second by second. This applies to all of us who have opened our hearts to this great line of masters. Yoganandaji, as Swami Kriyananda explained, was a Blissavatar (incarnation of divine joy). Yoganandaji described Sri Yukteswar as a gyanavatar (incarnation of wisdom). In fact, in God’s light all His qualities merge into one, and in our hour of need we, too, will find that God’s light is in every cell of our body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Sacred Gift</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-sacred-gift/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-sacred-gift/</guid>
      <description>Devi wrote recently about our pilgrimage to sacred sites in Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore. On our last day in Serampore a very special gift was given to us.
This city is on the banks of the Ganges and was the location of Sri Yukteswar’s ashram, where Paramhansa Yogananda spent the better part of ten years in training with his beloved guru. During that period, Yogananda often visited the family of his elder brother, Anantalal Ghosh, who also resided in Serampore.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi wrote recently about our pilgrimage to sacred sites in Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore. On our last day in Serampore a very special gift was given to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This city is on the banks of the Ganges and was the location of Sri Yukteswar’s ashram, where Paramhansa Yogananda spent the better part of ten years in training with his beloved guru. During that period, Yogananda often visited the family of his elder brother, Anantalal Ghosh, who also resided in Serampore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had lunch with members of the Ghosh family. We have known Durlov and his son Ishan for years, having first met them many years ago with Swami Kriyananda. At the end of the meal we withdrew to a private patio where they presented us with an extremely precious plate that had been in the family for well over one hundred years. Here is a description given to us by Ishan of this sacred relic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The object which we gave you is a plate made of stone. My father heard from his grandmother, that is, the wife of Anantalal Ghosh, that this plate was there when she was married. That means it must have been bought by either Guruji’s parents or someone else in the family in or before the year Anantalal Ghosh was married. Plates like this are usually used in Indian families for offering food to the gods. Usually, they rest at family altars, and so was the case with this plate as well. However, when Paramhansa Yogananda became a sanyasi, it was not possible for him to accept food at home, since all of the kitchen plates were somehow in touch with meat or fish. Therefore, he was offered food instead on plates from the altar; the plates in which food has been offered to the gods; the plate which we gave you. When Paramhansa Yogananda came back to India, he had his meals on these plates as always. This plate has been there in our family for more than a hundred years, and we gifted it to you since we feel that more people should have the opportunity to drink from its spiritual vibrations. We are so pleased that the gods gave us the opportunity to forward such priceless spiritual vibrations into your hands. We are so pleased that you accepted it with such deep reverence and joy.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-sacred-gift.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a sacred gift&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Presently the plate rests on the lap of a statue of Master that sits in our meditation room in Delhi. We will soon place it along with other sacred objects where visitors and pilgrims can meditate and feel the holy vibrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plate also embodies a deep spiritual lesson for us all. Food is a symbol of the gift of life from Divine Mother, and Yogananda would only eat if the food had first been offered back to God. But everything is a gift from Divine Mother, and God-offering should be applied to all aspects of life. Yogananda spoke of this truth poetically in his beautiful poem “God! God! God!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first rise from slumber, the day ahead should be offered to God. When we break our fast, we should be aware that the very food we eat is a form of Divine Mother. If, during our working hours, the spotlight of our mind ever keeps returning to God, our work can be transformed into sacred service. Giving God our worries, our memories, and our dreams transforms the mundane into the sacred. Ultimately, it is our love above all that must be purified through offering it to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually, all that we “own,” and all that we think we “are,” must be offered into God’s light. He will receive our offerings, purify them, and then playfully join us in a life free from attachment to the delusion of “I” and “mine.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t is interesting that the essence of the spiritual path is somehow magically condensed into a single sacred plate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
