<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>love on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/love/</link>
    <description>Recent content in love on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/love/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Yearning of the Soul</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-yearning-of-the-soul/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-yearning-of-the-soul/</guid>
      <description>Every soul yearns for the light, and will find a way to grow toward it. No matter what the obstacles, the soul will find its way upward just as a blade of grass will sometimes grow through a slab of concrete.
What follows is taken from the journal of a young woman who lives in an area where it is nearly impossible for young women to find a quality education. For the sake of safety we will call her by her initial, S.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Every soul yearns for the light, and will find a way to grow toward it. No matter what the obstacles, the soul will find its way upward just as a blade of grass will sometimes grow through a slab of concrete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is taken from the journal of a young woman who lives in an area where it is nearly impossible for young women to find a quality education. For the sake of safety we will call her by her initial, S. Like that blade of grass, she found her way through difficult circumstances to join the online version of Ananda’s Living Wisdom High School led Nayaswami Nitai and other teachers. These excerpts, used with her permission, describe a small slice of her journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; Today at 6:45 I had received an email from Sir Nitai. He asked me to introduce myself and how I found this school. Now it’s 12:17, and I am sending my response with so much anticipation. I will keep these words in my mind: “I won’t lose my heart and hope. I will remain hopeful since life without hope means nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-yearning-of-the-soul.png&#34;  alt=&#34;the-yearning-of-the-soul&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 1:06 p.m. Yay! Hurray! I can’t express how excited I am. I am going to have an interview with Sir Nitai and Mrs. Kathy tomorrow at 10 a.m. my time. Although I am so much excited, I am not sure what will happen after the interview. Ah, if only I could go into the future, I would have loved to see what it looks like. Am I ever going to achieve my goals? Well, I hope so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 9:50 a.m. I am a little anxious because I really want to get into school again. I miss how amazing it feels to study with passion. I better get even more ready for the interview. Just three minutes I have to calm my nerves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 10:50 a.m. I can’t believe it; my interview was beyond my imagination. I loved how they made me feel valued. Oh my God, it was wonderful. Well, it seems unbelievable, but it is true: “I GOT INTO THE SCHOOL.” Haha, it’s amazing! It seems like I was wrong that I don’t deserve good things. Maybe good things will come eventually. I should start working on my application. P.S. My little sister will also join the Life Skill Course. It is wonderful to see her happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 12:39 p.m. I GOT ACCEPTED! Living Wisdom will indeed help me turn my dreams into reality. I am crying because of pure joy. This is a great feeling. I will work really hard because I want to make my sweet mother proud and fulfill my cute siblings’ wishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 8:50 p.m. Before my first-ever class at school, I was invited to the staff meeting. I really wanted to meet my teachers! Ah, this internet is so frustrating! This package of internet is really cruel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;27th Feb. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 12:23. I really want to cry. Not only did I get into school, but I am also going to receive internet support. I am grateful for everything. My classes are absolutely perfect! I love spending the whole day doing my homework, actively engaging with what I am learning, and my extracurricular activities. Unlike the past, everything is fun now. It looks like I had truly lost my mind back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15th April 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; It is very interesting. I was always yearning for graduation but now I don’t want to finish school sooner. I have a meeting with my dearest Sir Nitai about future plans. I know he will figure out a way for me to continue my studies. I am so grateful. Evening: I am applying to UoP. I am not very anxious, maybe because I believe good things will happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd June 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; Last night I had my Self-Expression and Communication class. My teacher and classmates were bidding me farewell. They said things they had observed in me—I had never known I had those qualities. It is time to step into the next chapter of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15th June 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; The first day of college class was indeed amazing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30th June 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; My dear Mrs. Mirabai and her kind husband helped me buy a laptop. As the previous owner of this laptop said, this laptop had brought him so much luck. Haha, I hope it does the same for me. It is more convenient and is very helpful. I am thanking you in my heart, my dear teacher. I hope you will feel how much you made me happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14th July 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; 8:22 a.m. Today is a rare day that I open my eyes to the golden rays of the beautiful sun rather than starting my day with sharp words from a certain family member. Then, I saw an email that was unbelievable yet true. I was asked if I would like to work as a teacher assistant in World Religions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st August 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; I received a message from Aryavan if I wanted to join EFL teacher training. I was more than interested in joining. I really want to discover why my teachers were working more on us to reach our highest potential than on the curriculum. At the same time, students in our schools have more wisdom. It is very intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6th Sept. 2023:&lt;/strong&gt; First day of school. Now I come back to school as an assistant teacher. It is very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;31st Jan. 2024:&lt;/strong&gt; I got my first salary, $412. It feels so good to be financially independent. I will try even harder. I spend some of it on buying new jackets for all of my siblings and a dress for my mother. I also ordered pizza and chicken wings as per my little brother’s wish. I gifted a few things to my little, innocent, orphan students. So funny, but they wished I keep earning money so that I could spend it on them. I plan to save the remaining part of my salary for my education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7th Feb. 2024:&lt;/strong&gt; It has been a year now. Everything changes it is true. My life one year ago was much different from now. I am a college freshman with a CGPA of 3.95 so far. I volunteered to work as an English teacher in an online school to help my country’s sisters. At the same time, I am in the EFL training program and working together with Mrs. Kathy in the World Religions class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a little longer than our normal blogs, but I doubt that you’ve minded. I’m sure that you’ve felt, as I did, that God’s love and light have found their way into your heart and soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the love of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Can We Find Love?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/where-can-we-find-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/where-can-we-find-love/</guid>
      <description>We heard an amazing story last year when we were visiting the Ananda Community in Assisi. A friend of ours, with whom we were staying, told us that she had a beloved dog who had recently passed away at the age of fifteen. Her heart was still grieving for the loss of her dear friend and companion.
One rainy night while we were there, we heard a whining and scratching outside their house by the compost pile.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We heard an amazing story last year when we were visiting the Ananda Community in Assisi. A friend of ours, with whom we were staying, told us that she had a beloved dog who had recently passed away at the age of fifteen. Her heart was still grieving for the loss of her dear friend and companion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One rainy night while we were there, we heard a whining and scratching outside their house by the compost pile. When our friend went out with a flashlight to see what was happening, she saw a starving, injured little dog who had gotten caught on the wire fence. Approaching him to help, she startled the abandoned creature, and he tore himself loose and ran away toward the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our friend got into her car hoping, even though the night was dark and rainy, to find the poor puppy. Eventually she spotted him, and pulled over to the side of the road, but with each step she took toward him, he backed farther away. Finally, in desperation, she prayed to her beloved dog who had passed away, “Please let this little one trust me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost miraculously, the little fellow immediately turned and ran to her. Looking at her with beseeching eyes, he allowed her to pick him up and take him home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they got to the house, she fed him with dog food left over from her former pet. She was amazed to see that he ate three times the normal amount. From then on, he refused to leave her sight. A year later when we returned, we saw a plump, energetic, happy little beagle with a sleek coat. He was entirely devoted to our friend who had showered him with food, good care, and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How mysterious are God’s ways! Praying to a dog for help?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love is more than a mere human feeling. As the great saints tell us, God’s love is the very fabric from which all creation is made. In one of Swami Kriyananda’s beautiful songs, “What Is Love?,” he says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;What is love? Is it only ours?
Or does love whisper in the flowers?
     Surely we, children of this world,
Could not love by our own powers.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/where-can-we-find-love.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;where-can-we-find-love&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Many years ago before I came to Ananda and took up Master’s path, I had an interesting experience which took me some time to fully understand. It happened during my last semester of college, when I had just begun reading Autobiography of a Yogi. One sunny spring afternoon, I was sitting on a couch in the living room in the apartment I shared with several friends. No one else was at home, so the place was quiet and still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I gazed out the window at the sunlight on the trees, I fell into a sort of reverie. I started thinking how fortunate I had been to be surrounded by a loving family and friends. I began to visualize each one of them—parents, brother, cousins, aunts, uncles, teachers, and good friends—and feel the love that they had given me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the image of each person faded into the next, my awareness became increasingly expanded and still, until all I could feel was that I was bathed in light and love. As I said, it took me time to understand that it had been God loving me through all of those forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a wonderful letter from Swami Kriyananda to a devotee, he wrote: “If we feel God’s love in someone’s love for us, then that is right and good. I remember once in India telling the woman saint, Ananda Moyi Ma, how much I and others in America loved her. Her reply was, ‘There is no love except God’s love.’ . . . Ultimately, the only important thing you can do in life is love God. The only fact that truly matters in life is that God loves you. . . . The solution to our worries is love, and more love—divine love, not egoic love. . . . As the Bible says, ‘Perfect love casteth out fear.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of a world in turmoil, let’s remember that God’s love for us—in fact, simply God’s love—is the only important thing, the only reality. Whether it’s expressed through the love of another person, through a pet, or through a challenging situation, look behind the surface, and see God’s love. Let it saturate your heart, and then share it with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where do we find love? If we have eyes to see, everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the One in all,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dual Nature of Divine Love</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-dual-nature-of-divine-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-dual-nature-of-divine-love/</guid>
      <description>Some years ago Jyotish and I arrived at Ananda’s community near Assisi, Italy, where Swami Kriyananda was then residing. We hadn’t seen him for many months, and were eagerly looking forward to having some relaxed time with him to enjoy the blessings of his company.
Much to my disappointment, however, it was evident that Swamiji was very busy with writing a new book and teaching many programs. My heart sank as I realized that my dream of spending personal time with him probably wasn’t going to happen on that trip.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Some years ago Jyotish and I arrived at Ananda’s community near Assisi, Italy, where Swami Kriyananda was then residing. We hadn’t seen him for many months, and were eagerly looking forward to having some relaxed time with him to enjoy the blessings of his company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much to my disappointment, however, it was evident that Swamiji was very busy with writing a new book and teaching many programs. My heart sank as I realized that my dream of spending personal time with him probably wasn’t going to happen on that trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My disappointment, however, turned out to be an opportunity for an important spiritual lesson. Sensing my letdown, Swamiji took the time to give me this piece of advice: “No one is special to me, Devi. I’m not even special to myself.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-dual-nature-of-divine-love.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the dual nature of divine love&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Was he saying that he was cold, aloof, and too busy to be bothered with the emotional needs of others? Not at all. Quite the opposite, in fact: Second only to his longing for union with God was his compassion and desire to help others spiritually. Even as he was speaking those words, I felt great love flowing from him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divine love is impersonal, because it is universally rather than individually rooted. And it is also personal, because it touches each of us uniquely according to our own nature. This is what Swamiji was trying to convey to me when seeing my disappointment: To feel God’s love for us we need to open ourselves to a greater reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the chapter in Autobiography of a Yogi in which Master meets his guru, Sri Yukteswar, we find a remarkable demonstration of this impersonal/personal kind of love. Though they had never met before in that lifetime, Master recognized his guru immediately and fell at his feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“O my own, you have come to me!” Sri Yukteswar repeated again and again. “How many years I have waited for you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some time in eloquent silence, Sri Yukteswar said, “I give you my unconditional love.” Master goes on to write, “Precious words! A quarter-century elapsed before I had another auricular proof of his love. His lips were strange to ardor; silence became his oceanic heart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sri Yukteswar told his new disciple: “Ordinary love is selfish, darkly rooted in desires and satisfactions. Divine love is without condition, without boundary, without change. The flux of the human heart is gone forever at the transfixing touch of pure love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we tune in to this eternal, unconditional love? First, we must find it in meditation as we still the emotional tumult of the heart and the restless thoughts of the mind. In tranquility of heart and mind, God’s love slowly makes itself felt within and around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also important to think not of how much love you are receiving, but how much you are giving. Yogananda said that the channel is blessed by what flows through it. By striving to be a channel for divine love to others, we, in turn, become filled with its blessings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his years with Master at Mt. Washington, Swamiji used to pray, “Teach me to love you as you love me.” One day, Master looked at him penetratingly and said, “How can the little cup expect to hold the whole ocean of love?” In other words, to truly feel the vastness of divine love, we need to expand the boundaries of our heart to embrace God’s infinite nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So divine love is both personal and impersonal, because it touches our unique soul nature, while at the same time existing beyond our individuality. Master captures this dual nature beautifully in his description of the woman saint, Ananda Moyi Ma: “The closest of dear friends, she made one feel, yet an aura of remoteness was ever around her—the paradoxical isolation of Omnipresence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a wonderful saying that in every human heart there is a God-shaped hole. However much we try to fill it with other expressions of love, it remains empty until we fill it with God’s presence. Then alone do we find the fulfillment we are seeking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With loving friendship in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All the World is My Friend</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/all-the-world-is-my-friend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/all-the-world-is-my-friend/</guid>
      <description>We have two dear friends in Australia who are helping to lead Ananda’s growing work there. The man is a person with great openness of heart. When we spoke with them recently, his wife shared that when they’re in public, often a stranger will come up to him and ask, “Do I know you? It seems like we’ve met before.” In most cases they’ve never met, but there’s a quality about our friend that makes him feel familiar, even to strangers.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We have two dear friends in Australia who are helping to lead Ananda’s growing work there. The man is a person with great openness of heart. When we spoke with them recently, his wife shared that when they’re in public, often a stranger will come up to him and ask, “Do I know you? It seems like we’ve met before.” In most cases they’ve never met, but there’s a quality about our friend that makes him feel familiar, even to strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observed the same phenomenon when traveling with Swami Kriyananda. People would often approach him, not having a clue about who he was, and ask if they might sit with him and talk. If it was possible, Swamiji would listen to them as they shared their problems, and offer what advice he could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that people can feel so close and trusting with a stranger? There are several factors at play. First, as I mentioned about our Australian friend, his expansive heart quality touches people on some level. Through the practice of meditation and devotion, we naturally begin to project our love to everyone and everything around us. Others sense this love, and although it isn’t directed towards them personally, they are drawn to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A remarkable statement is attributed to Buddha: “We should try to love everyone we meet, because during the long journey of countless past incarnations, we have, indeed, known and loved each one.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/all-the-world-is-my-friend.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;all the world is my friend&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Strangers are also drawn to us when we radiate peace, a quality which develops naturally as we learn to be more centered in ourselves. Once in India with Swami Kriyananda, we were traveling together on a crowded plane. Every seat was taken, so Swamiji sat a few rows behind us. Upon landing, as we prepared to disembark through the front of the plane, we were instructed to allow those in the back rows to exit first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Swamiji passed by us in the aisle, he smiled and nodded. Though he was dressed in Western clothes, rather than his customary ochre robes, an aura of tranquility radiated from him. Two Indian gentlemen standing behind us had watched him greet us and asked who he was. After we explained, one of them commented, “India needs more men like that today.” Swamiji hadn’t spoken a single word, but they could feel the peace and joy of his consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the regular practice of meditation, we begin to change in ways of which we perhaps aren’t even aware. A greater capacity to love, unshakable peace, and deep joy under all circumstances—these qualities and many others become a part of who we are. Others may not know us or be aware of what is causing it, but they feel better in our presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American philosopher and writer, Ralph Waldo Emerson, said, “Who you are speaks so loudly, I can’t hear what you are saying.” The greatest good we can do in the world is to fill ourselves with those qualities—love, peace, harmony, acceptance—which humanity needs so deeply now. Though we need never speak a word, our God-attuned consciousness has a great power to uplift those around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a wonderful practice also to actively share love with everyone, whether you know them are not. Look for the discouraged face, or the lonely heart, and help them to feel that someone cares. The more we serve as channels for God’s love, the more we feel that love flowing through us. As Master said, “The channel is blessed by that which flows through it.” Let divine love flow through you unimpeded, and you will begin to awaken to your oneness with all life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda wrote a song for children that carries this message beautifully. The words are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;All the world is my friend
   When I learn how to share my love—
When I stretch out my hand and smile,
   When I live from above.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Matters in the End</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-matters-in-the-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-matters-in-the-end/</guid>
      <description>A poignant quote from Buddha came to us recently: “In the end only three things matter. How much you loved, how gently you lived, and how gracefully you let go of things not meant for you.”
Often we live locked up in self-focused goals and desires. Yet, as we depart from this incarnation, goals must be relinquished and desires discarded. Those desires we fail to abandon will inevitably pull us back into another incarnation, and another, and another.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A poignant quote from Buddha came to us recently: “In the end only three things matter. How much you loved, how gently you lived, and how gracefully you let go of things not meant for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we live locked up in self-focused goals and desires. Yet, as we depart from this incarnation, goals must be relinquished and desires discarded. Those desires we fail to abandon will inevitably pull us back into another incarnation, and another, and another. The solution is disarmingly simple: Expand our heart’s energy by directing it toward God and the benefit of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda explained that the heart is the center of the primordial feeling element (chitta). He added that we perceive and respond to the world primarily through feeling rather than intellect. Ultimately, to find liberation we must still the mind and, especially, neutralize the whirlpools of likes and dislikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy in the “switching station” of the heart is constantly seeking fulfillment. This quest can lead us toward worldly attachments and sensory experiences, or towards the divine joy of God. When our energy is funneled downward and outward, we set ourselves up for anxiety and disappointment. As Yogananda put it, “Delusion always breaks its promises.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best strategies to channel the energy positively is to think of the welfare of others. When we embarked on Ananda’s work in San Francisco, we started a small restaurant/bookstore. The manager, a single woman, had to close the store late at night and then take a bus through a very run-down area of town. Often sharing the bus with drunks and drug addicts, she dreaded the nightly ride home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As she explained her dilemma to Swami Kriyananda, he first explored the standard solutions: Could she drive home? Could she take a taxi? Could someone else drive her? All of these proved either impractical or too expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami said, “All right, then, I suggest that you do this: When you get on the bus, pick out one person who appears to need help and pray for him the whole way home. If that person gets off, choose another.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later she told Swamiji that the bus ride home had transformed into her favorite part of the day. Her prayers for others had shifted her heart’s energy from isolation and fear to connection and joy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-matters-in-the-end.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what matters in the end&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Love is fundamental, but almost as important is gratitude. By being grateful for the circumstances and people in our lives, we open a positive flow of energy from the heart up to the spiritual eye. It’s virtually impossible to harbor negativity when we’re feeling grateful. We don’t have to express it outwardly—we can just silently allow the feeling of thankfulness to reverberate in the heart. Begin by being grateful for things that are easy to accept. Then train yourself also to feel appreciation for challenging situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda wrote, “Teach me to look upon all that happens in my life with a pleased, interested attitude, that at the end of each episode, no matter how sad or difficult, I may exclaim: “Ah, that was a good show, full of thrills, suspense, and excitement! I am happy to have seen it, and I have learned much from it for my own benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we find it challenging to hold such a high attitude, we can at least strive toward it. Some years ago, while experiencing a difficult period, I wrote an affirmation to help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I am grateful for my life exactly as it is.
I am thankful for this day;
I welcome every hour.
Thank you, God. Thank you, God.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have the potential to expand our heart and let it become a channel for the infinite love of God. If we do our best, we can face our final review and say, “I loved greatly, lived gently, and gracefully let go of those things that kept me from Thee, Lord.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In love and gratitude,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Can I Best Help Them?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</guid>
      <description>Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”
We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to meditate before talking with them&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the fruits of meditation is the ability to detach yourself from the events around you and maintain a state of inner equilibrium under all circumstances. This is by no means easy, but needs to be cultivated continuously with energy and determination. During your meditation before meeting them, visualize them surrounded by God’s light and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept people as they are, while at the same time relating to their own higher nature.&lt;/strong&gt; If people feel accepted, it allows them the space to self-correct the behaviors that are causing them unhappiness. While meeting with them, pray and see them resting in their true self—divine love and wisdom. Unconditional acceptance is what God offers all of His children. Try to be a channel of this for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/how-can-i-best-help-them.png&#34;  alt=&#34;how can i best help them&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give direct advice unless they ask; rather, listen attentively so that they feel open to share with you.&lt;/strong&gt; Often an open ear is all people are really seeking. You can inwardly ask God to guide them from within themselves. If they do ask for advice, present it in a positive, nonjudgmental way. A beautiful passage from Master in this regard is: “I am the servant ready to serve all needy minds with my simple advice, with my gifts of healing truth, and with my humble wisdom gathered in the shrine of silence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you feel yourself getting engaged in negativity, quickly and consciously detach yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Be attentive to your own reactions, and inwardly strive to remain centered. Without seeming to withdraw, hold your mind at the spiritual eye. You can also quietly practice regular breathing: inhaling, holding the breath, and exhaling to the same count. Yoganandaji wrote: “When fear or anger or any kind of suffering comes to me, I will view it as a spectator. I will separate myself from my experiences. At all costs I will endeavor to retain my peace and happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always send love. Don’t withhold this no matter how difficult the situation.&lt;/strong&gt; Once a friend of ours was working as a doctor in an emergency room. Late one night, the police brought in a drunken, homeless man who had fallen and broken his arm. He was screaming, both with pain and fear, and it took two policemen to hold him down. To their amazement, our friend told the policemen to leave the treatment room—that she could handle him alone. Surrounding him in love, our friend was able to get the man to calm down so that she could set his arm. Afterwards the poor man looked at her beseechingly with eyes filled with years of loneliness and want, and asked, “Will you be my doctor?” He felt her love surrounding him—a feeling he hadn’t known for a long time. Healing can take place on many levels. By expressing love and forgiveness, not only can we help others, but we can remain uplifted as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, offer them to God for His help. Remember that God is always in charge of guiding every soul to inner freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; We are all on a journey to find the truth of who and what we really are. Offer a helping hand to others, when you can, but remember that ultimately, true happiness and freedom come when we allow God to guide our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these words of Master’s: “I will be a fisher of souls. I will catch the ignorance of others in a net of my wisdom and offer it for transmutation to the God of all gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With loving friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Global Circle of Love</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-global-circle-of-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-global-circle-of-love/</guid>
      <description>This is a special moment in time for Jyotish and me. Yesterday we had our last public satsang in Mumbai after nearly four months of traveling, teaching, and sharing love with friends in Assisi and India. By the time you read this, we will be returning to Ananda Village.
In many ways, this trip has been life-changing. Seeing the waves of devotion to Yoganandaji spreading throughout the world, we realize how blessed we’ve been to be a part of this great work started by Swami Kriyananda over fifty years ago.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This is a special moment in time for Jyotish and me. Yesterday we had our last public satsang in Mumbai after nearly four months of traveling, teaching, and sharing love with friends in Assisi and India. By the time you read this, we will be returning to Ananda Village.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this trip has been life-changing. Seeing the waves of devotion to Yoganandaji spreading throughout the world, we realize how blessed we’ve been to be a part of this great work started by Swami Kriyananda over fifty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-global-circle-of-love.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a global circle of love&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thousands of new students are studying Master’s teachings in person and online, and thousands more are taking discipleship and initiation into Kriya Yoga. What touched us the most, however, was seeing the divine love for others that is being offered by Ananda devotees throughout the world. Here are three stories that we heard during our travels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was told to us by Mahiya, one of the leaders of Ananda Assisi. It took place at Terre di Luce (Lands of Light), their beautiful organic gardens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer, Satya, a Kriyaban friend, came to help us in the kitchen. He brought his parents with him: Adamo, ninety-two years old, and Eleonora, in her eighties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Satya did his service in the kitchen, they would sit on the sofas and just be. Often people would sit with them, making conversation and expressing kindness. Satya had told them nothing about this path, and they had no idea what Ananda was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eleonora has dementia, but Adamo was fully aware of everything. He loved it here, and wanted to participate in everything! When Satya tried to leave them at the nearby house he had rented, Adamo would have nothing of it—he wanted to be at Terre di Luce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every afternoon after lunch we have a chanting circle before we start our service. We would often chant to the Guru or to Divine Mother in Sanskrit. The fact that it was all in a strange language didn’t matter to Adamo—he would never miss the chanting circle! After one circle he said, “This place is a paradise. I want to stay here forever. Here you are all friends, and everybody loves and respects one another. You can’t find that in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks after Satya and his parents went back to Rome, Adamo left his body. We had an Astral Ascension Ceremony for him in which everyone shared deeply how much this wonderful soul loved Ananda. We all felt that his wish of “wanting to stay at Ananda forever,” or in the presence of the Masters that he felt here, had come true: He was now in the astral world in the loving hands of our Masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what Terre di Luce is for me and why I love it here. I see it as a place where people come and experience love and friendship which transforms them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories of kindness and compassion from our travels in India are too numerous to tell (I’ll share a few more in the recorded commentary), but two others especially stand out. India was hit very hard by the pandemic, with many deaths and inadequate supplies of medicine, oxygen, and hospital beds. Our center leaders told us that they were often performing eight to ten Astral Ascension Ceremonies per week for members or their loved ones who had passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two dear Kriyaban friends of ours, Dr. Mansi and Dr. Amar, shared stories about serving together on the Covid ward in a hospital in Pune. They’re a married couple, with two teenaged daughters and his parents living with them. In spite of these responsibilities, they served for months on end, often with just a few hours of sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the hospital began filling up with Covid patients who occupied all the beds and spilled out into the hallways, Dr. Amar felt some hesitation about working in such close proximity to infected people. He thought, “I don’t want to catch the disease and bring it home to my family.” In answer, he heard a voice within him say, “Would you hesitate to help your own children? These people are all your children!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this divine guidance, he served wholeheartedly throughout the pandemic. Both he and Dr. Mansi did contract Covid, but their children and parents were never infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the pandemic, when the deaths began overwhelming even the crematoriums, Dr. Mansi was exhausted and hit an emotional wall. One day in particular she saw many deaths not only of the elderly, but also of young men who were the sole support of their families. She returned home in the evening exhausted and with a heavy heart. As she closed her eyes for a few minutes, she had a remarkable dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it Master appeared in the hospital dressed in silvery-white robes, bustling here and there attending to the patients. He turned to her and said, “The disease is caused by bad karma brought on by people’s negative thoughts. We can’t stop the disease, but we must stay very busy trying to help everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mansi then began shaping balls of mud into babies. When she held them, they were living children; when she put them down they were only mud once more. “Don’t you see?” Master said. “When Divine Mother touches them, they come alive. Otherwise they are dead. Don’t grieve, my daughter.” After this dream, Mansi was able to continue in her service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, in these stories you can see the beauty of living for God and serving Him in others. Our lives have been changed by witnessing such self-offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Return of the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-return-of-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-return-of-the-light/</guid>
      <description>“They’re coming! Our king and queen are coming! Ram, our beloved God, and Sita, our beautiful queen, are finally coming home!” Thus rejoiced the happy citizens of Ayodhya centuries ago when Ram and Sita returned. After long years away, the living light was returning to Ayodhya, and the people were placing lamps along the road to celebrate the occasion.
This event, central to the Ramayana (one of two great spiritual epics of India), has inspired people for thousands of years.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“They’re coming! Our king and queen are coming! Ram, our beloved God, and Sita, our beautiful queen, are finally coming home!” Thus rejoiced the happy citizens of Ayodhya centuries ago when Ram and Sita returned. After long years away, the living light was returning to Ayodhya, and the people were placing lamps along the road to celebrate the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event, central to the Ramayana (one of two great spiritual epics of India), has inspired people for thousands of years. Even today the victory of light over darkness fills a deep soul-longing in the heart of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diwali, the Festival of Light, is celebrated throughout India. Lights can be seen everywhere: strings of it decorating balconies and windows, candles placed in doorways and windows and on the altars of homes, and fireworks bursting like stars in the night sky. It’s not only in India that Diwali is celebrated. In New York City it is an official public holiday, given that there are over 200,000 people of Indian origin living there. Diwali is celebrated in the White House and, of course, in the U.K., which now has the first prime minister of Indian origin. The light of Diwali is, indeed, spreading around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, these outward displays are what might be called “social Diwali.” Spiritual Diwali is our daily return to the light in the spiritual eye, which can be experienced in every meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout long cycles of time, this theme—the triumph of light over darkness—has recurred in many different forms. For much of the Western world, it is celebrated at Christmas time, when the Christ was born. Each race and culture recognizes and celebrates light in its own special way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-return-of-the-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the return of the light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This holy season is a good time to open our hearts, to recognize and give thanks to the people and events that have been channels for God’s light and love to us. For many of our readers, our “Diwali” is the coming of Paramhansa Yogananda, often experienced when we first read Autobiography of a Yogi. Take a moment to reflect on how God has come into your life, and offer prayers of gratitude. Meditate for a while on all the people—family, friends, and teachers—who have been channels of Divine Mother’s love to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that Devi and I try to do in these weekly essays is to share little moments of inspiration that occur in our lives. As a Diwali gift we were given a small book, 365 Quotes by Gandhi, and I thought it would be nice to share with you a few rays of Gandhi’s light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You may never know what results come of your actions, but if you do nothing there will be no results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whenever you are confronted with an opponent, conquer him with love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The day the power of love overrules the love of power, the world will know peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Diwali talk that Swami Kriyananda gave in India in 2004, he urged everyone to fully open themselves to God’s light. That, however, is not enough. He went on to say that we should also strive to see the light of God in everyone we meet, and that we must actively spread God’s love to a world that desperately needs it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let each of us be a channel of light and live every day as if it were Diwali, a new dawning of the divine light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
