<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>surrender on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/surrender/</link>
    <description>Recent content in surrender on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/surrender/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An Approach for Every Challenge</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/an-approach-for-every-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/an-approach-for-every-challenge/</guid>
      <description>Many readers will know that Ananda Village was mostly destroyed by a huge forest fire in 1976. Devi and I were new parents with an eleven-day-old infant when the flames devoured our home, our clothes, and virtually all our possessions. In meditation this morning I was remembering that day and contemplating some of the cherished lessons I learned.
It was June 28, 1976. Our first awareness of danger was when we saw smoke arising from a nearby road.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Many readers will know that Ananda Village was mostly destroyed by a huge forest fire in 1976. Devi and I were new parents with an eleven-day-old infant when the flames devoured our home, our clothes, and virtually all our possessions. In meditation this morning I was remembering that day and contemplating some of the cherished lessons I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was June 28, 1976. Our first awareness of danger was when we saw smoke arising from a nearby road. The summer was upon us, and the fields and forests had already begun to dry out. The hundred or so members of the community were at first merely vigilant, then concerned, and finally aroused into action. The winds were blowing the fire uphill through knee-high grasses, and in our direction. About twenty of us gathered on a road at the crest of the hill with rakes, hoes, and whatever firefighting equipment we had at our disposal. I had a small water-tank backpack with a pump and nozzle, which we kept handy in case a chimney fire broke out in our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire was creeping steadily up the hill toward us, waist-high flames spread across the terrain. For some inexplicable reason I decided that it would be a good idea to go down the hill, meet the flames head on, and slow them down with my pumper. As I approached, however, I realized that the flames were moving much faster than I’d thought, and much faster than I could run up the hill. In a moment I realized my safest bet was to jump through the wall of flames into the already burned area. This may have saved my life, and it also steeled my determination to fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then returned to our house. It was a small geodesic dome with a leaky roof, but it was home for our little family. I was completely focused on digging a little perimeter trench when a young member of the community drove up shouting, “You have to leave. The flames are in the trees. There’s no chance to save your house.” Only then did I realize the unstoppable force of nature unleashed. Devi, meanwhile, had taken our infant son to the doctor for his first checkup. That morning she had packed up the items from our meditation room, intending to clean it when she got home. In the few remaining moments, this was all I could save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finally emerged from the smoking hillside, I found Devi standing there, obviously alarmed, not knowing whether I was alive or dead. My first instinct was to comfort her and do what I could to de-escalate the alarm while still letting her know that our home was gone. My first words, some of the best I’ve ever spoken, were, “Well, we don’t have to worry about those leaks anymore.” We comforted each other and soon realized that our baby’s real home was built from the threads of love in our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I contemplated that fateful event I realized that there were different approaches to working with the challenges presented by the fire, each of which was valid. The same is true for the spiritual tests we face.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/an-approach-for-every-challenge.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;an approach for every challenge&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confront it head-on.&lt;/strong&gt; If the challenge seems small enough to overcome, our growth lies in confronting it. Spiritually, it may be the fires of anger or the fear of loss that has to be faced. We will each draw our own test to conquer, sized just right for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept, surrender, and move on.&lt;/strong&gt; Many of life’s issues are too big for us to change. Politics, economics, pandemics, and weather are all things that we can’t fight individually. The best approach here is just to accept conditions as they are, surrender ourselves to the goodness of God, and move on. This is harder than it seems, since it involves overcoming the reactive process. It will help if you can remember that it is all a dream of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think of others.&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, the best spiritual approach in almost all situations is to forget about yourself and your “needs.” Think about the welfare of others. Self-forgetfulness broadens the human heart and opens up space for the all-healing flow of love. It then becomes possible to offer up the little love that is in us into the infinite love of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fires of devotion,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pink Man</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/pink-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/pink-man/</guid>
      <description>My major field of study in college was cultural anthropology. One of my professors shared some interesting experiences he’d had during a year in which he lived with a remote tribe in New Guinea. These people were so inaccessible that they’d never seen a Westerner before.
At first they just ignored him or stared at him suspiciously as though he were a new variety of albino snake or toad. After weeks of such treatment, he would withdraw into his tent, read Shakespeare, and try to affirm, “I am an educated, intelligent human being who is part of an advanced civilization.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;My major field of study in college was cultural anthropology. One of my professors shared some interesting experiences he’d had during a year in which he lived with a remote tribe in New Guinea. These people were so inaccessible that they’d never seen a Westerner before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first they just ignored him or stared at him suspiciously as though he were a new variety of albino snake or toad. After weeks of such treatment, he would withdraw into his tent, read Shakespeare, and try to affirm, “I am an educated, intelligent human being who is part of an advanced civilization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little by little the tribe’s people saw that he meant them no harm, and they allowed him to enter into their daily life. As he began to learn their language and culture, he realized that what they’d been calling him all along was “Pink Man.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After more time had passed, he no longer had to affirm who he had been, but could accept that he was now a different version of himself. After a year, “Pink Man” returned to his university and wrote an ethnography of the tribe that had opened his eyes to another worldview and helped change how he thought about himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the professor’s experience, I realized that what interested me was not so much the customs and languages of other peoples, but the opportunity to expand one’s self-definition by immersing in a different reality. Fortunately, God showed me a better way to do this through the spiritual path and discipleship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inner self-transformation is never easy, no matter how you approach it. In trying to transcend self-limitations and old ways of thinking, we find ourselves clinging to the familiar, even if it no longer serves our aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/pink-man.png&#34;  alt=&#34;pink man&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Paramhansa Yogananda’s unparalleled explanation of the Bhagavad Gita, he tells us that the challenges Arjuna faces before the battle of Kurukshetra are allegorical. Each character, friend or foe, is symbolic of an inner quality that lives within each of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those on the opposing side, the Kauravas, are his relatives and mentors, although they represent such things as material desire, ego, habits, and attachment. As the great warrior Arjuna surveys the Kaurava army before the battle begins, he becomes discouraged, drops his bow, and says to his charioteer, Krishna, “These are my kinsmen. I cannot kill them. Therefore, I will not fight.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji explains that this is the inner battle we all must face. We fear killing old patterns and habits, because we’re not sure who we will become when the familiar is gone. Yet unless we take up the fight, we can never discover our own higher Self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the remainder of the Gita, Krishna explains to Arjuna that the true Self is never lost, but through spiritual effort, its energy is transmuted into a higher expression. “The soul is never touched; it is immutable, all-pervading, calm, unshakable; its existence is eternal.” (Chapter 2:24)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Jyotish and I enter our second month of traveling to Ananda centers in Italy and India, the process of personal transformation and letting go of the familiar is something we face daily. What a joy to offer oneself up to the process, allowing God to guide us toward inner freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether through the example of “Pink Man” overcoming the fear of loss of self-identity, or Arjuna transcending the reluctance to fight old mental tendencies, we need to take the leap of faith. It’s by surrendering the self to God that we go beyond our limitations and find who and what we really are: a spark of the Divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
