<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>God on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/god/</link>
    <description>Recent content in God on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/god/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stranger in a Strange Land</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/stranger-in-a-strange-land/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/stranger-in-a-strange-land/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago Jyotish and I led the Astral Ascension Ceremony for a dear friend, Judy Fox, who passed away recently. Judy was part of a small team, as were we, that Swami Kriyananda sent to Italy in the early 1980s to help start Ananda’s work there.
We landed in Northern Italy near Lake Como at a lovely summer villa that belonged to a friend and fellow disciple. Sound idyllic?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago Jyotish and I led the Astral Ascension Ceremony for a dear friend, Judy Fox, who passed away recently. Judy was part of a small team, as were we, that Swami Kriyananda sent to Italy in the early 1980s to help start Ananda’s work there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We landed in Northern Italy near Lake Como at a lovely summer villa that belonged to a friend and fellow disciple. Sound idyllic? Perhaps, but as the months passed and temperatures dropped, living in a summer house with little heat during the coldest winter in Europe in one hundred years was a huge challenge for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, living in a different culture from what we were accustomed to, knowing very few people on whom to call, and having none of our usual comforts all reinforced the feeling that we were “stranieri,” foreigners. As time passed, we felt more and more like “strangers in a strange land” (Exodus 2:22).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji knew all of us well, however, and felt that we had the strength and commitment not only to survive the challenges, but to grow spiritually in the process. And so it proved. We soon realized we had one of two choices: 1) to let our energy drop, and sink into loneliness and depression; or 2) to raise our energy level and deepen our faith in God’s guiding presence with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together our small team consciously chose the second option: to keep our spirits uplifted and to look for ways to share Master’s great teachings with seekers in Europe. From these humble beginnings, Ananda now has a thriving international community outside of Assisi, Italy, as well as centers spreading throughout Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our friend Judy, who was there that first winter, had an especially joyful and ebullient nature, and helped us all to stay positive. At her Astral Ascension Ceremony, her partner of twenty-seven years, Ric, shared with us a beautiful story about her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judy met him shortly after returning to California from Italy, and told him about Master’s path and Ananda. Then (after knowing Ric for only ten days) she told him that he should visit Assisi, because: “The farther you are from home, the closer you are to God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With those simple words, Judy captured our whole experience of that difficult first winter. With nothing familiar from which to draw, we had to tune in to another form of comfort and sense of “home”: God’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This world—which alternates between seeming welcoming and familiar to seeming unloving and foreign—can never really be our home. Why? Because on the deepest level, it’s only an impermanent illusion. We are strangers in a strange land. Our true soul home can only be found by reuniting with God, from Whom we sprang lifetimes ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So remember, when you’re going through a difficult time outside of your comfort zone and the world seems inimical and unwelcoming, think of Judy’s mantra: &lt;strong&gt;“The farther you are from home, the closer you are to God.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at those other times when life is going all your way? Recall Judy’s mantra to mind just as forcefully then. Will you rest comfortably in all that’s familiar? Will you, in Yogananda’s immortal words, “bask in the familial warmth”? Or will you embrace self-expansion and as yet uncharted waters? This choice is always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/stranger-in-a-strange-land.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;stranger in a strange land&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these stanzas from Swamiji’s beautiful song, “God’s Call Within,” which captures the essence of our soul’s search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.


Friend, how long will you wander?
Friend, as long as you seek your home
In a land where all are strangers,
Love locks her door.


Turn, turn, turn within:
In silence of soul, in cave of love
Find My abode.
 

Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your fellow wanderer,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Can I Best Help Them?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</guid>
      <description>Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”
We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to meditate before talking with them&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the fruits of meditation is the ability to detach yourself from the events around you and maintain a state of inner equilibrium under all circumstances. This is by no means easy, but needs to be cultivated continuously with energy and determination. During your meditation before meeting them, visualize them surrounded by God’s light and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept people as they are, while at the same time relating to their own higher nature.&lt;/strong&gt; If people feel accepted, it allows them the space to self-correct the behaviors that are causing them unhappiness. While meeting with them, pray and see them resting in their true self—divine love and wisdom. Unconditional acceptance is what God offers all of His children. Try to be a channel of this for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/how-can-i-best-help-them.png&#34;  alt=&#34;how can i best help them&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give direct advice unless they ask; rather, listen attentively so that they feel open to share with you.&lt;/strong&gt; Often an open ear is all people are really seeking. You can inwardly ask God to guide them from within themselves. If they do ask for advice, present it in a positive, nonjudgmental way. A beautiful passage from Master in this regard is: “I am the servant ready to serve all needy minds with my simple advice, with my gifts of healing truth, and with my humble wisdom gathered in the shrine of silence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you feel yourself getting engaged in negativity, quickly and consciously detach yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Be attentive to your own reactions, and inwardly strive to remain centered. Without seeming to withdraw, hold your mind at the spiritual eye. You can also quietly practice regular breathing: inhaling, holding the breath, and exhaling to the same count. Yoganandaji wrote: “When fear or anger or any kind of suffering comes to me, I will view it as a spectator. I will separate myself from my experiences. At all costs I will endeavor to retain my peace and happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always send love. Don’t withhold this no matter how difficult the situation.&lt;/strong&gt; Once a friend of ours was working as a doctor in an emergency room. Late one night, the police brought in a drunken, homeless man who had fallen and broken his arm. He was screaming, both with pain and fear, and it took two policemen to hold him down. To their amazement, our friend told the policemen to leave the treatment room—that she could handle him alone. Surrounding him in love, our friend was able to get the man to calm down so that she could set his arm. Afterwards the poor man looked at her beseechingly with eyes filled with years of loneliness and want, and asked, “Will you be my doctor?” He felt her love surrounding him—a feeling he hadn’t known for a long time. Healing can take place on many levels. By expressing love and forgiveness, not only can we help others, but we can remain uplifted as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, offer them to God for His help. Remember that God is always in charge of guiding every soul to inner freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; We are all on a journey to find the truth of who and what we really are. Offer a helping hand to others, when you can, but remember that ultimately, true happiness and freedom come when we allow God to guide our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these words of Master’s: “I will be a fisher of souls. I will catch the ignorance of others in a net of my wisdom and offer it for transmutation to the God of all gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With loving friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding God in the Big City</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-god-in-the-big-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-god-in-the-big-city/</guid>
      <description>Twenty million people! That’s the population of the Greater Los Angeles area, we were told recently when we visited friends and Ananda centers there.
For one of our satsangs, in Torrance, the center leader asked us to talk about how to find spirituality in big-city life. I thought you, too, might be interested in the thoughts we shared that evening on the challenges faced by city-dwellers and some of the spiritual solutions to them.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Twenty million people! That’s the population of the Greater Los Angeles area, we were told recently when we visited friends and Ananda centers there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one of our satsangs, in Torrance, the center leader asked us to talk about how to find spirituality in big-city life. I thought you, too, might be interested in the thoughts we shared that evening on the challenges faced by city-dwellers and some of the spiritual solutions to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;distraction-vs-focused-attention&#34;&gt;Distraction vs. Focused Attention&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving on big-city freeways is an experience in itself. It’s almost overwhelming to deal with the long commutes, the speed of the traffic, and the constantly flashing billboards screaming (as a friend of ours once humorously put it), “Eat me. Buy me. Take me home!” The mind gets scattered in a myriad of different directions, and even after arriving at your destination, it takes an effort of will to get focused again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no small obstacle to achieving peace of mind, but the opportunity is also there: to keep the mind more concentrated on whatever we’re doing. Build up the habit of attentive awareness in everything you do—talking with a friend, working on a project at your job, going for a walk. While driving, listen to something uplifting—beautiful music or an inspiring talk—and give it your attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more you make the conscious effort to concentrate, the more will you find yourself actively and rewardingly engaged in every area of your life. And the greater will your ability be to go deep in meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;self-interest-vs-self-giving&#34;&gt;Self-Interest vs. Self-Giving&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forces of competition and self-interest are strong in any large group. Even lab rats turn on one another when placed in overcrowded tanks. The seeming cold indifference in a big city may lead us to think, “If I don’t look out for ‘Number One,’ how will I get by?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity here is to counter the pull of self-interest by consciously finding ways to serve and to give to others. We have a friend in Los Angeles who would give her daughters a small weekly allowance, and then (at their request) drive them to an area where homeless people lived, so that they could give their money away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find ways to help others, even at your own inconvenience or loss. Keeping the heart open to those in need frees us from preoccupation with the demands of our limited self. Ultimately we realize that God alone is the provider, and that the more we give, the more we are given. Self-giving also leads us to experience a loving connection with all of life.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/finding-god-in-the-big-city.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;finding-god-in-the-big-city&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;self-indulgence-vs-self-control&#34;&gt;Self-Indulgence vs. Self-Control&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big-city life offers many dark pathways that lead to overstimulation of the senses, even to the point of self-destruction. Master set up his headquarters in Los Angeles, and lived there for nearly twenty-five years. He would sometimes walk up and down some of the seedy, bar-lined streets in order to bring light and upliftment to the poor souls there trapped in addictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity for us here is to examine our own life and find areas where we lack sufficient self-control. Take up a challenge with the thought, “I will practice inner discipline so that others may follow my lead and develop self-control in their life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’ve improved in one area, take up another challenge, until you begin to see that you—not old habits or karma—are in charge of your life. What freedom comes with this realization!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;downward-emotions-vs-uplifted-feelings&#34;&gt;Downward Emotions vs. Uplifted Feelings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer number of life stories and struggles in a big city can create a fog of hopelessness and despair. Especially now with economic and political uncertainty rife—and with the possibility looming on the horizon of even worse to come—it’s easy to be pulled down into negativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To counter this tendency, we should strive energetically to keep hope and joy foremost in our minds. One of my favorite quotes of Master’s is, “Life is a battle for joy every step of the way. May I fight to win the battle on the very spot where I now stand.” These words have stood me in good stead through many a difficult situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you choose joy under all circumstances, you begin to find that joy is your constant companion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, finding God in big-city life comes down to this: In each of life’s circumstances, choose the highest and best road to follow. And use all of your strength and commitment to stay the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember these words of Yoganandaji: “There are no obstacles, only opportunities.” Your very effort will uplift those around you, whether you live in a big city or a small ashram. Then you become, as Swami Kriyananda used to say, “part of the solution, not the problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from the Snow</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/lessons-from-the-snow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/lessons-from-the-snow/</guid>
      <description>We have been experiencing historic snowfalls in Northern California. Hard as it is to imagine, some areas near Lake Tahoe have gotten nearly fifty feet of snow so far, with more on the way! Much less has fallen at Ananda Village, but still we’ve gotten more than any time in recent memory. With hills, freezing temperatures, and snowy roads, many of us have been snowbound. Here is the view from our living room this morning.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We have been experiencing historic snowfalls in Northern California. Hard as it is to imagine, some areas near Lake Tahoe have gotten nearly fifty feet of snow so far, with more on the way! Much less has fallen at Ananda Village, but still we’ve gotten more than any time in recent memory. With hills, freezing temperatures, and snowy roads, many of us have been snowbound. Here is the view from our living room this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For restless people, conditions like these are probably a torment. For yogis, being forced to go within is actually quite nice. The snow brings with it some wonderful lessons. Here are a few that have struck me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;give-help-receive-help&#34;&gt;Give Help, Receive Help&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During times of hardship, people of goodwill rise to the occasion. At Ananda Village our maintenance crews have worked around the clock to help people cope with the icy roads; our market staff has been delivering food orders to residents; and many of us are feeding the birds and animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-minded people naturally want to serve others. But the snow is bringing another lesson: to be willing and grateful to receive help when offered. Many devotees are better at giving than receiving. This is a good quality in moderation, but becomes a spiritual flaw when taken too far. We need to learn the art of receiving also. Everything in life is a gift from the Divine. It delays our spiritual progress if we ignore or reject the help that is given to us. In meditation our first act should be to open our hearts, receive God’s presence, and silently say, “Thank you, God.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/lessons-from-the-snow.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;lessons-from-the-snow&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;use-the-time-well&#34;&gt;Use the Time Well&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having one’s schedule disrupted can be a good thing, if you are flexible and can shift your energies to alternative activities. It sounds like this should be easy, but restlessness is one of the great curses of our times. According to our great Masters, we live in a rajasic (restless) age on a rajasic planet in a rajasic galaxy. Is it any wonder that people are habituated, even addicted, to activity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental restlessness is perhaps the greatest block to meditation. When circumstances shut down our normal schedule, let’s use the time to turn our consciousness upward. For me personally the snow gave me some time to paint for which I was joyfully grateful. The inspiration came to do a pair of paintings of the same scene at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dawn” and “Midnight,” the two paintings I drew during the snowstorm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;live-more-in-god&#34;&gt;Live More in God&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest gift of inwardness, whether forced or voluntary, is the opportunity to turn a quieted mind toward living in God’s presence. No matter the conditions or the place, we can always choose to turn our minds and hearts Godward. Yoganandaji stated it so poetically in this beautiful poem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wherever-we-go&#34;&gt;Wherever We Go&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Whether in Himalayan caves or crowded subway;

Whether in the concrete jungle of modern life,

Or in a simple village in Hindustan:

Wherever we go, teach us to seek Thee out

In all Thy secret nooks—east, west, north, south—everywhere!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I pray that for all of us, we can see behind every circumstance, good or bad, the hidden opportunity to live more in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Approach for Every Challenge</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/an-approach-for-every-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/an-approach-for-every-challenge/</guid>
      <description>Many readers will know that Ananda Village was mostly destroyed by a huge forest fire in 1976. Devi and I were new parents with an eleven-day-old infant when the flames devoured our home, our clothes, and virtually all our possessions. In meditation this morning I was remembering that day and contemplating some of the cherished lessons I learned.
It was June 28, 1976. Our first awareness of danger was when we saw smoke arising from a nearby road.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Many readers will know that Ananda Village was mostly destroyed by a huge forest fire in 1976. Devi and I were new parents with an eleven-day-old infant when the flames devoured our home, our clothes, and virtually all our possessions. In meditation this morning I was remembering that day and contemplating some of the cherished lessons I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was June 28, 1976. Our first awareness of danger was when we saw smoke arising from a nearby road. The summer was upon us, and the fields and forests had already begun to dry out. The hundred or so members of the community were at first merely vigilant, then concerned, and finally aroused into action. The winds were blowing the fire uphill through knee-high grasses, and in our direction. About twenty of us gathered on a road at the crest of the hill with rakes, hoes, and whatever firefighting equipment we had at our disposal. I had a small water-tank backpack with a pump and nozzle, which we kept handy in case a chimney fire broke out in our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire was creeping steadily up the hill toward us, waist-high flames spread across the terrain. For some inexplicable reason I decided that it would be a good idea to go down the hill, meet the flames head on, and slow them down with my pumper. As I approached, however, I realized that the flames were moving much faster than I’d thought, and much faster than I could run up the hill. In a moment I realized my safest bet was to jump through the wall of flames into the already burned area. This may have saved my life, and it also steeled my determination to fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then returned to our house. It was a small geodesic dome with a leaky roof, but it was home for our little family. I was completely focused on digging a little perimeter trench when a young member of the community drove up shouting, “You have to leave. The flames are in the trees. There’s no chance to save your house.” Only then did I realize the unstoppable force of nature unleashed. Devi, meanwhile, had taken our infant son to the doctor for his first checkup. That morning she had packed up the items from our meditation room, intending to clean it when she got home. In the few remaining moments, this was all I could save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finally emerged from the smoking hillside, I found Devi standing there, obviously alarmed, not knowing whether I was alive or dead. My first instinct was to comfort her and do what I could to de-escalate the alarm while still letting her know that our home was gone. My first words, some of the best I’ve ever spoken, were, “Well, we don’t have to worry about those leaks anymore.” We comforted each other and soon realized that our baby’s real home was built from the threads of love in our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I contemplated that fateful event I realized that there were different approaches to working with the challenges presented by the fire, each of which was valid. The same is true for the spiritual tests we face.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/an-approach-for-every-challenge.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;an approach for every challenge&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confront it head-on.&lt;/strong&gt; If the challenge seems small enough to overcome, our growth lies in confronting it. Spiritually, it may be the fires of anger or the fear of loss that has to be faced. We will each draw our own test to conquer, sized just right for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept, surrender, and move on.&lt;/strong&gt; Many of life’s issues are too big for us to change. Politics, economics, pandemics, and weather are all things that we can’t fight individually. The best approach here is just to accept conditions as they are, surrender ourselves to the goodness of God, and move on. This is harder than it seems, since it involves overcoming the reactive process. It will help if you can remember that it is all a dream of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think of others.&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, the best spiritual approach in almost all situations is to forget about yourself and your “needs.” Think about the welfare of others. Self-forgetfulness broadens the human heart and opens up space for the all-healing flow of love. It then becomes possible to offer up the little love that is in us into the infinite love of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fires of devotion,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our True Value</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/our-true-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/our-true-value/</guid>
      <description>In the first few years after Swami Kriyananda started Ananda, a number of swamis from India visited us. Most of them were not well known and were traveling alone without any entourage, but they brought with them the authentic spirituality of India. Perhaps it was Yoganandaji’s way of helping to imbue our lives, and Ananda’s work for the future, with deep spiritual vibrations.
One of these swamis said something in answer to a question I put to him that made a lasting impact on my life.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In the first few years after Swami Kriyananda started Ananda, a number of swamis from India visited us. Most of them were not well known and were traveling alone without any entourage, but they brought with them the authentic spirituality of India. Perhaps it was Yoganandaji’s way of helping to imbue our lives, and Ananda’s work for the future, with deep spiritual vibrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these swamis said something in answer to a question I put to him that made a lasting impact on my life. I asked, “How do you develop the kind of dedication that enables you to stay on the spiritual path for your whole life?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His answer puzzled me at the time, and over the years I’ve tried to understand its deeper meaning. He replied simply, “Don’t compare yourself to others.” That was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’d never met before, so his response couldn’t have been based on seeing something in my behavior. But high souls have a deep sense of intuition that enables them to pierce to the heart of things. Over time I could see how his reply had hit home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw how most of my training in life was to find my value by comparing my performance to that of others. “Am I better than my classmates?” “How much better?” “Am I the best?” were questions that ran through my mind. I wanted to do well in school and work, but my only gauge to judge my value was to compare my performance with others. This kind of thinking may get you to the top of your class or job, but it has its limitations in our spiritual growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I read an article by a psychologist about something called “Goal Orientation Theory.” According to this, there are two kinds of goals: 1)“performance-oriented goals,” also called “ego-goals” (I’m not making this up), and 2) “mastery-oriented goals,” also called “learning goals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With “performance-oriented goals,” we try to show others how well we’re doing and are concerned about how they judge us. With “mastery-oriented goals,” we seek challenges and try to overcome difficulties, and our primary concern is self-improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/our-true-value.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;our true value&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This psychological distinction reflects the same thing that the swami told me years ago. By comparing ourself with others, we’re stuck in a world of smoke and mirrors in which all we see are distorted reflections of who we really are. By seeking inner challenges and personal growth, we move towards self-mastery, wherein lies our actual value. And in the ultimate realization of our oneness with God we find truly the only thing in life worth achieving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his book Visits to Saints of India, Swami Kriyananda wrote about a saint he’d visited in 1960 named Yogi Ramiah, or Sri Rama Yogi. Yoganandaji had previously visited him during his return trip to India in 1936, and said that he was a fully liberated master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji wrote, “I found Sri Rama Yogi by nature extremely withdrawn, hiding his spiritual glory from a wish to avoid curiosity seeking.” He lived in a small village in southern India, with only a few aged disciples around him. Sensing his high state of consciousness, Swamiji asked him why he didn’t have a more public work through which he could help many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sri Rama Yogi answered simply, “God has done what He wants to do with this body.” He was able to cast aside the lower expression of self-will for the higher value of doing only God’s will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is our true value? It’s not what others think of us, or even what we can accomplish in this world. It lies in the truth that God is the only reality behind everything that we do and are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji put it beautifully with these words: “Beloved Lord, teach me to feel that Thou art the sole activating power, and that in recognition of Thee as the Doer lies the value of all my life’s experiences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, in God’s eyes we are all “the best.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Permanent Gains</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/making-permanent-gains/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/making-permanent-gains/</guid>
      <description>As we enter the new year, it’s traditional to use this juncture as an opportunity to make resolutions about how we’d like to improve our life. It’s a little discouraging, however, to think back on previous New Year’s resolutions and realize that we’d resolved to change the same things in years past without any discernible results.
How much exercise equipment is bought at the beginning of the new year only to be sold unused a few months later?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;As we enter the new year, it’s traditional to use this juncture as an opportunity to make resolutions about how we’d like to improve our life. It’s a little discouraging, however, to think back on previous New Year’s resolutions and realize that we’d resolved to change the same things in years past without any discernible results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much exercise equipment is bought at the beginning of the new year only to be sold unused a few months later? Yet at the same time, it’s encouraging to reflect that we’ve never given up hope and are still trying. Our desire to improve remains with us, because it’s prompted from a higher level of our own consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I was leading a New Year’s retreat at The Expanding Light, during which we each made a list of resolutions for the coming year. During a break in the class, one of the students came up to me and said, “I find that very depressing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean?” I asked him in surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’ve been on the spiritual path for a long time now,” he replied, “and you still have things about yourself that you want to change?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately a friend of mine, Roma, happened to be walking by at that moment and rescued me. With a twinkle in her eye, she said, “Devi is the only one in the community who isn’t perfect yet. That’s why we have her working with the guests.” We all laughed, and I hope the young man realized that the search for perfection is a long process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s an aspect of personal transformation that’s often overlooked, and it’s the main thought I want to share with you today: To make lasting improvements in our life, it takes more than our own personal efforts. &lt;strong&gt;True inner change comes about through a combination of sincere devotion to God and the grace that it draws.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite passages in the Bhagavad Gita is: “To those who meditate on Me as their very own, their hearts ever united to Me by incessant inward worship, I supply their deficiencies and make permanent their gains.” (9:22)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is God who “supplies our deficiencies.”&lt;/strong&gt; He/She alone knows our shortcomings, loves us unconditionally in spite of them, and gives us the strength and understanding to transcend them. Our minds may be clouded by past karmic tendencies, but when the light of God’s love and wisdom shines in, we gain the power and clarity to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/making-permanent-gains.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;making permanent gains&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And it is God who “makes permanent our gains.”&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes it’s hard to see the spiritual progress we’ve made. We can become so focused on how much farther we have still to go that we fail to appreciate how far we have already come. Remember, whatever progress we’ve made remains with us on some level, because it’s based on the truth of our own being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through our devotion, the sense of “I-ness” that identifies with our limitations begins to dissolve. When, time and again, we stray from the knowledge of who we really are, God is there to steer us back on course towards our own highest potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as we enter the new year, remember, whatever the outer circumstances, to keep your love for God foremost in your mind. This is the most powerful and effective way to turn our resolutions into realities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referring to the passage quoted earlier, Swami Kriyananda writes in The Essence of the Bhagavad Gita: Explained by Paramhansa Yogananda: “Thus, the highest teaching, which Krishna expounds here, is to love God, the Infinite Spirit, above all: ‘to meditate on Him as one’s very own.’ God alone can lift us out of the relativities of karmic merits and demerits into the absolute peace and freedom of Infinite Being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing you a blessed and joyful New Year,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Message in a Strange Encounter</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter/</guid>
      <description>The winter’s night was very cold and windy, and I huddled by the little stove in my camper reading the Bible by the light of a kerosene lamp. In the early years of Ananda our dwellings were simple—without electricity, running water, phones, or any way to communicate with others.
But we were more than happy to live in whatever was available—campers, teepees, old delivery trucks—just to be part of Ananda. Here we could dedicate our lives to God as well as help Swami Kriyananda fulfill Yoganandaji’s dream of world brotherhood colonies.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The winter’s night was very cold and windy, and I huddled by the little stove in my camper reading the Bible by the light of a kerosene lamp. In the early years of Ananda our dwellings were simple—without electricity, running water, phones, or any way to communicate with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we were more than happy to live in whatever was available—campers, teepees, old delivery trucks—just to be part of Ananda. Here we could dedicate our lives to God as well as help Swami Kriyananda fulfill Yoganandaji’s dream of world brotherhood colonies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this particular night as I was reading, I was startled to hear a loud pounding on the door. I cautiously opened it, and there on the cinder block step stood a strange man with a wild look in his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I need to come in,” he said in a demanding voice. Offering silent prayers to God for protection, I stood aside and let him enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sat down on one of the two benches at my little table. “I’m hungry. What do you have to eat?” he again demanded. (More silent prayers on my part.) I offered him some food which he ate voraciously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m thirsty. What can I drink?”(Still more silent prayers.) I placed some water before him, which he quickly gulped down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeming to relax a bit he said, “I like it here. It’s nice and warm.” After a pause he added, “I have these big sores on my arms.” He rolled up one of his sleeves and showed me open, oozing sores on his arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(“Please God, resolve this quickly,” I fervently prayed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more moments passed. Then he suddenly stood up and said, “Thank you. I have to go now,” and quickly departed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totally baffled by what had just happened, I sat stunned for a few minutes. Then taking a few deep breaths, I continued reading the Bible. These were the first words that my eyes fell upon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;For I was hungry, and ye gave me meat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink; I was a stranger, and ye took me in;

Naked, and ye clothed me; I was sick, and ye visited me; I was in prison, and ye came unto me.

Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, and fed thee? or thirsty, and gave thee drink? . . .

And the King shall answer and say unto them, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto me.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;“God,” I asked inwardly, “was it really You who came in the form of that desperate man?” I never saw the stranger again. To this day I’ve suspected that the encounter was God’s way of showing me that He Himself receives any act of kindness we express to others.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the message in a strange encounter&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now as we approach the Christmas season, it’s a good opportunity to introspect and cleanse our hearts of any negative emotions we may hold towards others. Throughout December, I’m taking up the personal challenge of holding only positive, loving thoughts towards everyone—be they wise or foolish; well-kempt or disheveled. Remember that love offered to any form of life is love offered to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Whispers from Eternity, Master writes: “Let every feeling that I have glow with Thy love. Let every act of my will be impregnated with Thy divine vitality. Let every thought, every expression, every ambition be ornamented by Thee.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invite you to join me in this challenge for the rest of 2022: to feel God’s love flowing through you in each moment of the day. This is the greatest gift you can give to the world. And who knows? God may come in hidden form to receive it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your sister in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Letter to God</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-letter-to-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-letter-to-god/</guid>
      <description>Dear God,
This has been a particularly eventful year, and it seems fitting that I should write You a note of gratitude.
My heart is very full, and words seem insufficient. I know that You don’t need my words of thanks any more than the sun needs to be praised for sending forth its rays, but for my own sake let me recognize how much love You shower on me.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Dear God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a particularly eventful year, and it seems fitting that I should write You a note of gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My heart is very full, and words seem insufficient. I know that You don’t need my words of thanks any more than the sun needs to be praised for sending forth its rays, but for my own sake let me recognize how much love You shower on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, thank you for this enlightened path and for the wonderful teachers You have sent. Let me thank You above all for Master and for Swamiji, who have molded my life and blessed my humble self-effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for Devi, my friend and life companion. What a joy and fulfilment our life together has been. And thank you for the joy that comes from our son and grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-letter-to-god.png&#34;  alt=&#34;a letter to god&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Divine Mother, for giving us so many loving friends. Everywhere we go You are wearing a different disguise, waiting for us with a warm smile and a new experience. Thanks, also, for the constant support and beautiful examples of discipleship with which you’ve surrounded us. What wonderful times we’ve had this last year: amazing food, interesting trips, and let’s not forget all the jokes and laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for the many outward gifts You have given us: of health, energy, and enthusiasm. I’m grateful, too, for having sufficient finances so that we not only have enough to live simply and comfortably, but also enough to share with others and to give back to You in remembrance that You are the giver of all that we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful, too, for all the tests that You’ve provided. This year, with all the travel, has been particularly helpful in stripping away so many unnecessary necessities. The constant changes have helped me drop those unwanted habits that managed to creep in, and establish new and better ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all these outward signs pale in comparison with Your inward gifts. Thank you for the peace of mind and the expansion of love that I feel when my mind begins to become still. Thank you for the inward yearning to reunite with You and for the techniques, especially Kriya, that bring me closer with each meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, thank you for the growing realization that it is all You. You are playing all the parts and doing all the deeds. It is, in a strange way, You writing this note of appreciation to Yourself. As “I” mentioned at the beginning, words seem insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With deepest gratitude and appreciation,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Celebration of God</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-celebration-of-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-celebration-of-god/</guid>
      <description>A small group of us just returned from a glorious trip to Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore—all places known for their holiness, and filled with events sacred to our line of gurus. Everywhere we saw and experienced the joyful celebration of God in many things that is characteristic of life in India, a celebration not somber and serious, but filled with exuberance.
The evening we arrived in Varanasi, we visited the ashram of Ananda Moyi Ma, the great woman saint about whom Yoganandaji writes in Autobiography of a Yogi.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A small group of us just returned from a glorious trip to Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore—all places known for their holiness, and filled with events sacred to our line of gurus. Everywhere we saw and experienced the joyful celebration of God in many things that is characteristic of life in India, a celebration not somber and serious, but filled with exuberance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening we arrived in Varanasi, we visited the ashram of Ananda Moyi Ma, the great woman saint about whom Yoganandaji writes in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt;. We meditated there on the balcony overlooking the Ganges next to the room where Ma did puja to her beloved image of Krishna, and in her small bedroom. As we sat quietly, a small boy appeared and began doing cartwheels, laughing all the while. How pleased Ma must have been, I thought, to have so much joy expressed before her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early the next morning we visited the home of Lahiri Mahasaya, where he lived, initiated people into Kriya, and left his body. Though the building is locked, there is a large stone bench across the narrow lane on which we sat to meditate. Despite the steady stream of people walking to work, children on their way to school, and noisy motorcycles, we felt a deep inner stillness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, I opened my eyes to see that many of those passing by stopped at Lahiri’s door and touched it to take his blessings. A motorcycle driven by a father with his three children on their way to school also stopped, and each one took blessings. What a wonderful way to start the school day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our time in Kolkata was one long celebration with Yoganandaji and his disciples. Our wonderful center leaders there, Dithi and Alok, along with a team of devotees, have renovated the house of Master’s boyhood friend, Tulsi Bose. It’s quite near to Master’s family home, and it is at the Bose house that Guruji spent most of his days as a teenager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Made holy by visits from great saints like Sri Yukteswar, Ananda Moyi Ma, and Vivekananda, and by the many holy relics from Babaji and our line of gurus, the house is beautifully kept now, with all the relics carefully placed in glass cases. Here we all chanted and meditated with the Kolkata devotees, and felt awash with joy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-celebration-of-god.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a celebration of god&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next we stopped at the Ghosh family home at 4 Gurpar Road, and were lovingly hosted by Master’s great-nephew, Somnath, and his wife Sarita. After meditating in the little attic room where Yoganandaji tells us he “first found God,” we were served a delicious homemade lunch. One of our group said, “It felt like a family reunion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few more days of public events in Kolkata, we took a beautiful boat ride on the Ganges at twilight to Serampore. It is here, on the riverbank, that the banyan tree still stands where Babaji appeared to Sri Yukteswar and where Sri Yukteswar’s ashram is located. As we walked to our hotel, we stopped to pray at the holy tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time of year, it is customary to celebrate Durga Puja, a ten-day holiday in honor of Durga, the goddess of strength, determination, victory, and wisdom. As part of the festival, large images of Durga are fashioned out of clay, beautifully painted and decorated, and then immersed in the Ganges to let her dissolve back into the Infinite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we prayed at the banyan tree, many groups of people carrying their images of Durga released her into the river lovingly, laughingly, joyfully. What a beautiful moment it was!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many blessings have come thus far on our trip, but the main insight I want to share with you is this: The path to God can be a celebration, a joyful release of all that we are into the infinite arms of God. Yes, we need determination to continue, but don’t forget to celebrate God’s presence every step of the way. This is what draws us closer to Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and blessings to you,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Body Touched That Sod</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/my-body-touched-that-sod/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/my-body-touched-that-sod/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I are once again in India after an absence of more than three years. There is a palpable sense of the Divine here, which Paramhansa Yogananda highlighted on March 7, 1952, as he uttered the last words of his incarnation. Swami Kriyananda recounted that momentous event in The New Path:
Master was scheduled to speak after the banquet. His brief talk was so sweet, so almost tender, that I think everyone present felt embraced in the gossamer net of his love.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I are once again in India after an absence of more than three years. There is a palpable sense of the Divine here, which Paramhansa Yogananda highlighted on March 7, 1952, as he uttered the last words of his incarnation. Swami Kriyananda recounted that momentous event in The New Path:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master was scheduled to speak after the banquet. His brief talk was so sweet, so almost tender, that I think everyone present felt embraced in the gossamer net of his love. Warmly he spoke of India and America, and of their respective contributions to world peace and true human progress. He talked of their future cooperation. Finally he read his beautiful poem, “My India.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout his speech I was busy recording his words, keeping my eyes on my notebook. He came to the last lines of the poem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Where Ganges, woods, Himalayan caves, and men dream God.

I am hallowed; my body touched that sod!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sod became a long-drawn-out sigh. Suddenly from all sides of the room there came a loud cry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though we have been here for only a few days, on some subtle plane I, too, feel hallowed that my feet are touching this sacred land. One can feel an elusive holiness in the very air of this land. Swami Kriyananda writes, “God chooses those who choose Him.” Over and again through the long mists of time, great souls who have inhabited India have chosen God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor is it only the great saints who focus their lives around a relationship with the Divine. The head of our charitable work in Brindaban, which takes care of thousands of widow-mothers, told us this story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the care workers came upon an elderly lady who was quite upset, muttering to herself, “He hasn’t eaten for two days, and I’m getting quite hungry. I am going to have to get a stick and beat him until he agrees to eat. I don’t know what to do with that naughty Krishna.” She had made a vow, you see, to feed her beloved Krishna before she would take food herself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/my-body-touched-that-sod.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;my body touched that sod&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda on the Ganges during his return trip to India in 1935.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master starts his great book, &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt;, with these words, “The characteristic features of Indian culture have long been a search for ultimate verities and the concomitant disciple-guru relationship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, it is September 12th, the anniversary of Swami Kriyananda meeting Yogananda. Swamiji showed us, in the clearest possible way, how to draw God’s grace. As he knelt for the first time at his guru’s feet, he uttered those simple, yet life-changing words that draw God’s love: “I want to be your disciple.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those enchanted words are, of course, only the first step: an affirmation that starts the process of transformation. They must then be reinforced by the discipline of discipleship, by a daily practice of meditation, and by deep self-offering. This, too, Swami Kriyananda modeled for us in every imaginable way. His discipleship to Master became the very core of his self-definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can all choose to do the same. That devotee of Krishna offered her love in the form of physical food. But yogis must offer the ego itself to God. Over time, as we do so, the veils of separation become ever more transparent. Then, our lives, too, become hallowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let God Decide</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-god-decide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-god-decide/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I have been spending a month at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, where there is great reverence for St. Francis. Paramhansa Yogananda, too, honored him, calling him his “patron saint.”
A few years after Ananda’s arrival in Italy, word began to reach Swami Kriyananda, who was residing here at the time, that the Bishop of Assisi had been issuing warnings against us. Apparently, Church authorities had come to consider our presence there a threat.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I have been spending a month at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, where there is great reverence for St. Francis. Paramhansa Yogananda, too, honored him, calling him his “patron saint.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years after Ananda’s arrival in Italy, word began to reach Swami Kriyananda, who was residing here at the time, that the Bishop of Assisi had been issuing warnings against us. Apparently, Church authorities had come to consider our presence there a threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda, being a very forthright person, decided to have a talk with him. In many ways they turned out to be kindred souls: both of them highly intelligent, well educated, and sincere in their spirituality. After spending some time discussing spiritual matters, Swamiji was about to take his leave. As he was at the door the Bishop said, “I enjoyed our time together and really like you. Too bad you aren’t a Christian.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji, knowing that it would be useless to argue, replied with a twinkle in his eye, “You say I am not a Christian, and I say I am. Let’s let Jesus decide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thought, “Let’s let God decide,” should be like a mantra, a compass that guides our life. It is a shorthand way of saying, “Not my will, nor your will, but God’s will.” For devotees of this path, we might translate it as, “What would Master do?” or, “What does my own higher Self advise for me?” How many arguments could be avoided if we let this attitude guide us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda put it this way: “Learning to love our relatives is simply a training in stretching our consciousness. It is a preliminary practice in loving all others as we do our relations, whom we think of as our own. We have to learn to look on family and strangers alike, because all are children of God. He has given you certain family members with whom you are practicing stretching your consciousness. When the husband serves the wife, and she serves him, each with the desire to see the other happy, Christ Consciousness—God’s loving Cosmic Intelligence that permeates every atom of creation—has begun to express itself through their consciousness. Whenever you do something for someone else, without any selfish motive, you have stepped into the sphere of Christ Consciousness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we align our heart and mind with those of the stretched consciousness of a master, we have a polestar to guide us. If we could simply remember to ask the question, “What do you advise?” most problems in life, and especially in relationships, could be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I have recently finished a ten-class course, How to Develop Harmonious Relationships. In it we explore all facets of relationships of every kind: personal and intimate ones as well as others such as friendships and those that are work-related.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-god-decide.png&#34;  alt=&#34;let god decide&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all relationships are expressions of the Christ consciousness, but the more we are caught up in desires, attachments, and ego, the more conflicts arise. Human emotions, especially negative ones, are a labyrinth with no exit. The only real solution is to rise above the limiting walls of ego into the free skies of higher consciousness. How? By remembering to ask God or a master, “What do you advise here?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking is one part of the picture. Listening for His response is the other part. God won’t intrude on our free will, so we must first be truly ready to accept His advice. Then we must allow our minds and emotions to become still. He loves us as His very own, and is waiting for us to turn to Him. When we do, He will answer us with a soft and loving whisper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you are about to argue a point, follow Swami Kriyananda’s model and say, perhaps with a twinkle in your eye, “Let’s let God decide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In His all-embracing love,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Only Knew ...</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-only-knew/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-only-knew/</guid>
      <description>“If you only knew how much God loved you, you would die for joy.” These words from St. Jean Vianney, a French saint of the nineteenth century, have always inspired and motivated me spiritually.
Jyotish and I are visiting Ananda’s community and retreat center outside of Assisi now, and are staying in the lovely guest apartment of two good friends, Shantidev and Radhika. On the wall in one of the rooms is a print of a beautiful Indian painting called, “Enter the Spiritual World.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“If you only knew how much God loved you, you would die for joy.” These words from St. Jean Vianney, a French saint of the nineteenth century, have always inspired and motivated me spiritually.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/if-you-only-knew.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;if you only knew&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Jyotish and I are visiting Ananda’s community and retreat center outside of Assisi now, and are staying in the lovely guest apartment of two good friends, Shantidev and Radhika. On the wall in one of the rooms is a print of a beautiful Indian painting called, “Enter the Spiritual World.” It depicts Krishna tenderly embracing one of his devotees in a pastoral setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked Shantidev what the story was behind the painting, and here is what he recounted. The devotee being embraced is Gopal Kumar, who, in a past incarnation, had been one of the gopis with Krishna in Brindaban. Through subsequent lives of spiritual seeking, Gopal Kumar had become a great yogi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now he had reached the stage where all he wanted was to achieve union with God. In his quest he traveled throughout the three worlds—causal, astral, and physical—to find what he was seeking. Still, his life’s burning goal eluded him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally he arrived in Goloka Brindaban, the dimension where Krishna resides in the spiritual realm. Here, after many incarnations of separation, he beheld Krishna once again. There was an immediate mutual recognition; Krishna enfolded his dear devotee, Gopal Kumar, in a loving embrace. And just then, to everyone’s alarm, Krishna fainted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the devotees gasped, not knowing what had befallen their beloved Lord. They fanned him and rubbed his feet, and eventually Krishna returned to consciousness. He explained that he had been so full of ecstasy and joy to meet Gopal Kumar again after their long separation that he had lost consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a beautiful thought to reflect upon: &lt;em&gt;that God is even more ecstatic than we are when one of His lost children returns home&lt;/em&gt;. Jean Vianney described the transcendent joy that comes to that devotee who knows God’s love, and Krishna shows us the completion of divine union: God’s joy is even greater than our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is life’s tests and challenges that help us to feel God’s love more deeply. Recently while in Assisi, Jyotish and I contracted Covid, which fortunately was a very mild case. Now we are almost totally recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During our illness, we received such an outpouring of love, support, and prayers from friends around the world that we were deeply touched. As we read the many notes, we were moved at how God’s love for us is sometimes expressed outwardly through divine friendship. Often when we need it the most, we get glimpses of how much we are loved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Gopal Kumar, let’s continue on our journey to find Oneness with God. One day, we will know the fullness of His love and merge with it into ecstasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where the Answers Live</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/where-the-answers-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/where-the-answers-live/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever lost something and searched for it everywhere? Of course you have! So have we all. You may hunt here and there, but finally a moment comes when you realize, “I’ve been looking in the wrong place.” Unfortunately, we look in the wrong place not only for things but, more importantly, for the answers to our deepest questions.
The answers to important questions lie more in the heart than in the head.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever lost something and searched for it everywhere? Of course you have! So have we all. You may hunt here and there, but finally a moment comes when you realize, “I’ve been looking in the wrong place.” Unfortunately, we look in the wrong place not only for things but, more importantly, for the answers to our deepest questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to important questions lie more in the heart than in the head. Swami Kriyananda told us that true wisdom comes from a combination of pure feeling and discrimination. God has given us both discrimination (buddhi) and feeling (chitta) to navigate this world. But in this age, our purified feeling nature “burns low, and is ill attended.” In such an imbalanced age we can rarely see clearly until we are uplifted by the warm currents of the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is from the heart that intuitive answers whisper to us. After his first great experience of cosmic consciousness, Paramhansa Yogananda said, “I cognized the center of the empyrean as a point of intuitive perception in my heart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuitive answers can only come once we are calm. Recently an elderly friend of ours had lost a container of protein powder. Not only she, but many of her friends searched high and low with no success. Finally, she said, “Let’s ask Master for the answer.” After they had centered themselves for a few minutes she declared, “Look on the shelf in my bedroom closet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve already looked there,” they protested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let’s look again,” she said, undeterred. Sure enough, there it was. It had fallen over behind some clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding something like protein powder is a relatively trivial thing, but the intuitive heart also holds the solutions to more vital questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your heart knows your true purpose.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your intuition already knows your unique pathway to spiritual freedom. If you can calm the restless thoughts and listen sensitively to the deep feelings in your heart you will know your purpose in life. Once you have clarity on this, all else will begin to fall into place as you set out on a journey of wonder and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ananda Village just celebrated its fifty-third anniversary on July 4th, a date we share with the founding of America. In the beginning, only Swamiji discerned the true purpose of Ananda: not political, but spiritual freedom. He said, “Since we are all seeking the same goal, it will be easier if we gather together and support one another in our quest.” He then set about gathering a small group of those attuned to Yogananda’s ray and willing to work together. Since our founding a half-century ago, that little group has grown into a worldwide army of truth seekers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/where-the-answers-live.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;where the answers live&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your heart knows how to connect to others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world filled with polarity and conflict, we need to prioritize loving connections with one another. Divine Mother loves everyone, and if we attune to Her vibration we, too, will feel that everyone is our brother or sister. As long as humanity stays divided, it will continue to find reasons to judge and to hate one another. The desperate need of our time is to give ascendance to acceptance and friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are with others, listen and speak to them from your heart. Feel behind their words to their unspoken yearnings and needs. And let both your eyes and words radiate loving balms of kindness and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The heart will lead us to God.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it is the heart that will lead us to God. In meditation we must go beyond thoughts to find God. As Master’s chant says: “Thee I find behind the fringe of my mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the techniques of meditation, sit quietly and feel deep devotion in your heart. Go beyond mere thoughts into the deep yearnings of your soul. When the magnet of your love is strong enough, God will no longer be able to stay hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the heart,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
