<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>God on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/tags/god/</link>
    <description>Recent content in God on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda-email.netlify.app/tags/god/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Can I Best Help Them?</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</guid>
      <description>Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”
We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to meditate before talking with them&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the fruits of meditation is the ability to detach yourself from the events around you and maintain a state of inner equilibrium under all circumstances. This is by no means easy, but needs to be cultivated continuously with energy and determination. During your meditation before meeting them, visualize them surrounded by God’s light and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept people as they are, while at the same time relating to their own higher nature.&lt;/strong&gt; If people feel accepted, it allows them the space to self-correct the behaviors that are causing them unhappiness. While meeting with them, pray and see them resting in their true self—divine love and wisdom. Unconditional acceptance is what God offers all of His children. Try to be a channel of this for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/how-can-i-best-help-them.png&#34;  alt=&#34;how can i best help them&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give direct advice unless they ask; rather, listen attentively so that they feel open to share with you.&lt;/strong&gt; Often an open ear is all people are really seeking. You can inwardly ask God to guide them from within themselves. If they do ask for advice, present it in a positive, nonjudgmental way. A beautiful passage from Master in this regard is: “I am the servant ready to serve all needy minds with my simple advice, with my gifts of healing truth, and with my humble wisdom gathered in the shrine of silence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you feel yourself getting engaged in negativity, quickly and consciously detach yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Be attentive to your own reactions, and inwardly strive to remain centered. Without seeming to withdraw, hold your mind at the spiritual eye. You can also quietly practice regular breathing: inhaling, holding the breath, and exhaling to the same count. Yoganandaji wrote: “When fear or anger or any kind of suffering comes to me, I will view it as a spectator. I will separate myself from my experiences. At all costs I will endeavor to retain my peace and happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always send love. Don’t withhold this no matter how difficult the situation.&lt;/strong&gt; Once a friend of ours was working as a doctor in an emergency room. Late one night, the police brought in a drunken, homeless man who had fallen and broken his arm. He was screaming, both with pain and fear, and it took two policemen to hold him down. To their amazement, our friend told the policemen to leave the treatment room—that she could handle him alone. Surrounding him in love, our friend was able to get the man to calm down so that she could set his arm. Afterwards the poor man looked at her beseechingly with eyes filled with years of loneliness and want, and asked, “Will you be my doctor?” He felt her love surrounding him—a feeling he hadn’t known for a long time. Healing can take place on many levels. By expressing love and forgiveness, not only can we help others, but we can remain uplifted as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, offer them to God for His help. Remember that God is always in charge of guiding every soul to inner freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; We are all on a journey to find the truth of who and what we really are. Offer a helping hand to others, when you can, but remember that ultimately, true happiness and freedom come when we allow God to guide our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these words of Master’s: “I will be a fisher of souls. I will catch the ignorance of others in a net of my wisdom and offer it for transmutation to the God of all gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With loving friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding God in the Big City</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/finding-god-in-the-big-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/finding-god-in-the-big-city/</guid>
      <description>Twenty million people! That’s the population of the Greater Los Angeles area, we were told recently when we visited friends and Ananda centers there.
For one of our satsangs, in Torrance, the center leader asked us to talk about how to find spirituality in big-city life. I thought you, too, might be interested in the thoughts we shared that evening on the challenges faced by city-dwellers and some of the spiritual solutions to them.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Twenty million people! That’s the population of the Greater Los Angeles area, we were told recently when we visited friends and Ananda centers there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one of our satsangs, in Torrance, the center leader asked us to talk about how to find spirituality in big-city life. I thought you, too, might be interested in the thoughts we shared that evening on the challenges faced by city-dwellers and some of the spiritual solutions to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;distraction-vs-focused-attention&#34;&gt;Distraction vs. Focused Attention&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving on big-city freeways is an experience in itself. It’s almost overwhelming to deal with the long commutes, the speed of the traffic, and the constantly flashing billboards screaming (as a friend of ours once humorously put it), “Eat me. Buy me. Take me home!” The mind gets scattered in a myriad of different directions, and even after arriving at your destination, it takes an effort of will to get focused again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no small obstacle to achieving peace of mind, but the opportunity is also there: to keep the mind more concentrated on whatever we’re doing. Build up the habit of attentive awareness in everything you do—talking with a friend, working on a project at your job, going for a walk. While driving, listen to something uplifting—beautiful music or an inspiring talk—and give it your attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more you make the conscious effort to concentrate, the more will you find yourself actively and rewardingly engaged in every area of your life. And the greater will your ability be to go deep in meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;self-interest-vs-self-giving&#34;&gt;Self-Interest vs. Self-Giving&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forces of competition and self-interest are strong in any large group. Even lab rats turn on one another when placed in overcrowded tanks. The seeming cold indifference in a big city may lead us to think, “If I don’t look out for ‘Number One,’ how will I get by?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity here is to counter the pull of self-interest by consciously finding ways to serve and to give to others. We have a friend in Los Angeles who would give her daughters a small weekly allowance, and then (at their request) drive them to an area where homeless people lived, so that they could give their money away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find ways to help others, even at your own inconvenience or loss. Keeping the heart open to those in need frees us from preoccupation with the demands of our limited self. Ultimately we realize that God alone is the provider, and that the more we give, the more we are given. Self-giving also leads us to experience a loving connection with all of life.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/finding-god-in-the-big-city.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;finding-god-in-the-big-city&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;self-indulgence-vs-self-control&#34;&gt;Self-Indulgence vs. Self-Control&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big-city life offers many dark pathways that lead to overstimulation of the senses, even to the point of self-destruction. Master set up his headquarters in Los Angeles, and lived there for nearly twenty-five years. He would sometimes walk up and down some of the seedy, bar-lined streets in order to bring light and upliftment to the poor souls there trapped in addictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity for us here is to examine our own life and find areas where we lack sufficient self-control. Take up a challenge with the thought, “I will practice inner discipline so that others may follow my lead and develop self-control in their life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’ve improved in one area, take up another challenge, until you begin to see that you—not old habits or karma—are in charge of your life. What freedom comes with this realization!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;downward-emotions-vs-uplifted-feelings&#34;&gt;Downward Emotions vs. Uplifted Feelings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer number of life stories and struggles in a big city can create a fog of hopelessness and despair. Especially now with economic and political uncertainty rife—and with the possibility looming on the horizon of even worse to come—it’s easy to be pulled down into negativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To counter this tendency, we should strive energetically to keep hope and joy foremost in our minds. One of my favorite quotes of Master’s is, “Life is a battle for joy every step of the way. May I fight to win the battle on the very spot where I now stand.” These words have stood me in good stead through many a difficult situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you choose joy under all circumstances, you begin to find that joy is your constant companion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, finding God in big-city life comes down to this: In each of life’s circumstances, choose the highest and best road to follow. And use all of your strength and commitment to stay the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember these words of Yoganandaji: “There are no obstacles, only opportunities.” Your very effort will uplift those around you, whether you live in a big city or a small ashram. Then you become, as Swami Kriyananda used to say, “part of the solution, not the problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from the Snow</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/lessons-from-the-snow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/lessons-from-the-snow/</guid>
      <description>We have been experiencing historic snowfalls in Northern California. Hard as it is to imagine, some areas near Lake Tahoe have gotten nearly fifty feet of snow so far, with more on the way! Much less has fallen at Ananda Village, but still we’ve gotten more than any time in recent memory. With hills, freezing temperatures, and snowy roads, many of us have been snowbound. Here is the view from our living room this morning.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We have been experiencing historic snowfalls in Northern California. Hard as it is to imagine, some areas near Lake Tahoe have gotten nearly fifty feet of snow so far, with more on the way! Much less has fallen at Ananda Village, but still we’ve gotten more than any time in recent memory. With hills, freezing temperatures, and snowy roads, many of us have been snowbound. Here is the view from our living room this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For restless people, conditions like these are probably a torment. For yogis, being forced to go within is actually quite nice. The snow brings with it some wonderful lessons. Here are a few that have struck me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;give-help-receive-help&#34;&gt;Give Help, Receive Help&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During times of hardship, people of goodwill rise to the occasion. At Ananda Village our maintenance crews have worked around the clock to help people cope with the icy roads; our market staff has been delivering food orders to residents; and many of us are feeding the birds and animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-minded people naturally want to serve others. But the snow is bringing another lesson: to be willing and grateful to receive help when offered. Many devotees are better at giving than receiving. This is a good quality in moderation, but becomes a spiritual flaw when taken too far. We need to learn the art of receiving also. Everything in life is a gift from the Divine. It delays our spiritual progress if we ignore or reject the help that is given to us. In meditation our first act should be to open our hearts, receive God’s presence, and silently say, “Thank you, God.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/lessons-from-the-snow.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;lessons-from-the-snow&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;use-the-time-well&#34;&gt;Use the Time Well&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having one’s schedule disrupted can be a good thing, if you are flexible and can shift your energies to alternative activities. It sounds like this should be easy, but restlessness is one of the great curses of our times. According to our great Masters, we live in a rajasic (restless) age on a rajasic planet in a rajasic galaxy. Is it any wonder that people are habituated, even addicted, to activity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental restlessness is perhaps the greatest block to meditation. When circumstances shut down our normal schedule, let’s use the time to turn our consciousness upward. For me personally the snow gave me some time to paint for which I was joyfully grateful. The inspiration came to do a pair of paintings of the same scene at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dawn” and “Midnight,” the two paintings I drew during the snowstorm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;live-more-in-god&#34;&gt;Live More in God&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest gift of inwardness, whether forced or voluntary, is the opportunity to turn a quieted mind toward living in God’s presence. No matter the conditions or the place, we can always choose to turn our minds and hearts Godward. Yoganandaji stated it so poetically in this beautiful poem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wherever-we-go&#34;&gt;Wherever We Go&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Whether in Himalayan caves or crowded subway;

Whether in the concrete jungle of modern life,

Or in a simple village in Hindustan:

Wherever we go, teach us to seek Thee out

In all Thy secret nooks—east, west, north, south—everywhere!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I pray that for all of us, we can see behind every circumstance, good or bad, the hidden opportunity to live more in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
