<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>help on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/help/</link>
    <description>Recent content in help on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/help/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Swami Kriyananda Worked With People</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/how-swami-kriyananda-worked-with-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/how-swami-kriyananda-worked-with-people/</guid>
      <description>It is not easy these days to find models of righteous leadership. We see plenty of negative examples but few that truly inspire us. I thought it would be helpful to write about Swami Kriyananda, the most uplifting example of leadership that I’ve ever encountered. Not only did he teach principles of good leadership but, more importantly, he modeled them in his own life. Here are some of the key points he shared:</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;It is not easy these days to find models of righteous leadership. We see plenty of negative examples but few that truly inspire us. I thought it would be helpful to write about Swami Kriyananda, the most uplifting example of leadership that I’ve ever encountered. Not only did he teach principles of good leadership but, more importantly, he modeled them in his own life. Here are some of the key points he shared:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on principles:&lt;/strong&gt; Swamiji was very clear about the ultimate purpose of life: to achieve Self-realization personally, and to help others do the same. When working with people, he always guided them toward the appropriate next step in expanding their consciousness, but he also recognized that every person was different. One time after a Kriya Initiation, during which he had blessed each person individually, he told us, “I had an amazing experience. As I blessed each person, I could see his unique pathway to God, and every one was different.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work with each individual as they need:&lt;/strong&gt; For me, and I think it was true for many of the men, he mainly guided me by working on projects. We would often talk over community decisions, and he would offer advice on how to accomplish something. At first I thought he was talking about the project, but later I realized the advice was usually his way of helping me change my attitudes. One time he corrected me strongly because I was blocking a project that I was sure would fail. He said, “Let him try, even if he doesn’t succeed. That’s the way he will learn and grow.” But he was also saying, “Each person has to play out his own karma. Don’t be too eager to interfere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be patient:&lt;/strong&gt; He rarely gave personal advice until he thought a person was ready to accept it. There was a woman at Ananda Village who drove everyone crazy by being bossy and critical. One time our son, about seven years old at the time, came home crying and asked us, “Who made her the boss of the world?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many complaints, Swamiji finally said, “I’ll talk to her.” We all waited expectantly for the details of how he had told her off. We found out, though, that he had simply invited her to dinner and praised her for her high energy. He knew she was too fragile to hear criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, for those who were ready, he could be very direct. If we were dedicated to finding God and serving the mission of the Masters, he didn’t hold back. Often he gave us advice or assignments that were quite untimely. He sent Devi and me along with our young son, first to San Francisco and later to Italy, even though it was very disruptive to our family life. When we asked him about the effect on our son, he said, “He chose you as parents. When you serve selflessly, he also reaps the benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/how-swami-kriyananda-worked-with-people.png&#34;  alt=&#34;how-swami-kriyananda-worked-with-people&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help everyone:&lt;/strong&gt; Swamiji not only helped his friends, but often went out of his way to comfort strangers. One time he bought an expensive massage table for a young man he’d met for the first time. The man burst into tears. “I grew up on the streets as an orphan,” he said, “having always to fend for myself. The one thing I have always yearned for was the love of a father. Today I felt it for the first time in my life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How we work with others is an indication of how we work with ourselves. We can apply the principles above to our own lives as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always make major decisions in attunement with your highest principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work with different parts of yourself as if they were individuals. Be firm with those habits and attitudes where you’re ready and willing to grow. Be patient with yourself in areas where you still have heavy resistance to changing. If you keep making a spiritual effort, the resistance will eventually fall away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Help everyone, including strangers. Every great religion has some version of this advice: Do unto others as you would have them do unto you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Short Memory</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-short-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-short-memory/</guid>
      <description>“Are you there, God? Are you listening to my prayers? Do you even know what I’m going through?”
I think we all have thoughts like these from time to time—especially when we’re facing challenges in life. To keep our faith strong, it’s important to remember those times—and we’ve all had them—when our prayers have in fact been answered.
Recently a friend told me about a trip she’d taken in which she encountered one hurdle after another.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“Are you there, God? Are you listening to my prayers? Do you even know what I’m going through?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we all have thoughts like these from time to time—especially when we’re facing challenges in life. To keep our faith strong, it’s important to remember those times—and we’ve all had them—when our prayers have in fact been answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend told me about a trip she’d taken in which she encountered one hurdle after another. The final blow came when she was driving home alone at night from the airport and realized she had a flat tire. Not knowing what to do, she was about to panic when a friend “coincidentally” drove by. He stopped his car and helped her change the tire; soon she was on her way home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her story reminded me of an incident in my own life that happened about fifteen years ago—one that I’d forgotten. A friend of mine had been diagnosed with widespread cancer. To slow the disease’s advance, she began receiving intravenous chemotherapy. A group of her friends would take turns driving her to the chemo sessions, and would sit with her throughout the day until she was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marilyn (this was her name) was a quiet, gentle soul who was a devoted follower of Yoganandaji. She never complained about her diagnosis, the treatments, the changes they wrought on her body, nor the upheaval the disease caused in her life. She passed away peacefully about a year after this story took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that particular day, Marilyn had finished her latest chemotherapy session, and I was driving her back to Ananda Village. It was late afternoon; exhausted from the treatment, Marilyn reclined in the passenger seat and drifted off to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were a few miles away from Ananda on a rural road, when suddenly I heard the dreaded “thump, thump, thump,” and knew we had a flat tire. I pulled over to the side of the road, and not knowing how to change a tire nor seeing anyone around, inwardly I offered a desperate prayer for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just at that moment, an old, beat-up pickup truck pulled over in front of us. Two disreputable-looking characters with long, greasy hair and dirty clothes came over to the car. Since I didn’t know what to expect, I cautiously rolled my window down a crack. To my great relief one of them said, “Looks like you ladies can use a little help.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order, they changed the tire and were on their way. I was sitting in stunned silence, when Marilyn opened her eyes and quietly asked, “What happened?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think God just heard my prayer,” was my quiet reply.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-short-memory.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a short memory&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Left to right) Jitendra Mazumdar, companion on the “penniless test” at Brindaban; Lalita-da, Master’s cousin; Swami Kebalananda, Master’s saintly Sanskrit tutor; and Master, as a high school youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most beautiful and powerful chapters in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt; is “Two Penniless Boys in Brindaban,” in which Yoganandaji’s eldest brother, Ananta, challenges him to put his faith in God to a test. Ananta proposes that young Yoganandaji travel to the nearby city of Agra with a friend, Jitendra, but with no money and no return ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complete the test, they must not beg, reveal their predicament to anyone, nor miss any meals. Further, the boys must see the sights of Agra and return home by train before midnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps feeling some remorse for sending two young boys on such a journey, the skeptical Ananta added: “If by any chance or grace you pass successfully through the Brindaban ordeal, I shall ask you to initiate me as your disciple.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are familiar with the rest of the story. While still on the train to Brindaban, they were approached by two strangers who invited them to lunch at their ashram. The meal turned out to be a sumptuous repast prepared for two princes, patrons of the ashram who at the last minute were unable to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they were leaving the ashram, replete from their elaborate banquet, Jitendra complained, “A fine mess you have got me into! Our luncheon was only accidental good fortune! How can we see the sights of this city, without a single pice between us? And how on earth are you going to take me back to Ananta’s?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda’s reply was one we all need to remember: “You forget God quickly, now that your stomach is filled.” His account continues, “My words, not bitter, were accusatory. &lt;strong&gt;How short is human memory for divine favors! No man lives who has not seen certain of his prayers granted.&lt;/strong&gt;” (If you haven’t read the Autobiography, I’ll let you discover for yourself how the story ends.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, how short our memory is for the graces we have received. As you finish reading these words, I suggest that you take a moment to recall an instance in your own life of an answered prayer, or a feeling of certainty of God’s love for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great saints tell us that God’s blessings, guidance, and protection are always with us. It is we who too often forget them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking always to remember,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
