<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>purpose on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/purpose/</link>
    <description>Recent content in purpose on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/purpose/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Children of the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/children-of-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/children-of-the-light/</guid>
      <description>When Swami Kriyananda wrote the Festival of Light, a ceremony we read each Sunday at Ananda centers, he included an allegory depicting the journey of the soul. It ends with these thrilling words about the purpose of life:
[Evolution] had but this for its design: The birth of life, And, with life’s birth, the dawn of self-awareness: Passage through dim corridors of waking consciousness To emerge at last into infinite light— Into perfect Joy!</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;When Swami Kriyananda wrote the Festival of Light, a ceremony we read each Sunday at Ananda centers, he included an allegory depicting the journey of the soul. It ends with these thrilling words about the purpose of life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Evolution] had but this for its design: The birth of life,
And, with life’s birth, the dawn of self-awareness:
Passage through dim corridors of waking consciousness
To emerge at last into infinite light—
Into perfect Joy!

O Children of Light, forsake the darkness!
Know that, forever, you and He are one!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The theme of the evolution of consciousness is woven repeatedly throughout the great teachings of India. First there is the long, more-or-less automatic, evolution through the reincarnations prior to reaching the human form. This passage through the dim corridors of waking consciousness reaches its pinnacle in the higher animals, who can sometimes demonstrate extraordinary intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a remarkable dog in our family named Nipper. I grew up in Decorah, Iowa, and across from our house was a large park used for picnics by the residents of the town. Many Sundays would find Nipper entertaining large crowds. He had learned how to climb the steep ladder of a ten-foot slide and then slide down. This he would do repeatedly until a big audience had gathered to cheer him on. My brother and I would lurk on the outskirts of the group, secretly proud of our dog, but too embarrassed to publicly reveal our relationship with this shameless exhibitionist.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/children-of-the-light.png&#34;  alt=&#34;children-of-the-light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even more remarkable is the story of Koko, a gorilla who could communicate through sign language. She had a vocabulary of more than a thousand words, and understood twice that many. Koko helped people break down the delusion that only humans have intelligence, compassion, and love. Here is a link to a video showing some of her extraordinary interactions, and another to one of her with the actor/comedian, Robin Williams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next major phase of evolutionary development comes when we reach the human form. Now we have an advanced nervous system and, more importantly, an astral spine, including the chakras, which gives us the capacity to achieve enlightenment. With our heightened abilities comes also both the gift and the curse of free will. Our job now is to choose to expand our consciousness and, eventually, dissolve the ego—the sense of separation from God. To accomplish this, we must develop the extraordinary powers of our mind and will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “When the ‘can’t’ disappears from your mind, divine power comes. You have to pour forth will power continuously through constructive actions. When you persist, refusing to accept failure, the object of will must materialize. In that kind of will lies God’s answer, because will comes from God, and continuous will is divine will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This determination of mind and will enables us to fulfill the objects of our desire. At first, being centered in the ego, we seek possessions, pleasure, and power. But as our consciousness evolves, so also does the focus of our desires. Master says that after countless lives we feel an “anguishing monotony”; our search turns inward, and our yearning is for God alone. While it is good to be energetic in our efforts, it is also good to relax and enjoy the process. Divine Mother is lovingly watching over us as we progress from crawling to toddling, walking, running, and, finally, soaring into the skies of awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation, of course, is central, but so is living in joy, love, and service throughout the day. Eventually the self-doubts fade, the “cant’s” disappear, and we actually live the immortal lines that Swamiji wrote: “O Children of Light, forsake the darkness! Know that, forever, you and He are one!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s love and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Trunk and the Branches</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-trunk-and-the-branches/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-trunk-and-the-branches/</guid>
      <description>About six months after Swami Kriyananda passed from this world, Devi and I had a Nadi reading about our life—past, present, and future. This experience was fascinating on many levels. The pundit who did the reading had only our birth date, time, and place: the standard information needed to cast an astrological chart. Using this, he found in his storage room long, narrow wooden boxes containing ancient Sanskrit writing on palm leaves with readings for each of us.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;About six months after Swami Kriyananda passed from this world, Devi and I had a Nadi reading about our life—past, present, and future. This experience was fascinating on many levels. The pundit who did the reading had only our birth date, time, and place: the standard information needed to cast an astrological chart. Using this, he found in his storage room long, narrow wooden boxes containing ancient Sanskrit writing on palm leaves with readings for each of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda wrote a small booklet, India’s Ancient Book of Prophecy, about a similar reading he had during the time he lived in India. These profound readings were written many thousands of years ago by sages who were able to transcend the limitations of time. Nadi readings come from the line of Sukhdev, a revered Indian master. The information itself was fascinating, and perhaps I will write about it another time. The purpose of this blog, however, is different.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-trunk-and-the-branches.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the trunk and the branches&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reading began by addressing the reason for my present incarnation. It said, “The purpose of this incarnation is moksha (spiritual liberation) and Guru seva.” Other friends who have had readings were told quite different reasons for this life, showing the uniqueness of each individual path. These two, however, are the core energy of my life, and as long as I stay aligned with that intent there will be a flow of energy and grace from the Infinite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone is able to have such a reading. However, it would be helpful to introspect and try to feel the core purpose of your own life, the trunk of your particular tree. What motivates and energizes you? Look for themes that have been there since early childhood. For me, there was always a deep and abiding desire to know truth at the deepest level possible. Only later did that core energy eventually lead me to read Autobiography of a Yogi and to meet Swami Kriyananda. As you meditate, try to feel the essential aspiration of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have a sense of your purpose, it is important to honor it and allow it to guide your major life choices. As long as you stay aligned to your core purpose, the forms in which it will be expressed will reveal themselves. Those who stray from their essential vibration never seem to feel settled in anything they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The driving force of Swami Kriyananda’s life was his discipleship to Yogananda. When he read Autobiography of a Yogi as a young man, it awakened in him his life direction. As he traveled from New York to California in 1948 to meet Yogananda for the first time, he said his predominant thought was, “I want to find God, and I want to share Him with everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, it’s the seventy-fifth anniversary of Swami Kriyananda’s meeting his guru. His first words that day were, “I want to be your disciple.” This was his essence, and his life became a creative expression of that intention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Groups, too, have a core purpose. To a certain extent the purpose of my life—moksha and Guru seva—are shared by many who have been drawn to Ananda. Many of us feel that we incarnated in order to find God and to help Paramhansa Yogananda and Swami Kriyananda with their mission in this age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a great power and grace that flows to those who stay attuned to this particular ray. This is not meant to be exclusive. There are many true paths, and even among the disciples of Paramhansa Yogananda there are several different valid groups, each with its own basic vibration and purpose. Master, in this case, is the trunk and each group is a different branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends, I urge you to take some time to clarify your life’s purpose. All else will follow naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
