<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Index on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Index on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda-email.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Anxiety</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/overcoming-anxiety/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/overcoming-anxiety/</guid>
      <description>Anxiety is one of the diseases of our age, affecting almost two-thirds of the population, with nearly a third finding it debilitating.
Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The main causes of nervousness are 1) long-continued overactivity, 2) excessive stimulation of the senses from physical overindulgence, and 3) mental overstimulation from chronic fear, anger, sorrow, hatred, jealousy, discontent, or similar harmful emotions.
“Any violent or prolonged excitement disturbs the flow of life force through the nervous system.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Anxiety is one of the diseases of our age, affecting almost two-thirds of the population, with nearly a third finding it debilitating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The main causes of nervousness are 1) long-continued overactivity, 2) excessive stimulation of the senses from physical overindulgence, and 3) mental overstimulation from chronic fear, anger, sorrow, hatred, jealousy, discontent, or similar harmful emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any violent or prolonged excitement disturbs the flow of life force through the nervous system. If you put a two-thousand-volt current through a fifty-watt lamp, it will burn out the lamp. In the same way, excessive stimulation burns the nerves, cutting off the supply of energy and upsetting the functioning of the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most damaging emotions are anger and fear. Anger burns the nerves in the brain and causes poisons to be secreted throughout the body. Fear burns the nerves that supply the heart and can cause heart trouble. Feelings of timidity destroy the nerve endings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety, therefore, can be seen as a disease of the nerves, and the following physical methods can help cool our system and alleviate symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, water is an excellent nerve tonic, so bathing, swimming, or even taking a cold shower can help. Yogananda taught that lime juice in water sweetened to neither sweet nor sour can soothe the nerves. Satwic foods, particularly fruit, will cool the nerves, while tamasic foods, excessive spices, or overeating will be harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, exercise and walking, especially in nature, can help reset the entire system. Hippocrates is reported to have said, “If you are in a bad mood go for a walk. If you are still in a bad mood go for another walk.” Yogananda’s Energization Exercises, yoga postures, and the affirmations of the Ananda Yoga system are specifically designed to strengthen and realign the flow of prana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, sleep is very healing. If you have trouble falling asleep, try this: First relax your entire face including the tongue; next, drop your shoulders and let your hands drop to your sides. Then exhale, relaxing your chest, and focus on the breath; let your lower body and limbs relax, succumbing to the pull of gravity. Finally, clear your mind of all thoughts for ten seconds. The US military teaches this system (it sounds like it is straight out of a yoga class) and reports that a vast majority of people can learn to fall asleep within two minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/overcoming-anxiety.png&#34;  alt=&#34;overcoming anxiety&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since the most damaging emotions are anger and fear, it’s essential to control these sentiments actively. Accept that anxiety is an emotional condition and not amenable to logic. News and media, especially opinions, are designed to evoke fear and anger, so avoid that mental poison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t control the uncontrollable, especially world situations that have little direct influence on our daily lives. Focus on changing yourself, since this is all you can actually control, and even that is a Herculean task. “Do your best and forget tomorrow” is Yogananda’s advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;meditation-and-faith&#34;&gt;Meditation and Faith&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation is a powerful tool for calming the mind and reducing stress. It allows us to step back from the constant chatter of our thoughts and emotions, and to connect with a deeper sense of peace and stillness within ourselves. Regular meditation and breathing techniques will rewire the brain, making us less vulnerable to stress and anxiety. Serving others will break the tendency to think about our own worries and fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most powerful antidote to anxiety is faith. Yogananda said, “The cure for soul nervousness lies in transferring your attention from this little cage of the body to the perception of the Infinite. As a child of the Infinite, you must learn to reflect the image of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety is a physical, mental, and spiritual disease. Overcome it by giving your hopes and fears to God. Pray in this manner: “Divine Mother, I accept everything that happens as coming from Thee. Please bless me and those I love. Let Thy will be my will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In peace,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Can I Best Help Them?</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</guid>
      <description>Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”
We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to meditate before talking with them&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the fruits of meditation is the ability to detach yourself from the events around you and maintain a state of inner equilibrium under all circumstances. This is by no means easy, but needs to be cultivated continuously with energy and determination. During your meditation before meeting them, visualize them surrounded by God’s light and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept people as they are, while at the same time relating to their own higher nature.&lt;/strong&gt; If people feel accepted, it allows them the space to self-correct the behaviors that are causing them unhappiness. While meeting with them, pray and see them resting in their true self—divine love and wisdom. Unconditional acceptance is what God offers all of His children. Try to be a channel of this for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/how-can-i-best-help-them.png&#34;  alt=&#34;how can i best help them&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give direct advice unless they ask; rather, listen attentively so that they feel open to share with you.&lt;/strong&gt; Often an open ear is all people are really seeking. You can inwardly ask God to guide them from within themselves. If they do ask for advice, present it in a positive, nonjudgmental way. A beautiful passage from Master in this regard is: “I am the servant ready to serve all needy minds with my simple advice, with my gifts of healing truth, and with my humble wisdom gathered in the shrine of silence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you feel yourself getting engaged in negativity, quickly and consciously detach yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Be attentive to your own reactions, and inwardly strive to remain centered. Without seeming to withdraw, hold your mind at the spiritual eye. You can also quietly practice regular breathing: inhaling, holding the breath, and exhaling to the same count. Yoganandaji wrote: “When fear or anger or any kind of suffering comes to me, I will view it as a spectator. I will separate myself from my experiences. At all costs I will endeavor to retain my peace and happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always send love. Don’t withhold this no matter how difficult the situation.&lt;/strong&gt; Once a friend of ours was working as a doctor in an emergency room. Late one night, the police brought in a drunken, homeless man who had fallen and broken his arm. He was screaming, both with pain and fear, and it took two policemen to hold him down. To their amazement, our friend told the policemen to leave the treatment room—that she could handle him alone. Surrounding him in love, our friend was able to get the man to calm down so that she could set his arm. Afterwards the poor man looked at her beseechingly with eyes filled with years of loneliness and want, and asked, “Will you be my doctor?” He felt her love surrounding him—a feeling he hadn’t known for a long time. Healing can take place on many levels. By expressing love and forgiveness, not only can we help others, but we can remain uplifted as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, offer them to God for His help. Remember that God is always in charge of guiding every soul to inner freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; We are all on a journey to find the truth of who and what we really are. Offer a helping hand to others, when you can, but remember that ultimately, true happiness and freedom come when we allow God to guide our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these words of Master’s: “I will be a fisher of souls. I will catch the ignorance of others in a net of my wisdom and offer it for transmutation to the God of all gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With loving friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taming the Mind</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/taming-the-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/taming-the-mind/</guid>
      <description>A restless mind is a common and ancient problem for meditators. If you also have this problem, know, my friend, that you are not alone.
In the Bhagavad Gita, Arjuna says to Krishna, “Owing to my restlessness I’ve achieved no lasting results in the attempts You’ve taught me to steady the mind. Verily the mind is restless, tumultuous, madly stubborn! O, Krishna, I consider it to be as difficult to master as the wind!</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A restless mind is a common and ancient problem for meditators. If you also have this problem, know, my friend, that you are not alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bhagavad Gita, Arjuna says to Krishna, “Owing to my restlessness I’ve achieved no lasting results in the attempts You’ve taught me to steady the mind. Verily the mind is restless, tumultuous, madly stubborn! O, Krishna, I consider it to be as difficult to master as the wind!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should, of course, strive to calm our thoughts during meditation, but lest we think that a completely still mind is the only doorway to higher states of consciousness, we have this comforting example from Autobiography of a Yogi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A few mornings later I [Yogananda] made my way to Master’s empty sitting room. I planned to meditate, but my laudable purpose was unshared by disobedient thoughts. They scattered like birds before the hunter.” Just a few moments later his guru granted him his first great experience of cosmic consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficult though controlling the mind might seem, there are several things we can do to help reduce restless thoughts. The first and most important requirement, however, is that we want to quiet our minds. Without this “laudable purpose” you will achieve little. As you begin your meditation, you need to make a conscious decision to be still. The first few minutes are particularly important, so resolutely push aside any restless thoughts or desires. Then use meditation techniques, especially those of pranayama, to withdraw the life force into the spine and channel it toward the spiritual eye. As the prana withdraws, the mind will naturally become calmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an apt analogy: When a mahout takes his elephant through a village market it can cause havoc, stealing some bananas from one stall, some oranges from the next. But the wise driver has a trick up his sleeve. He trains the elephant to take a short piece of bamboo in his trunk and proudly hold it high. This, of course, keeps his trunk out of mischief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major senses of touch, sight, and hearing are our uncontrolled elephants, and meditation techniques are meant, in part, to give them a piece of bamboo on which to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central techniques of Yogananda’s path are ones of pranayama, especially Hong-Sau, where we try to feel each inhalation and exhalation and accompany them with the mantra Hong-Sau. Even as a child, Yogananda would practice this for hours at a time until he went breathless. Similar techniques of observing the breath form the foundation of nearly every path of meditation, including mindfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda-email.netlify.app/img/taming-the-mind.png&#34;  alt=&#34;taming the mind&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The breath becomes our piece of bamboo. By focusing on it the mind and senses turn inward and the mind begins to calm. Likewise, looking into the light of the spiritual eye turns the sense of sight inward, and the same is true for hearing when listening to the sound of AUM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is one of the most effective way to calm the mind in meditation: Whenever you become aware that your mind is restless, return it gently but firmly to its inner home by observing the breath, looking into the spiritual eye, or listening to AUM. If you make this a habit, you will take a giant leap in taming your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This practice also works in the marketplace of daily life. When your thoughts become upset or your emotions agitated, take a few deep breaths, focus briefly at the spiritual eye, or listen to the inner sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Yogananda wrote, “Remain ever calm within. Be even-minded. When working be calmly active. Someday you will know yourself to be subject no longer to the tides of Destiny. Your strength will come from within; you will not depend on outer incentives of any kind for motivation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joy and peace,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts Archive</title>
      <link>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda-email.netlify.app/posts/archive/</guid>
      <description>This page contains an archive of all posts.</description>
      <content></content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
