<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Index on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Index on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stranger in a Strange Land</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/stranger-in-a-strange-land/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/stranger-in-a-strange-land/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago Jyotish and I led the Astral Ascension Ceremony for a dear friend, Judy Fox, who passed away recently. Judy was part of a small team, as were we, that Swami Kriyananda sent to Italy in the early 1980s to help start Ananda’s work there.
We landed in Northern Italy near Lake Como at a lovely summer villa that belonged to a friend and fellow disciple. Sound idyllic?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago Jyotish and I led the Astral Ascension Ceremony for a dear friend, Judy Fox, who passed away recently. Judy was part of a small team, as were we, that Swami Kriyananda sent to Italy in the early 1980s to help start Ananda’s work there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We landed in Northern Italy near Lake Como at a lovely summer villa that belonged to a friend and fellow disciple. Sound idyllic? Perhaps, but as the months passed and temperatures dropped, living in a summer house with little heat during the coldest winter in Europe in one hundred years was a huge challenge for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, living in a different culture from what we were accustomed to, knowing very few people on whom to call, and having none of our usual comforts all reinforced the feeling that we were “stranieri,” foreigners. As time passed, we felt more and more like “strangers in a strange land” (Exodus 2:22).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji knew all of us well, however, and felt that we had the strength and commitment not only to survive the challenges, but to grow spiritually in the process. And so it proved. We soon realized we had one of two choices: 1) to let our energy drop, and sink into loneliness and depression; or 2) to raise our energy level and deepen our faith in God’s guiding presence with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together our small team consciously chose the second option: to keep our spirits uplifted and to look for ways to share Master’s great teachings with seekers in Europe. From these humble beginnings, Ananda now has a thriving international community outside of Assisi, Italy, as well as centers spreading throughout Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our friend Judy, who was there that first winter, had an especially joyful and ebullient nature, and helped us all to stay positive. At her Astral Ascension Ceremony, her partner of twenty-seven years, Ric, shared with us a beautiful story about her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judy met him shortly after returning to California from Italy, and told him about Master’s path and Ananda. Then (after knowing Ric for only ten days) she told him that he should visit Assisi, because: “The farther you are from home, the closer you are to God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With those simple words, Judy captured our whole experience of that difficult first winter. With nothing familiar from which to draw, we had to tune in to another form of comfort and sense of “home”: God’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This world—which alternates between seeming welcoming and familiar to seeming unloving and foreign—can never really be our home. Why? Because on the deepest level, it’s only an impermanent illusion. We are strangers in a strange land. Our true soul home can only be found by reuniting with God, from Whom we sprang lifetimes ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So remember, when you’re going through a difficult time outside of your comfort zone and the world seems inimical and unwelcoming, think of Judy’s mantra: &lt;strong&gt;“The farther you are from home, the closer you are to God.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at those other times when life is going all your way? Recall Judy’s mantra to mind just as forcefully then. Will you rest comfortably in all that’s familiar? Will you, in Yogananda’s immortal words, “bask in the familial warmth”? Or will you embrace self-expansion and as yet uncharted waters? This choice is always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/stranger-in-a-strange-land.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;stranger in a strange land&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these stanzas from Swamiji’s beautiful song, “God’s Call Within,” which captures the essence of our soul’s search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.


Friend, how long will you wander?
Friend, as long as you seek your home
In a land where all are strangers,
Love locks her door.


Turn, turn, turn within:
In silence of soul, in cave of love
Find My abode.
 

Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your fellow wanderer,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Anxiety</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/overcoming-anxiety/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/overcoming-anxiety/</guid>
      <description>Anxiety is one of the diseases of our age, affecting almost two-thirds of the population, with nearly a third finding it debilitating.
Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The main causes of nervousness are 1) long-continued overactivity, 2) excessive stimulation of the senses from physical overindulgence, and 3) mental overstimulation from chronic fear, anger, sorrow, hatred, jealousy, discontent, or similar harmful emotions.
“Any violent or prolonged excitement disturbs the flow of life force through the nervous system.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Anxiety is one of the diseases of our age, affecting almost two-thirds of the population, with nearly a third finding it debilitating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The main causes of nervousness are 1) long-continued overactivity, 2) excessive stimulation of the senses from physical overindulgence, and 3) mental overstimulation from chronic fear, anger, sorrow, hatred, jealousy, discontent, or similar harmful emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any violent or prolonged excitement disturbs the flow of life force through the nervous system. If you put a two-thousand-volt current through a fifty-watt lamp, it will burn out the lamp. In the same way, excessive stimulation burns the nerves, cutting off the supply of energy and upsetting the functioning of the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most damaging emotions are anger and fear. Anger burns the nerves in the brain and causes poisons to be secreted throughout the body. Fear burns the nerves that supply the heart and can cause heart trouble. Feelings of timidity destroy the nerve endings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety, therefore, can be seen as a disease of the nerves, and the following physical methods can help cool our system and alleviate symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, water is an excellent nerve tonic, so bathing, swimming, or even taking a cold shower can help. Yogananda taught that lime juice in water sweetened to neither sweet nor sour can soothe the nerves. Satwic foods, particularly fruit, will cool the nerves, while tamasic foods, excessive spices, or overeating will be harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, exercise and walking, especially in nature, can help reset the entire system. Hippocrates is reported to have said, “If you are in a bad mood go for a walk. If you are still in a bad mood go for another walk.” Yogananda’s Energization Exercises, yoga postures, and the affirmations of the Ananda Yoga system are specifically designed to strengthen and realign the flow of prana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, sleep is very healing. If you have trouble falling asleep, try this: First relax your entire face including the tongue; next, drop your shoulders and let your hands drop to your sides. Then exhale, relaxing your chest, and focus on the breath; let your lower body and limbs relax, succumbing to the pull of gravity. Finally, clear your mind of all thoughts for ten seconds. The US military teaches this system (it sounds like it is straight out of a yoga class) and reports that a vast majority of people can learn to fall asleep within two minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/overcoming-anxiety.png&#34;  alt=&#34;overcoming anxiety&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Since the most damaging emotions are anger and fear, it’s essential to control these sentiments actively. Accept that anxiety is an emotional condition and not amenable to logic. News and media, especially opinions, are designed to evoke fear and anger, so avoid that mental poison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t control the uncontrollable, especially world situations that have little direct influence on our daily lives. Focus on changing yourself, since this is all you can actually control, and even that is a Herculean task. “Do your best and forget tomorrow” is Yogananda’s advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;meditation-and-faith&#34;&gt;Meditation and Faith&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation is a powerful tool for calming the mind and reducing stress. It allows us to step back from the constant chatter of our thoughts and emotions, and to connect with a deeper sense of peace and stillness within ourselves. Regular meditation and breathing techniques will rewire the brain, making us less vulnerable to stress and anxiety. Serving others will break the tendency to think about our own worries and fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the most powerful antidote to anxiety is faith. Yogananda said, “The cure for soul nervousness lies in transferring your attention from this little cage of the body to the perception of the Infinite. As a child of the Infinite, you must learn to reflect the image of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety is a physical, mental, and spiritual disease. Overcome it by giving your hopes and fears to God. Pray in this manner: “Divine Mother, I accept everything that happens as coming from Thee. Please bless me and those I love. Let Thy will be my will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In peace,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Can I Best Help Them?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/how-can-i-best-help-them/</guid>
      <description>Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”
We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend wrote asking: “How can I help family members who are going through a difficult time, or have a sour relationship with one another, without being affected by the situation personally? How does one know when to intervene and support, and when to be an observer and send support from a distance?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have all faced this dilemma in one form or another. With my friend’s permission, I’ll share with you some thoughts that I offered her about the art of helping others while remaining unaffected by their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to meditate before talking with them&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the fruits of meditation is the ability to detach yourself from the events around you and maintain a state of inner equilibrium under all circumstances. This is by no means easy, but needs to be cultivated continuously with energy and determination. During your meditation before meeting them, visualize them surrounded by God’s light and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept people as they are, while at the same time relating to their own higher nature.&lt;/strong&gt; If people feel accepted, it allows them the space to self-correct the behaviors that are causing them unhappiness. While meeting with them, pray and see them resting in their true self—divine love and wisdom. Unconditional acceptance is what God offers all of His children. Try to be a channel of this for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/how-can-i-best-help-them.png&#34;  alt=&#34;how can i best help them&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give direct advice unless they ask; rather, listen attentively so that they feel open to share with you.&lt;/strong&gt; Often an open ear is all people are really seeking. You can inwardly ask God to guide them from within themselves. If they do ask for advice, present it in a positive, nonjudgmental way. A beautiful passage from Master in this regard is: “I am the servant ready to serve all needy minds with my simple advice, with my gifts of healing truth, and with my humble wisdom gathered in the shrine of silence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you feel yourself getting engaged in negativity, quickly and consciously detach yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Be attentive to your own reactions, and inwardly strive to remain centered. Without seeming to withdraw, hold your mind at the spiritual eye. You can also quietly practice regular breathing: inhaling, holding the breath, and exhaling to the same count. Yoganandaji wrote: “When fear or anger or any kind of suffering comes to me, I will view it as a spectator. I will separate myself from my experiences. At all costs I will endeavor to retain my peace and happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always send love. Don’t withhold this no matter how difficult the situation.&lt;/strong&gt; Once a friend of ours was working as a doctor in an emergency room. Late one night, the police brought in a drunken, homeless man who had fallen and broken his arm. He was screaming, both with pain and fear, and it took two policemen to hold him down. To their amazement, our friend told the policemen to leave the treatment room—that she could handle him alone. Surrounding him in love, our friend was able to get the man to calm down so that she could set his arm. Afterwards the poor man looked at her beseechingly with eyes filled with years of loneliness and want, and asked, “Will you be my doctor?” He felt her love surrounding him—a feeling he hadn’t known for a long time. Healing can take place on many levels. By expressing love and forgiveness, not only can we help others, but we can remain uplifted as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, offer them to God for His help. Remember that God is always in charge of guiding every soul to inner freedom.&lt;/strong&gt; We are all on a journey to find the truth of who and what we really are. Offer a helping hand to others, when you can, but remember that ultimately, true happiness and freedom come when we allow God to guide our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these words of Master’s: “I will be a fisher of souls. I will catch the ignorance of others in a net of my wisdom and offer it for transmutation to the God of all gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With loving friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taming the Mind</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/taming-the-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/taming-the-mind/</guid>
      <description>A restless mind is a common and ancient problem for meditators. If you also have this problem, know, my friend, that you are not alone.
In the Bhagavad Gita, Arjuna says to Krishna, “Owing to my restlessness I’ve achieved no lasting results in the attempts You’ve taught me to steady the mind. Verily the mind is restless, tumultuous, madly stubborn! O, Krishna, I consider it to be as difficult to master as the wind!</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A restless mind is a common and ancient problem for meditators. If you also have this problem, know, my friend, that you are not alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bhagavad Gita, Arjuna says to Krishna, “Owing to my restlessness I’ve achieved no lasting results in the attempts You’ve taught me to steady the mind. Verily the mind is restless, tumultuous, madly stubborn! O, Krishna, I consider it to be as difficult to master as the wind!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should, of course, strive to calm our thoughts during meditation, but lest we think that a completely still mind is the only doorway to higher states of consciousness, we have this comforting example from Autobiography of a Yogi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A few mornings later I [Yogananda] made my way to Master’s empty sitting room. I planned to meditate, but my laudable purpose was unshared by disobedient thoughts. They scattered like birds before the hunter.” Just a few moments later his guru granted him his first great experience of cosmic consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficult though controlling the mind might seem, there are several things we can do to help reduce restless thoughts. The first and most important requirement, however, is that we want to quiet our minds. Without this “laudable purpose” you will achieve little. As you begin your meditation, you need to make a conscious decision to be still. The first few minutes are particularly important, so resolutely push aside any restless thoughts or desires. Then use meditation techniques, especially those of pranayama, to withdraw the life force into the spine and channel it toward the spiritual eye. As the prana withdraws, the mind will naturally become calmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an apt analogy: When a mahout takes his elephant through a village market it can cause havoc, stealing some bananas from one stall, some oranges from the next. But the wise driver has a trick up his sleeve. He trains the elephant to take a short piece of bamboo in his trunk and proudly hold it high. This, of course, keeps his trunk out of mischief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major senses of touch, sight, and hearing are our uncontrolled elephants, and meditation techniques are meant, in part, to give them a piece of bamboo on which to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central techniques of Yogananda’s path are ones of pranayama, especially Hong-Sau, where we try to feel each inhalation and exhalation and accompany them with the mantra Hong-Sau. Even as a child, Yogananda would practice this for hours at a time until he went breathless. Similar techniques of observing the breath form the foundation of nearly every path of meditation, including mindfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/taming-the-mind.png&#34;  alt=&#34;taming the mind&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The breath becomes our piece of bamboo. By focusing on it the mind and senses turn inward and the mind begins to calm. Likewise, looking into the light of the spiritual eye turns the sense of sight inward, and the same is true for hearing when listening to the sound of AUM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is one of the most effective way to calm the mind in meditation: Whenever you become aware that your mind is restless, return it gently but firmly to its inner home by observing the breath, looking into the spiritual eye, or listening to AUM. If you make this a habit, you will take a giant leap in taming your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This practice also works in the marketplace of daily life. When your thoughts become upset or your emotions agitated, take a few deep breaths, focus briefly at the spiritual eye, or listen to the inner sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Yogananda wrote, “Remain ever calm within. Be even-minded. When working be calmly active. Someday you will know yourself to be subject no longer to the tides of Destiny. Your strength will come from within; you will not depend on outer incentives of any kind for motivation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joy and peace,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding God in the Big City</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-god-in-the-big-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-god-in-the-big-city/</guid>
      <description>Twenty million people! That’s the population of the Greater Los Angeles area, we were told recently when we visited friends and Ananda centers there.
For one of our satsangs, in Torrance, the center leader asked us to talk about how to find spirituality in big-city life. I thought you, too, might be interested in the thoughts we shared that evening on the challenges faced by city-dwellers and some of the spiritual solutions to them.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Twenty million people! That’s the population of the Greater Los Angeles area, we were told recently when we visited friends and Ananda centers there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one of our satsangs, in Torrance, the center leader asked us to talk about how to find spirituality in big-city life. I thought you, too, might be interested in the thoughts we shared that evening on the challenges faced by city-dwellers and some of the spiritual solutions to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;distraction-vs-focused-attention&#34;&gt;Distraction vs. Focused Attention&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving on big-city freeways is an experience in itself. It’s almost overwhelming to deal with the long commutes, the speed of the traffic, and the constantly flashing billboards screaming (as a friend of ours once humorously put it), “Eat me. Buy me. Take me home!” The mind gets scattered in a myriad of different directions, and even after arriving at your destination, it takes an effort of will to get focused again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no small obstacle to achieving peace of mind, but the opportunity is also there: to keep the mind more concentrated on whatever we’re doing. Build up the habit of attentive awareness in everything you do—talking with a friend, working on a project at your job, going for a walk. While driving, listen to something uplifting—beautiful music or an inspiring talk—and give it your attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more you make the conscious effort to concentrate, the more will you find yourself actively and rewardingly engaged in every area of your life. And the greater will your ability be to go deep in meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;self-interest-vs-self-giving&#34;&gt;Self-Interest vs. Self-Giving&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forces of competition and self-interest are strong in any large group. Even lab rats turn on one another when placed in overcrowded tanks. The seeming cold indifference in a big city may lead us to think, “If I don’t look out for ‘Number One,’ how will I get by?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity here is to counter the pull of self-interest by consciously finding ways to serve and to give to others. We have a friend in Los Angeles who would give her daughters a small weekly allowance, and then (at their request) drive them to an area where homeless people lived, so that they could give their money away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find ways to help others, even at your own inconvenience or loss. Keeping the heart open to those in need frees us from preoccupation with the demands of our limited self. Ultimately we realize that God alone is the provider, and that the more we give, the more we are given. Self-giving also leads us to experience a loving connection with all of life.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/finding-god-in-the-big-city.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;finding-god-in-the-big-city&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;self-indulgence-vs-self-control&#34;&gt;Self-Indulgence vs. Self-Control&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big-city life offers many dark pathways that lead to overstimulation of the senses, even to the point of self-destruction. Master set up his headquarters in Los Angeles, and lived there for nearly twenty-five years. He would sometimes walk up and down some of the seedy, bar-lined streets in order to bring light and upliftment to the poor souls there trapped in addictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity for us here is to examine our own life and find areas where we lack sufficient self-control. Take up a challenge with the thought, “I will practice inner discipline so that others may follow my lead and develop self-control in their life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’ve improved in one area, take up another challenge, until you begin to see that you—not old habits or karma—are in charge of your life. What freedom comes with this realization!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;downward-emotions-vs-uplifted-feelings&#34;&gt;Downward Emotions vs. Uplifted Feelings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer number of life stories and struggles in a big city can create a fog of hopelessness and despair. Especially now with economic and political uncertainty rife—and with the possibility looming on the horizon of even worse to come—it’s easy to be pulled down into negativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To counter this tendency, we should strive energetically to keep hope and joy foremost in our minds. One of my favorite quotes of Master’s is, “Life is a battle for joy every step of the way. May I fight to win the battle on the very spot where I now stand.” These words have stood me in good stead through many a difficult situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you choose joy under all circumstances, you begin to find that joy is your constant companion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, finding God in big-city life comes down to this: In each of life’s circumstances, choose the highest and best road to follow. And use all of your strength and commitment to stay the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember these words of Yoganandaji: “There are no obstacles, only opportunities.” Your very effort will uplift those around you, whether you live in a big city or a small ashram. Then you become, as Swami Kriyananda used to say, “part of the solution, not the problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from the Snow</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/lessons-from-the-snow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/lessons-from-the-snow/</guid>
      <description>We have been experiencing historic snowfalls in Northern California. Hard as it is to imagine, some areas near Lake Tahoe have gotten nearly fifty feet of snow so far, with more on the way! Much less has fallen at Ananda Village, but still we’ve gotten more than any time in recent memory. With hills, freezing temperatures, and snowy roads, many of us have been snowbound. Here is the view from our living room this morning.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We have been experiencing historic snowfalls in Northern California. Hard as it is to imagine, some areas near Lake Tahoe have gotten nearly fifty feet of snow so far, with more on the way! Much less has fallen at Ananda Village, but still we’ve gotten more than any time in recent memory. With hills, freezing temperatures, and snowy roads, many of us have been snowbound. Here is the view from our living room this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For restless people, conditions like these are probably a torment. For yogis, being forced to go within is actually quite nice. The snow brings with it some wonderful lessons. Here are a few that have struck me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;give-help-receive-help&#34;&gt;Give Help, Receive Help&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During times of hardship, people of goodwill rise to the occasion. At Ananda Village our maintenance crews have worked around the clock to help people cope with the icy roads; our market staff has been delivering food orders to residents; and many of us are feeding the birds and animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-minded people naturally want to serve others. But the snow is bringing another lesson: to be willing and grateful to receive help when offered. Many devotees are better at giving than receiving. This is a good quality in moderation, but becomes a spiritual flaw when taken too far. We need to learn the art of receiving also. Everything in life is a gift from the Divine. It delays our spiritual progress if we ignore or reject the help that is given to us. In meditation our first act should be to open our hearts, receive God’s presence, and silently say, “Thank you, God.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/lessons-from-the-snow.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;lessons-from-the-snow&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;use-the-time-well&#34;&gt;Use the Time Well&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having one’s schedule disrupted can be a good thing, if you are flexible and can shift your energies to alternative activities. It sounds like this should be easy, but restlessness is one of the great curses of our times. According to our great Masters, we live in a rajasic (restless) age on a rajasic planet in a rajasic galaxy. Is it any wonder that people are habituated, even addicted, to activity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental restlessness is perhaps the greatest block to meditation. When circumstances shut down our normal schedule, let’s use the time to turn our consciousness upward. For me personally the snow gave me some time to paint for which I was joyfully grateful. The inspiration came to do a pair of paintings of the same scene at different times of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dawn” and “Midnight,” the two paintings I drew during the snowstorm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;live-more-in-god&#34;&gt;Live More in God&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest gift of inwardness, whether forced or voluntary, is the opportunity to turn a quieted mind toward living in God’s presence. No matter the conditions or the place, we can always choose to turn our minds and hearts Godward. Yoganandaji stated it so poetically in this beautiful poem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wherever-we-go&#34;&gt;Wherever We Go&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Whether in Himalayan caves or crowded subway;

Whether in the concrete jungle of modern life,

Or in a simple village in Hindustan:

Wherever we go, teach us to seek Thee out

In all Thy secret nooks—east, west, north, south—everywhere!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I pray that for all of us, we can see behind every circumstance, good or bad, the hidden opportunity to live more in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Memory</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-power-of-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-power-of-memory/</guid>
      <description>“Many have been My births, O Arjuna, and many also yours. I remember all of Mine, though you remember yours not.” These words from Sri Krishna to his disciple in the Bhagavad Gita show a divine memory of the soul’s eternal nature.
Memory, in its highest expression, is much more than remembering what is on a grocery list. It is the soul’s ability to transcend the limitations of time.
Paramhansa Yogananda spoke of the “easy resurrection of memory” through which he brought to mind past experiences with his guru, Sri Yukteswar.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“Many have been My births, O Arjuna, and many also yours. I remember all of Mine, though you remember yours not.” These words from Sri Krishna to his disciple in the Bhagavad Gita show a divine memory of the soul’s eternal nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memory, in its highest expression, is much more than remembering what is on a grocery list. It is the soul’s ability to transcend the limitations of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda spoke of the “easy resurrection of memory” through which he brought to mind past experiences with his guru, Sri Yukteswar. With a trained and heightened sense of memory, we can meld past, present, and future into the eternal now. Patanjali, the ancient authority on yoga, described spiritual awakening as smriti, which means “memory.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The yogic teachings describe three different levels of our awareness. The &lt;strong&gt;subconscious mind&lt;/strong&gt; is the repository of all of our past experiences, impressions, and thoughts. It’s the archives for our memories, not only of this life, but of all of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;conscious mind&lt;/strong&gt; is the operating system that responds to the details and challenges of daily life. It’s how we solve problems, make decisions, and plan for the future. The conscious mind draws on memories held in the subconscious to inform its decisions, so they work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;superconscious mind&lt;/strong&gt; is our higher, intuitive faculty that allows us to expand our awareness beyond the limitations of the ego. Through it, we can experience our true Self, and ultimately our oneness with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this description, it’s easy to draw the conclusion that it’s a progression—that all we need to do is focus on the superconscious mind and forget about the “lower” levels of awareness. But it isn’t that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda said something in this regard that has always intrigued me. Superconsciousness, he wrote, is found at the thin line between the conscious and subconscious minds, rather like the horizon line between sea and sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we come to the power and importance of memory. The subconscious is much more than a dreamy, unaware state of hidden compulsions. Rather it’s an intrinsic part of our journey to enlightenment, both because it contains useful lessons from the past, and because it’s not limited to dwelling in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji spoke often about how to develop the power of memory, and how to use it properly. “Memory,” he said, “is that faculty of the conscious mind which, through the help of the subconscious mind, can recall any past conscious experience. Always awake, the subconscious mind is buried beneath the conscious mind, working during sleep and constantly memorizing experiences during the state of wakefulness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In order to perform important duties and recall valuable experiences for daily use, one must be able to work with the material recalled to the conscious mind by the power of memory. The subconscious mind can be trained to recall at will all conscious experiences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some ways Master gives to develop our memory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morning and evening, rap the scalp with the knuckles, then massage it with the fingers as taught in the Energization Exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perform every action with keen attention. Attention is the needle that cuts grooves in the memory cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night, remember in detail everything that happened during the past week. Try also to remember in detail the principal events of the month with regard to your life, your city, your country, and the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going to bed and upon awakening, command your subconscious mind to be attentive to all your activities and to store all valuable experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-power-of-memory.png&#34;  alt=&#34;the power of memory&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the proper use of memory. Yoganandaji said, “Memory was given to us to keep alive only life’s good experiences and lessons. To remember bad experiences and dwell upon them is an abuse of God’s gift to us of memory.” This doesn’t mean that we suppress bad experiences or ignore past mistakes. Rather, we should move on from painful experiences, and concentrate on filling our memory banks with positive, divine recollections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Sri Yukteswar said to a new student who doubted his own worthiness to seek God: “Forget the past. The vanished lives of all men are dark with many shames. . . . Everything in future will improve if you are making a spiritual effort now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what is the best use of this divine gift of memory? Remembering God. As I write this today, it’s the seventy-first anniversary of Yoganandaji’s mahasamadhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honor our great Guru, take some time at this very moment to remember his impact on your life. When was the first time you saw his photo? When did you first read his Autobiography of a Yogi? What was your first impression of it? If you’re a disciple, when did you realize that he was your God-given guru? Sit in stillness with these memories, and try to feel the timeless nature of your bond with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend sent us a description of an experience a direct disciple of Master had with him some decades after his mahasamadhi. Yogananda appeared to him holding a white and gold book in letters of light, entitled The Book of My Life. Master held it, and told him to turn the pages and read from the book. As he turned the pages backward and forward, he saw accounts of his previous and future incarnations, in which his guru was always guiding him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though, like Arjuna, we may not consciously remember our past lives, the eternal love between guru and disciple is always there, just beneath the surface. The more we’re able to access the stored memories of our Guru’s presence, and hold the thought of him in our conscious mind, the more quickly we will be able to realize our oneness with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the joy of remembering God and Guru,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Ways to Outwit Karma</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/four-ways-to-outwit-karma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/four-ways-to-outwit-karma/</guid>
      <description>Karma is one of the fundamental laws of the universe. Basically, it states that every thought, feeling, and action has a consequence. In the Bible, it says, “As you sow, so shall you reap.”
Once set in motion, there is normally no way to avoid the karma of past actions. But we can do much to change how severe the consequences will be. Sri Yukteswar said that the past lives of all men are dark with many shames.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Karma is one of the fundamental laws of the universe. Basically, it states that every thought, feeling, and action has a consequence. In the Bible, it says, “As you sow, so shall you reap.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once set in motion, there is normally no way to avoid the karma of past actions. But we can do much to change how severe the consequences will be. Sri Yukteswar said that the past lives of all men are dark with many shames. But that everything in the future will improve if we are making the right spiritual efforts now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are four ways to outwit our karmic consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move Away from Bad Behavior:&lt;/strong&gt; Every action or thought is like a bolt of energy. The energy once sent out will inevitably return. If we shout at someone in anger, we will often, if not always immediately, get an angry retort in return. Karmic paybacks are life’s way of teaching us the consequences of our actions and nudging us toward alignment with God’s laws. In this case, the returning karma is meant to teach us not to act out in anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bolt of angry retribution headed our way is like a car approaching us on a one-lane road. If we are still acting in the same deluded way, there will be a head-on crash. But now imagine that you have changed, and not only are no longer acting with anger, but instead are now patient and helpful when confronted. You are now moving in the same direction as your “car-mic” retribution, and the result may be just a little tap on the rear to remind you to keep making the right spiritual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we learn to head the right way? First, become aware of how you are behaving. Awareness always precedes action. Next, take responsibility for your behavior. Finally, put out energy in the opposite direction, the direction your karma wants to push you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serve Others:&lt;/strong&gt; Service is one of the best ways to overcome karma, which is always initiated by self-interest. Simply put, when we think about ourselves, we end up creating bad karma. When we forget ourselves and think about helping others, we become freer and happier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are self-involved, even a whisper of criticism can be devastating. When our hearts are strong and expanded through thinking of others, even an angry tirade can be shrugged off or provide an opportunity to help the irate person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditate and Do Pranayama:&lt;/strong&gt; Meditation is the fastest way to become free of ego, the root cause of all karma. All the whirlpools of karma reside in the astral spine. Meditation can neutralize those vortices. Paramhansa Yogananda said that each Kriya is the equivalent of a whole year of right living. Day by day, meditation by meditation, our astral spine is cleared of all destructive karmic tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may have innumerable seeds of karmic tendencies waiting for the right circumstances to sprout. But pranayama, especially Kriya Yoga, fills the spine with positive magnetism and burns up the seeds before they can be planted.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/four-ways-to-outwit-karma.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;fours ways to outwit karma&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attunement with a Guru:&lt;/strong&gt; A guru will take away much of our karma if we stay attuned. A good friend had a fascinating dream. He was walking along a beach and came upon a huge pile of sticky tar, which he knew was his past bad karma. His task was to eliminate it, but all he had for the job was a little toy plastic pail and shovel. After a great deal of effort he finally succeeded in filling his bucket one time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he began to despair of ever finishing the job, he heard a loud noise coming from the back of the pile. Curious, he went around and found Yogananda driving a tractor with a large scoop on the front. Master had a huge grin on his face as he dug into the mound of tar again and again and dumped the loads into the ocean to be dissolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rich man can easily pay the debts of a wayward child. Such is the power of attunement with a God-realized guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with a fascinating answer that Swami Kriyananda gave when asked how we can tell the difference between good and bad karma. He said good karma takes us closer to God, while bad karma takes us away. Sometimes unpleasant karma, like bitter medicine, is the best thing for us. We don’t have to enjoy it, but we would be wise to swallow it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take That Step!</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/take-that-step/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/take-that-step/</guid>
      <description>Driving on a stormy night to an uncertain destination is a daunting experience for all of us. It’s also a perfect analogy for the challenges on our spiritual journey.
First, we get in our car and are glad for the moment to be out of the storm. (This is our first step on the path to God, in which we have a longing to escape the turmoil of life and find peace of mind.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Driving on a stormy night to an uncertain destination is a daunting experience for all of us. It’s also a perfect analogy for the challenges on our spiritual journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we get in our car and are glad for the moment to be out of the storm. (&lt;em&gt;This is our first step on the path to God, in which we have a longing to escape the turmoil of life and find peace of mind.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we’re uncertain about driving in the storm. We even begin to question if getting to the destination is worth it, so we decide to cancel the trip. (&lt;em&gt;Some new seekers lose heart before they begin, and decide that the unknown destination of finding God and the demands of the trip are too much. They quit before they’ve even begun.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, if we’re plucky enough, we summon up the courage to start the car, turn on the headlights, and check our GPS unit to get an idea of where we’re going. (&lt;em&gt;We generate the initial energy to start the journey, then put out the positive energy that enables us to find a true guide—the guru—who can show us where we’re headed and how to get there.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the journey begins. Since the headlights enable us to see only a little distance ahead, we proceed slowly and cautiously. We hope that the road will become clearer as we continue driving. (&lt;em&gt;Each step on the spiritual path is revealed as we approach it. The techniques and teachings come into focus as we proceed.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, the storm seems to be letting up, and we begin to relax and enjoy the journey. As we draw closer to our destination, streetlights appear to guide us, the road gets wider, and the signs for our journey’s end are more frequent. (&lt;em&gt;As we continue towards our spiritual goal, the dark karma that obscured our way seems to lift. Our inner path to God becomes more brightly illumined, and reaching Him begins to seem possible.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as we approach our destination, we begin to speed up, because we see that we’re nearing the journey’s end. With a sigh of relief, we realize that the goal that for so long seemed obscure is now familiar and welcoming. (&lt;em&gt;Though the spiritual journey is seemingly filled with perils and uncertainty, as we continue the momentum builds. We realize that there was always an Unseen Passenger in the back seat silently guiding our way to our true home in God.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/take-that-step.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;take that step&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To complete the journey, we must find the faith to trust that we are never alone on the spiritual path, and that God’s grace is always with us. But we must also have the courage to take the next step, and then the next, until we arrive at our goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Yoganandaji was correcting a disciple for some behavior that needed changing. The man tried to justify himself by answering, “That’s easy for you to say—you’re a master.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji replied with great force: “And what do you think made me a master?” In other words, it’s by facing our challenges and overcoming them that we attain soul freedom. The journey may seem dark and daunting, but if we take each step in front of us, with God’s grace, we will get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master, who has the soul of a spiritual warrior, wrote a wonderful poem, “My Soul Is Marching On.” It’s filled with the determination and power to reach the journey’s end. As you read these stanzas excerpted from the poem, try to visualize him in armor of gleaming light holding a flaming sword to guide us forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The flowers bloomed, then hid in gloom,
The bounty of the trees did cease;
Colossal men have come and gone,
But still my soul is marching on!

Darkness, death, and failures vied;
To block my path they fiercely tried.
My fight with jealous Nature’s strong,
But still my soul is marching on!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take the next step with determination, friend. Marching bravely we will reach—each one of us—the journey’s end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living in the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/living-in-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/living-in-the-light/</guid>
      <description>It is good to celebrate noteworthy events, and this is one of those milestones. You are reading blog number five hundred! Writing five hundred in a row hasn’t always been easy or convenient, but sharing a Touch of Light has been one of the greatest blessings of our lives.
This week also marks another long-standing tradition. We are just finishing Inner Renewal Retreat, a decades-long annual event designed to reawaken and reenergize our spiritual commitment.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;It is good to celebrate noteworthy events, and this is one of those milestones. You are reading blog number five hundred! Writing five hundred in a row hasn’t always been easy or convenient, but sharing a Touch of Light has been one of the greatest blessings of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week also marks another long-standing tradition. We are just finishing Inner Renewal Retreat, a decades-long annual event designed to reawaken and reenergize our spiritual commitment. This year’s theme, “Living in God’s Light,” covered four pillars of the spiritual path: sadhana, service, self-offering, and attunement. The recorded classes will be available soon, but for the thousands of you around the world who couldn’t attend, let me recap a few of the most important points from the three sessions Devi and I did during the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1, Sadhana:&lt;/strong&gt; We talked about increasing the light within through sadhana, especially meditation. The conscious mind, limited by the senses, is ill equipped to recognize our hidden spiritual nature. The purpose of sadhana is to help us awaken in superconsciousness. But to accomplish this we must withdraw the life-force from the body and the senses so that we can see our true reality behind the fringes of a restless mind. “Be still and know that I am God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We gave a fun demonstration of magnetism, illustrating that, like our spiritual reality, many forces in nature are hidden from us.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/living-in-the-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;living in the light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2, Seva:&lt;/strong&gt; Paramhansa Yogananda defined his path as a combination of meditation and service. In this class we discussed thirteen different principles of service from an upcoming book of mine. Here are a few that will give you a sense of the subject, and something on which to meditate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seva is a means to dissolve the ego.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are channels for the Divine to serve through us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The attitude with which we serve is more important than what we do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serving with willingness, joy, and enthusiasm increases energy and magnetism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer the fruits of service back to the Divine from whom they come.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 3, Self-Offering:&lt;/strong&gt; People typically pick up this subject from the wrong end. They think about self-offering in terms of things they must give up. Seen this way, self-offering seems to be self-denial. There is a charming true story about an exchange Yogananda had with a famous Hollywood actor, Herb Jeffries, who was a follower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actor said, “Religion keeps telling me, ‘You shan’t do this, you shan’t do that.’ I’m not interested in what I shan’t do. I want to know what I can do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda replied, “Do you smoke?” “Yes,” the actor said. To his surprise, Yogananda said, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, Master asked, “Do you drink alcohol?” “Yes, I enjoy a good drink,” was the reply. Again, Master said, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Yogananda asked, “Do you enjoy the company of women?” “YES! Indeed I do.” And yet again, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herb, relieved but confused, looked at Yogananda curiously. Master concluded, “You may do all of these things, but I have to warn you that if you take up my teachings, the desire to do them will fall away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is the essence of self-offering: All we can ever offer are limiting desires and attachments. We can no more give God our actual possessions than we can give our bank account to the sun. God will never take anything from us until we willingly offer it to Him. But He lovingly awaits the hour when we realize that all those desires, possessions, and attitudes that we cling to so fiercely are the very things that obstruct our true happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The goal of life and of all spiritual practice is to dissolve the ego.&lt;/strong&gt; All God wants from us is our love, which we offer to Him through sadhana, service, self-offering, and attunement to the guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Paramhansa Yogananda puts it, “Those who are immersed in body-consciousness are like strangers in a foreign land. Our native country is Omnipresence.” And: “The purpose of human life is to find God. That is the only reason for our existence. Job, friends, material interests—these things in themselves mean nothing. They can never provide you with true happiness, for the simple reason that none of them, in itself, is complete. Only God encompasses everything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each week we end our Sunday service with these words from Swami Kriyananda’s Festival of Light:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Lord, we offer up the little light that is in us
Into Thy blazing light of Infinity.
Grant us the grace to know Thee.
And make us ever-increasingly
Pure channels of Thy love to all.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;May we all merge into that infinite light and bliss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Curious Tail</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-curious-tail/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-curious-tail/</guid>
      <description>As I walked along a forest path at Ananda’s Meditation Retreat one morning, I observed an unusual drama unfold before me. Crouched a few yards ahead was Lottie, a fluffy little gray cat who kept the Retreat’s kitchen free from mice. Her gaze was concentrated on something in front of her, and by her intense crouching pose, I could tell she was about to pounce on it.
But moments before she sprang, I saw something shoot off nearly ten yards ahead and lie wriggling in the path.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;As I walked along a forest path at Ananda’s Meditation Retreat one morning, I observed an unusual drama unfold before me. Crouched a few yards ahead was Lottie, a fluffy little gray cat who kept the Retreat’s kitchen free from mice. Her gaze was concentrated on something in front of her, and by her intense crouching pose, I could tell she was about to pounce on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But moments before she sprang, I saw something shoot off nearly ten yards ahead and lie wriggling in the path. Quietly drawing closer to find out what was happening, I saw that Lottie now held in her jaws the small, limp body of a lizard: a brown skink. These lizards have a remarkable ability to project their tail when attacked. Sure enough, the detached tail was what I’d seen thrashing around farther down the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confused by the movement, Lottie dropped the skink, which began creeping into the underbrush, and ran after the tail. After holding the bony appendage in her mouth for a few moments, the cat realized that she’d been tricked, and ran back to catch the lizard, which was still in sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much to my amazement, this spectacle repeated itself: the detached tail, still thrashing around, caused Lottie to drop the lizard once again and run after it. The second time, however, the little lizard was quicker and escaped to freedom, leaving Lottie with only a bony snack for all her efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching this singular drama play out before me, my mind was in a whirl. I continued on my way to the Retreat’s dining room for breakfast, and shared the story there with my friend Seva. “Surely there’s some spiritual lesson in this,” I said to her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without missing a beat, Seva replied with one word: “Detachment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As amusing as this story is, there is in fact a deep message in it for all of us. Non-attachment is one of the fundamental attitudes on the spiritual path. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are firmly held in the jaws of suffering, it’s important to cut loose that which is holding us back: that unfulfilled desire, or unattainable possession, or unsatisfied expectation of how others should treat us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also should seek inwardly to release things of a positive nature to which we’re attached—our possessions, our friends, our children, our spouse. This doesn’t mean that we reject them or give them the cold shoulder; rather, we should try to see them not as ours, but as gifts on loan to us from God. Then everything in life becomes much sweeter, as we begin to perceive God’s presence behind everything.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-curious-tail.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a curious tail&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;how to be nonattachedIs this easy? Of course not, but it is effective. Every time we inwardly detach from something troubling us or to which we’re clinging, we gain control over our happiness and our lives. In his book Affirmations for Self-Healing, Swami Kriyananda wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Nothing is ours. No one belongs to us. Mentally, we should make a bonfire of our love for God, and cast into it all attachments, all desires, all hopes and disappointments.

It helps mentally to examine one’s heart every evening, and liberate it anew of all desires. Pluck out from your heart any burrs of new attachments that you find clinging there. Cast them joyfully into the fire of devotion.

Pray to God energetically, “I destroy all my attachments. They are no longer mine, Lord. I am free in Thee!”
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here Swamiji offers us practical tools to aid in this process of detachment. Ultimately the choice is very simple: cling to your old attachments or find freedom in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, brown skink lizards do grow back a new tail. But for us, may our tale end when we replace all of our attachments with the one attachment to God alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards inner freedom,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>During the Day</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/during-the-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/during-the-day/</guid>
      <description>We are often asked, “How can I keep the peace and joy I feel in meditation during the demands and distractions of daily activity?” This is, in fact, one of life’s ever-present tests. Another way of phrasing this question is, “How can I keep my energy flowing in a positive direction, in tune with my higher aspirations, so that the world does not pull me down?”
Here are some solutions to this great challenge:</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We are often asked, “How can I keep the peace and joy I feel in meditation during the demands and distractions of daily activity?” This is, in fact, one of life’s ever-present tests. Another way of phrasing this question is, “How can I keep my energy flowing in a positive direction, in tune with my higher aspirations, so that the world does not pull me down?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some solutions to this great challenge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;during-activity&#34;&gt;During Activity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we must act, let us do our best to act properly. What constitutes proper action? We can learn much from the example of great teachers such as Patanjali, Jesus, and Buddha. Indeed, the essence of all spiritual teaching is that we should act in attunement with God or His saints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are unsure about a contemplated course of action, just ask, “Will this move me toward God or away from Him (or Her)?” The mere act of asking that question is half the battle. If we but ask, we will often feel an inward guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for when we are busily engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pray to God during the day:&lt;/strong&gt; before meals, before work, before interacting with others. It only takes a moment, and will keep the spotlight of your mind turned toward your higher Self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Control what you can:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure that the music you listen to is uplifting. A market owner was plagued by rough characters hanging around in his parking lot. His solution was brilliant. He played classical music through loudspeakers; they couldn’t stand the uplifting vibrations, and left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The same is true for the rough characters that inhabit the darker recesses of our mind. Drive them away with good vibrations.&lt;/strong&gt; Keep your environment clean and colors pure. With the movies you watch or books you read, imagine that God is sitting beside you, because He is. Choose your companions wisely; good company is vital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the breath to calm the mind.&lt;/strong&gt; Before or during tense situations, keep your posture erect and take a few deep, slow breaths. It will both center your mind and give you space to act rather than react.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;during-idle-moments&#34;&gt;During Idle Moments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have many times during the day when we are not engaged: between tasks, waiting in line, riding in a car. These are precious moments. The goal at these times is to practice the presence of God, conversing with Him as you would with a close friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some specific suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chant inwardly or repeat a mantra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the breath—you can even practice Hong-Sau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pray for those around you, or give them a smile and some positive energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remind yourself that everyone and everything you are seeing is God alone. As you gaze about, repeat to yourself, “I see only Thee, Lord.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most important of all, remember to relax and enjoy the day. Life is a long and winding road, and if we don’t enjoy the ride we will end up grim and bitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/during-the-day.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;during the day&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;when-youre-able-to-withdraw&#34;&gt;When You’re Able to Withdraw&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are times during the day when we are able to be completely still. The goal during these times is to retract the life force, bringing it inward and upward. We recently read this very powerful practice recommended by Yogananda: “The great work now before you is to practice going up and down the spine, chanting Aum at each center. In that way you will gain more than by reading all the books—practice going up and down the spine and get acquainted with those currents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often during the day you cannot control what is happening around you, but you can always control yourself. It is not difficult to practice any of these suggestions. The great challenge is to remember to do so during a busy day. If you forget, don’t despair. To paraphrase Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, “Even a little practice of the remembrance of the Divine will save us from dire fears and colossal suffering.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Joy I Live</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/in-joy-i-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/in-joy-i-live/</guid>
      <description>Anyone who has tried to have a regular practice of meditation knows that it’s no easy thing. Creating time in the midst of daily demands, leaving behind worries and preoccupations, summoning up enthusiasm every day: All of these and more are challenges we all face.
What I’d like to do is to walk you through a three-step process that may help you find renewed focus, energy, and enthusiasm for meditation.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has tried to have a regular practice of meditation knows that it’s no easy thing. Creating time in the midst of daily demands, leaving behind worries and preoccupations, summoning up enthusiasm every day: All of these and more are challenges we all face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’d like to do is to walk you through a three-step process that may help you find renewed focus, energy, and enthusiasm for meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step One:&lt;/strong&gt; Before sitting down to meditate, become aware of the thoughts and feelings that are running through your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Are you feeling rushed, and thinking, “I’ll get this over quickly”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Decide how much time you have, and be fully present for each moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Is your body feeling tense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Try doing some pranayamas or a few yoga asanas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Are you feeling discouraged, or that you’ll never be able to meditate deeply?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: This feeling of failure is probably present in everyone who takes up meditation. In the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna says to Arjuna: “But if you cannot think of Me, then give Me your intention.” Begin each meditation with the thought, “Today I give You the best effort of which I am capable.” Don’t look back or forward, but just offer God your intention to try your best today.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/in-joy-i-live.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;in joy i live&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step Two:&lt;/strong&gt; As you begin to meditate, immediately bring your full, focused energy to the spiritual eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Does your mind quickly revert to daily activities and problems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Start with repeating or chanting with concentration the words from Master’s poem, “Samadhi”: “From joy I came, for joy I live, in sacred joy I melt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Do you find that when you make an intense effort your body gets tense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t look for results; remember, simply, that this is your time with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Become aware of where you’re holding tension, then inhale, tense, and consciously relax those body parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Do you hold the subconscious thought that you’ll never achieve your goals for meditation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Don’t look for results; remember, simply, that this is your time with God. In his book Secrets of Meditation, Swami Kriyananda writes: “The secret of meditation is to pray with deep faith—not as an outsider to heaven, but as one whose true, eternal home is heaven.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also writes: “The secret of meditation is affirming that you already are those high truths towards which you aspire: inner peace, divine love, and perfect joy.” Try to feel that everything you are seeking is already within you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step Three:&lt;/strong&gt; After you finish meditation, throughout the day try to hold on to the feelings of peace that you experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: Do you leap into activities as soon as you finish meditation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Build a bridge between meditation and activity. Consciously do simple activities, such as making your bed, during which you keep your mind calm and centered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem: As challenges arise during the day, do you fall into negative emotions and reactions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: Keep the peace of meditation as a constant reference point throughout the day. If you feel yourself getting agitated, immediately try to direct your energy to the spiritual eye until you feel calmness restored. You can also bring to mind again Master’s words: “From joy I came, for joy I live, in sacred joy I melt.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we walk the spiritual path, it’s hard to see changes in ourselves, but that doesn’t mean we aren’t growing. Once Swamiji was discussing the progress that various Ananda members had made. Almost unaware of what I was saying, I blurted out, “I don’t see that I’ve changed all that much.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With great intensity, he said, “How can you say that? You’re an entirely different person than when you came.” This is true of anyone who sincerely tries their best to meditate and follow the spiritual path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s meditate with joy, live in joy, and eagerly anticipate the day when we melt in joy once more. And in our love for God, offer to Him the fruits of our efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Approach for Every Challenge</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/an-approach-for-every-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/an-approach-for-every-challenge/</guid>
      <description>Many readers will know that Ananda Village was mostly destroyed by a huge forest fire in 1976. Devi and I were new parents with an eleven-day-old infant when the flames devoured our home, our clothes, and virtually all our possessions. In meditation this morning I was remembering that day and contemplating some of the cherished lessons I learned.
It was June 28, 1976. Our first awareness of danger was when we saw smoke arising from a nearby road.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Many readers will know that Ananda Village was mostly destroyed by a huge forest fire in 1976. Devi and I were new parents with an eleven-day-old infant when the flames devoured our home, our clothes, and virtually all our possessions. In meditation this morning I was remembering that day and contemplating some of the cherished lessons I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was June 28, 1976. Our first awareness of danger was when we saw smoke arising from a nearby road. The summer was upon us, and the fields and forests had already begun to dry out. The hundred or so members of the community were at first merely vigilant, then concerned, and finally aroused into action. The winds were blowing the fire uphill through knee-high grasses, and in our direction. About twenty of us gathered on a road at the crest of the hill with rakes, hoes, and whatever firefighting equipment we had at our disposal. I had a small water-tank backpack with a pump and nozzle, which we kept handy in case a chimney fire broke out in our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire was creeping steadily up the hill toward us, waist-high flames spread across the terrain. For some inexplicable reason I decided that it would be a good idea to go down the hill, meet the flames head on, and slow them down with my pumper. As I approached, however, I realized that the flames were moving much faster than I’d thought, and much faster than I could run up the hill. In a moment I realized my safest bet was to jump through the wall of flames into the already burned area. This may have saved my life, and it also steeled my determination to fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then returned to our house. It was a small geodesic dome with a leaky roof, but it was home for our little family. I was completely focused on digging a little perimeter trench when a young member of the community drove up shouting, “You have to leave. The flames are in the trees. There’s no chance to save your house.” Only then did I realize the unstoppable force of nature unleashed. Devi, meanwhile, had taken our infant son to the doctor for his first checkup. That morning she had packed up the items from our meditation room, intending to clean it when she got home. In the few remaining moments, this was all I could save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finally emerged from the smoking hillside, I found Devi standing there, obviously alarmed, not knowing whether I was alive or dead. My first instinct was to comfort her and do what I could to de-escalate the alarm while still letting her know that our home was gone. My first words, some of the best I’ve ever spoken, were, “Well, we don’t have to worry about those leaks anymore.” We comforted each other and soon realized that our baby’s real home was built from the threads of love in our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I contemplated that fateful event I realized that there were different approaches to working with the challenges presented by the fire, each of which was valid. The same is true for the spiritual tests we face.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/an-approach-for-every-challenge.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;an approach for every challenge&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confront it head-on.&lt;/strong&gt; If the challenge seems small enough to overcome, our growth lies in confronting it. Spiritually, it may be the fires of anger or the fear of loss that has to be faced. We will each draw our own test to conquer, sized just right for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept, surrender, and move on.&lt;/strong&gt; Many of life’s issues are too big for us to change. Politics, economics, pandemics, and weather are all things that we can’t fight individually. The best approach here is just to accept conditions as they are, surrender ourselves to the goodness of God, and move on. This is harder than it seems, since it involves overcoming the reactive process. It will help if you can remember that it is all a dream of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think of others.&lt;/strong&gt; Finally, the best spiritual approach in almost all situations is to forget about yourself and your “needs.” Think about the welfare of others. Self-forgetfulness broadens the human heart and opens up space for the all-healing flow of love. It then becomes possible to offer up the little love that is in us into the infinite love of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fires of devotion,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our True Value</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/our-true-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/our-true-value/</guid>
      <description>In the first few years after Swami Kriyananda started Ananda, a number of swamis from India visited us. Most of them were not well known and were traveling alone without any entourage, but they brought with them the authentic spirituality of India. Perhaps it was Yoganandaji’s way of helping to imbue our lives, and Ananda’s work for the future, with deep spiritual vibrations.
One of these swamis said something in answer to a question I put to him that made a lasting impact on my life.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In the first few years after Swami Kriyananda started Ananda, a number of swamis from India visited us. Most of them were not well known and were traveling alone without any entourage, but they brought with them the authentic spirituality of India. Perhaps it was Yoganandaji’s way of helping to imbue our lives, and Ananda’s work for the future, with deep spiritual vibrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these swamis said something in answer to a question I put to him that made a lasting impact on my life. I asked, “How do you develop the kind of dedication that enables you to stay on the spiritual path for your whole life?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His answer puzzled me at the time, and over the years I’ve tried to understand its deeper meaning. He replied simply, “Don’t compare yourself to others.” That was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’d never met before, so his response couldn’t have been based on seeing something in my behavior. But high souls have a deep sense of intuition that enables them to pierce to the heart of things. Over time I could see how his reply had hit home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw how most of my training in life was to find my value by comparing my performance to that of others. “Am I better than my classmates?” “How much better?” “Am I the best?” were questions that ran through my mind. I wanted to do well in school and work, but my only gauge to judge my value was to compare my performance with others. This kind of thinking may get you to the top of your class or job, but it has its limitations in our spiritual growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I read an article by a psychologist about something called “Goal Orientation Theory.” According to this, there are two kinds of goals: 1)“performance-oriented goals,” also called “ego-goals” (I’m not making this up), and 2) “mastery-oriented goals,” also called “learning goals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With “performance-oriented goals,” we try to show others how well we’re doing and are concerned about how they judge us. With “mastery-oriented goals,” we seek challenges and try to overcome difficulties, and our primary concern is self-improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/our-true-value.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;our true value&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This psychological distinction reflects the same thing that the swami told me years ago. By comparing ourself with others, we’re stuck in a world of smoke and mirrors in which all we see are distorted reflections of who we really are. By seeking inner challenges and personal growth, we move towards self-mastery, wherein lies our actual value. And in the ultimate realization of our oneness with God we find truly the only thing in life worth achieving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his book Visits to Saints of India, Swami Kriyananda wrote about a saint he’d visited in 1960 named Yogi Ramiah, or Sri Rama Yogi. Yoganandaji had previously visited him during his return trip to India in 1936, and said that he was a fully liberated master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji wrote, “I found Sri Rama Yogi by nature extremely withdrawn, hiding his spiritual glory from a wish to avoid curiosity seeking.” He lived in a small village in southern India, with only a few aged disciples around him. Sensing his high state of consciousness, Swamiji asked him why he didn’t have a more public work through which he could help many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sri Rama Yogi answered simply, “God has done what He wants to do with this body.” He was able to cast aside the lower expression of self-will for the higher value of doing only God’s will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is our true value? It’s not what others think of us, or even what we can accomplish in this world. It lies in the truth that God is the only reality behind everything that we do and are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji put it beautifully with these words: “Beloved Lord, teach me to feel that Thou art the sole activating power, and that in recognition of Thee as the Doer lies the value of all my life’s experiences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, in God’s eyes we are all “the best.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Intuition Be Your Guide</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-intuition-be-your-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-intuition-be-your-guide/</guid>
      <description>I’ve come across some amazing and amusing examples of advanced souls being guided by intuition. These stories are from a book of letters from Paramhansa Yogananda to his second-most-advanced disciple, Yogacharya Oliver Black, My Dear Oliver. Here is the story of how Yogacharya met his guru:
Master said he was in Washington, D.C., and he was on his way back home to Los Angeles. A straight line for his travel would have been through Columbus, Ohio, but he said the inner voice/Divine Mother told him to come to Detroit.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I’ve come across some amazing and amusing examples of advanced souls being guided by intuition. These stories are from a book of letters from Paramhansa Yogananda to his second-most-advanced disciple, Yogacharya Oliver Black, My Dear Oliver. Here is the story of how Yogacharya met his guru:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master said he was in Washington, D.C., and he was on his way back home to Los Angeles. A straight line for his travel would have been through Columbus, Ohio, but he said the inner voice/Divine Mother told him to come to Detroit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After he got to Detroit, he didn’t know where to go or what to do. He got a telephone directory and ran his finger down the pages, leaf after leaf, until his finger stopped, and it stopped on the name of Maude Emerson. He called Maude Emerson and told her who he was—that he was Yogananda. She had in fact attended one of his lectures many years before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She explained to him that there was somebody meeting with a group in her home. He was teaching yoga to a class of about ten to twelve people. Master said, “I want to meet that man.” And she got us together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another story tells of this intuitive connection in the other direction. Yogacharya writes:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-intuition-be-your-guide.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let intuition be your guide&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One morning I came to my office and I had a strange feeling or sensation, or itch, and I was scratching the back of my head, at the medulla oblongata. I went in to our treasurer’s office and said, “Well, I don’t know what’s the matter, but while I go home and get my bag, I’d like to have you get me an airplane ticket to Indianapolis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I flew to Indianapolis, and after I got there, I didn’t know what I was there for! [He took a cab to one of the two best hotels in the city.] I went in, and I went up to the counter and asked the clerk, “Is there anybody registered here by the name of Yogananda?” He looked at me and said, “No, there isn’t.” I said, “Where is this other hotel?” He said, “Oh, it’s just down the street.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got there, I went up to the counter and asked, “Is there anyone here by the name of Yogananda?” He said, “Yes, on the ninth floor.” I just went up the elevator and knocked on the door. The door opened, and there he was! Yogananda said, “I knew you would come! I knew you would come! I knew you would come!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuition develops naturally as we grow closer to God and operate more from our soul than from our ego. Intuition, you see, is the soul’s natural way of perception. We can gradually improve our intuition. First, we need to develop our ability to feel: not with emotion, but with a calm sense of knowing. Next, we need to act on our intuitive guidance, which will help it develop just as exercising a muscle helps it grow strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we saw in these two stories, they each acted on a strong feeling even though the next step had not yet been revealed. It takes faith and courage to act on intuitive guidance. Try doing it a step at a time—I wouldn’t suggest you start by buying a plane ticket. Better to wait until your intuition is more highly developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we need to deepen our meditation, and contact our soul nature. A dear friend suggested something that I will pass on to you: He told me, “I have started to keep a log of each meditation. I write down a number to indicate how much of the time my attention was focused, and I also put down a number for how deep my devotion was. Making myself accountable in this way is really helping me deepen my meditation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have started to do this as a New Year’s resolution, and can attest to its effectiveness. I can feel that it is helping me focus better, open up my intuition, and draw Master’s grace and guidance. You might want to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Permanent Gains</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/making-permanent-gains/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/making-permanent-gains/</guid>
      <description>As we enter the new year, it’s traditional to use this juncture as an opportunity to make resolutions about how we’d like to improve our life. It’s a little discouraging, however, to think back on previous New Year’s resolutions and realize that we’d resolved to change the same things in years past without any discernible results.
How much exercise equipment is bought at the beginning of the new year only to be sold unused a few months later?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;As we enter the new year, it’s traditional to use this juncture as an opportunity to make resolutions about how we’d like to improve our life. It’s a little discouraging, however, to think back on previous New Year’s resolutions and realize that we’d resolved to change the same things in years past without any discernible results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much exercise equipment is bought at the beginning of the new year only to be sold unused a few months later? Yet at the same time, it’s encouraging to reflect that we’ve never given up hope and are still trying. Our desire to improve remains with us, because it’s prompted from a higher level of our own consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I was leading a New Year’s retreat at The Expanding Light, during which we each made a list of resolutions for the coming year. During a break in the class, one of the students came up to me and said, “I find that very depressing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean?” I asked him in surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’ve been on the spiritual path for a long time now,” he replied, “and you still have things about yourself that you want to change?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately a friend of mine, Roma, happened to be walking by at that moment and rescued me. With a twinkle in her eye, she said, “Devi is the only one in the community who isn’t perfect yet. That’s why we have her working with the guests.” We all laughed, and I hope the young man realized that the search for perfection is a long process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s an aspect of personal transformation that’s often overlooked, and it’s the main thought I want to share with you today: To make lasting improvements in our life, it takes more than our own personal efforts. &lt;strong&gt;True inner change comes about through a combination of sincere devotion to God and the grace that it draws.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite passages in the Bhagavad Gita is: “To those who meditate on Me as their very own, their hearts ever united to Me by incessant inward worship, I supply their deficiencies and make permanent their gains.” (9:22)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is God who “supplies our deficiencies.”&lt;/strong&gt; He/She alone knows our shortcomings, loves us unconditionally in spite of them, and gives us the strength and understanding to transcend them. Our minds may be clouded by past karmic tendencies, but when the light of God’s love and wisdom shines in, we gain the power and clarity to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/making-permanent-gains.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;making permanent gains&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And it is God who “makes permanent our gains.”&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes it’s hard to see the spiritual progress we’ve made. We can become so focused on how much farther we have still to go that we fail to appreciate how far we have already come. Remember, whatever progress we’ve made remains with us on some level, because it’s based on the truth of our own being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through our devotion, the sense of “I-ness” that identifies with our limitations begins to dissolve. When, time and again, we stray from the knowledge of who we really are, God is there to steer us back on course towards our own highest potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as we enter the new year, remember, whatever the outer circumstances, to keep your love for God foremost in your mind. This is the most powerful and effective way to turn our resolutions into realities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referring to the passage quoted earlier, Swami Kriyananda writes in The Essence of the Bhagavad Gita: Explained by Paramhansa Yogananda: “Thus, the highest teaching, which Krishna expounds here, is to love God, the Infinite Spirit, above all: ‘to meditate on Him as one’s very own.’ God alone can lift us out of the relativities of karmic merits and demerits into the absolute peace and freedom of Infinite Being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing you a blessed and joyful New Year,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christmas and Courage</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/christmas-and-courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/christmas-and-courage/</guid>
      <description>Courage is an essential quality, needed for success in both everyday life and spiritual growth. Fortunately, courage is an innate quality of the soul. We cannot avoid the challenges that come to us, because they are drawn by our own karma and the soul’s longing to be free.
Paramhansa Yogananda says it this way: “Every day is a fresh opportunity on the part of the human ego to gather more and more exploits of heroism.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Courage is an essential quality, needed for success in both everyday life and spiritual growth. Fortunately, courage is an innate quality of the soul. We cannot avoid the challenges that come to us, because they are drawn by our own karma and the soul’s longing to be free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda says it this way: “Every day is a fresh opportunity on the part of the human ego to gather more and more exploits of heroism. Meet everybody and every circumstance on the battlefield of life with the courage of a hero and the smile of a conqueror. Whatever comes your way and needs attention must be considered a duty. Duty is not imposed upon man by any super-power. It is the inherent urge of life toward progression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is enlightening to contemplate the examples of great courage displayed in the lives of the great world saviors. Let’s imagine, for a moment, the courage demonstrated in the story of Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary was an unmarried teenage woman in the small village of Nazareth when the angel Gabriel appeared to her and asked her to bear a holy child. Her first act of faith and courage was to say yes to this astounding request. &lt;em&gt;Whatever comes your way and needs attention must be considered a duty.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph, who was betrothed to Mary, had to have the courage to defy the cultural norms of the day and accept her. &lt;em&gt;Every day is a fresh opportunity on the part of the human ego to gather more and more exploits of heroism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/christmas-and-courage.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;christmas and courage&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Courage reveals itself through the inner struggle needed to say yes to whatever comes our way and needs attention. There are many other examples of valor shown by the young holy couple: the difficult circumstances of the birth in a manger, the visitations of angels and the three wise men, and the courage to flee to Egypt in order to save the young savior. As Yogananda puts it, “It takes courage to renounce the known for the unknown.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these last four “Advent blogs” we’ve given a few examples of spiritual qualities, especially courage: Devi’s bravery in accepting a strange stranger into her home and giving him comfort, my challenge that we have the strength to “willingly accept whatever is mine to do,” and Devi’s challenge to have the resolve to forgive and “Bless all who ever harmed you, or ever wished you harm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is a final challenge for this year. Look into your heart and find something that has “come your way, needs attention, and must be considered a duty,” but that you have been avoiding. Take on the challenge, face it head on, and conquer it, freeing yourself from its limiting cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this holy season the Masters are supporting our efforts by sending powerful blessings of grace and courage. These are their Christmas presents to each of us, wrapped in joy and tied with the bow of love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I also send you our loving thoughts and encouragement, that you may experience the Christ consciousness during this season and always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freedom in Forgiveness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/freedom-in-forgiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/freedom-in-forgiveness/</guid>
      <description>What is true freedom? Some would say, “It’s the ability to do whatever you want whenever you want.” That’s certainly a kind of freedom, but it’s one which ultimately leads to bondage. Living in that way, we become controlled by our desires.
There is another, more enduring, type of freedom. It comes through self-discipline, calming our mind, controlling our reactions to things, and accepting that everything in our life comes from God.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;What is true freedom? Some would say, “It’s the ability to do whatever you want whenever you want.” That’s certainly a kind of freedom, but it’s one which ultimately leads to bondage. Living in that way, we become controlled by our desires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another, more enduring, type of freedom. It comes through self-discipline, calming our mind, controlling our reactions to things, and accepting that everything in our life comes from God. This kind of freedom brings inner peace, and calm acceptance of whatever comes. Self-control frees us from sense compulsion, and from the ceaseless fluctuations of the restless mind. We become masters of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/freedom-in-forgiveness.png&#34;  alt=&#34;freedom in forgiveness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Another key to finding inner freedom is the practice of forgiveness.&lt;/strong&gt; We have no control over the behavior of others. Holding onto past hurts and grievances only strengthens the false thought that we are subject to the ceaseless fluctuations of an inimical universe. Forgiveness is an act of both divine courage and love. It affirms our strength, and our ability to react positively even in adversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” we may think, “I want to love everyone, but if you only knew what she did to me—I just can’t forgive her for that.” With this kind of thinking, we reduce in our mind the vast field of God-awareness into mere patches of brambles and thorns. To forgive others reminds us that beyond the joys and sorrows of this world, our true life is in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her book &lt;em&gt;The Hiding Place&lt;/em&gt;, Corrie ten Boom tells a remarkable story of forgiveness. She, her father, and her sister Betsie were resistance workers against the Nazis in Holland during World War II. Though not themselves Jewish, they hid many Jews in their home and helped them to escape. Corrie and her family were eventually arrested and sent to a concentration camp, where her sister and father perished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corrie survived and later began a global ministry, sharing the teachings of Christ throughout the world. She tells this dramatic story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was at a church service in Munich that I saw him, the former S.S. man who had stood guard at the shower door in the processing center at Ravensbrück. He was the first of our actual jailers that I had seen since that time. And suddenly it was all there—the roomful of mocking men, the heaps of clothing, Betsie’s pain-blanched face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He came up to me as the church was emptying, beaming and bowing. “How grateful I am for your message, Fräulein,” he said. “To think that, as you say, He has washed my sins away!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His hand was thrust out to shake mine. And I, who preached so often to the people in Bloemendaal the need to forgive, kept my hand at my side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as the angry, vengeful thoughts boiled through me, I saw the sin of them. Jesus Christ had died for this man; was I going to ask for more? Lord Jesus, I prayed, forgive me and help me to forgive him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to smile, I struggled to raise my hand. I could not. I felt nothing, not the slightest spark of warmth or charity. And so again I breathed a silent prayer. Jesus, I cannot forgive him. Give me your forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I took his hand the most incredible thing happened. From my shoulder along my arm and through my hand a current seemed to pass from me to him, while into my heart sprang a love for this stranger that almost overwhelmed me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so I discovered that it is not on our forgiveness any more than on our goodness that the world’s healing hinges, but on his. When he tells us to love our enemies, he gives, along with the command, the love itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past two weeks, Jyotish and I offered you two practices to follow during this holy season: 1) to feel God’s love flowing through you constantly throughout the day; and 2) to accept willingly whatever is given to you as yours to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in this third week of Advent—the month before Christmas—we offer you another suggestion. Follow these words of Swami Kriyananda: &lt;strong&gt;“Claim your soul’s freedom! Bless all who ever harmed you, or ever wished you harm. Give them your love, and your prayer for their freedom in God.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May you, like Corrie, feel God’s love flowing through you as you forgive others. May each one of us place our little candle on the divine altar of forgiveness, whose light can heal and bless the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing you blessings in this holy season,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discontent to Some Extent</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/discontent-to-some-extent/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/discontent-to-some-extent/</guid>
      <description>During a recent talk in Bangalore, India, I said that most people are “discontent to some extent.” Devi liked the catchy phrase so much that she even wryly suggested we should print it on T-shirts. Personally, I think that’s going too far, but it does make a good topic for a blog.
Poetically speaking, God sings the universe into existence by chanting AUM, the vibration of duality. One of these dualities is likes and dislikes.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;During a recent talk in Bangalore, India, I said that most people are “discontent to some extent.” Devi liked the catchy phrase so much that she even wryly suggested we should print it on T-shirts. Personally, I think that’s going too far, but it does make a good topic for a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poetically speaking, God sings the universe into existence by chanting AUM, the vibration of duality. One of these dualities is likes and dislikes. As Sri Yukteswar put it, “The mere existence of a physical body signifies that its existence is made possible by unfulfilled desires.” Poetically speaking, discontent is the glue that holds creation together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the fastest (and happiest) paths to Self-realization is simply to accept things as they are. We spend so much time and effort pushing away things in the world that don’t fit our particular bundle of likes and dislikes. Wanting things to be other than they are drains us of our energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda tells of an interesting revelation in this regard. This incident took place when he was living in San Francisco. His schedule was intense, with classes in different locations every evening as well as writing, correspondence, and counseling required during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One evening he was scheduled to teach a class on “Energy and Energization” in Palo Alto, California. He stopped at his parents’ house, which happened to be close to the classroom. His mother took one look at him and said, “You look exhausted. You just have to cancel that class tonight.” He knew that wasn’t possible, but compromised by taking a rest.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/discontent-to-some-extent.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;discontent to some extent&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of falling asleep, he began to think of all the obligations that were sapping his strength. He realized that the problem wasn’t the actual work itself but rather the energy drained by his mental resistance. One by one he visualized each obligation: the classes and commute time, the correspondence, the writing, the many people asking for his guidance. As each one arose, he deeply accepted it. As he did so his energy flooded back. When he emerged from the bedroom his mother remarked, “Oh, you look so much better! You must have had a good nap.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working with him at the time as his assistant, and he told me about the experience the next day. He concluded the story with a twinkle in his eye and the comment, “It was the best class on energy I have ever given.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just an interesting story but a life lesson. Who among us hasn’t felt resentful about our responsibilities? And, who among us hasn’t felt drained because of inner resistance? This very morning in meditation I was doing what Swamiji did that evening so many years ago. I was deeply accepting that which God has given me to do. And, like Swamiji, I emerged from our meditation room with much greater energy and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s use this holy advent season as a chance to develop new qualities and re-energize our spiritual life. Last week Devi wrote, &lt;em&gt;“I invite you to join me in this challenge for the rest of 2022: to feel God’s love flowing through you in each moment of the day. This is the greatest gift you can give to the world. And who knows? God may come in hidden form to receive it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I invite you to add this challenge. From now until the end of the year practice this: “I will willingly accept whatever is given to me as mine to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we do this we will become “more content to a great extent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Message in a Strange Encounter</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter/</guid>
      <description>The winter’s night was very cold and windy, and I huddled by the little stove in my camper reading the Bible by the light of a kerosene lamp. In the early years of Ananda our dwellings were simple—without electricity, running water, phones, or any way to communicate with others.
But we were more than happy to live in whatever was available—campers, teepees, old delivery trucks—just to be part of Ananda. Here we could dedicate our lives to God as well as help Swami Kriyananda fulfill Yoganandaji’s dream of world brotherhood colonies.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The winter’s night was very cold and windy, and I huddled by the little stove in my camper reading the Bible by the light of a kerosene lamp. In the early years of Ananda our dwellings were simple—without electricity, running water, phones, or any way to communicate with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we were more than happy to live in whatever was available—campers, teepees, old delivery trucks—just to be part of Ananda. Here we could dedicate our lives to God as well as help Swami Kriyananda fulfill Yoganandaji’s dream of world brotherhood colonies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this particular night as I was reading, I was startled to hear a loud pounding on the door. I cautiously opened it, and there on the cinder block step stood a strange man with a wild look in his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I need to come in,” he said in a demanding voice. Offering silent prayers to God for protection, I stood aside and let him enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sat down on one of the two benches at my little table. “I’m hungry. What do you have to eat?” he again demanded. (More silent prayers on my part.) I offered him some food which he ate voraciously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m thirsty. What can I drink?”(Still more silent prayers.) I placed some water before him, which he quickly gulped down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeming to relax a bit he said, “I like it here. It’s nice and warm.” After a pause he added, “I have these big sores on my arms.” He rolled up one of his sleeves and showed me open, oozing sores on his arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(“Please God, resolve this quickly,” I fervently prayed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more moments passed. Then he suddenly stood up and said, “Thank you. I have to go now,” and quickly departed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totally baffled by what had just happened, I sat stunned for a few minutes. Then taking a few deep breaths, I continued reading the Bible. These were the first words that my eyes fell upon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;For I was hungry, and ye gave me meat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink; I was a stranger, and ye took me in;

Naked, and ye clothed me; I was sick, and ye visited me; I was in prison, and ye came unto me.

Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, and fed thee? or thirsty, and gave thee drink? . . .

And the King shall answer and say unto them, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto me.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;“God,” I asked inwardly, “was it really You who came in the form of that desperate man?” I never saw the stranger again. To this day I’ve suspected that the encounter was God’s way of showing me that He Himself receives any act of kindness we express to others.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the message in a strange encounter&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now as we approach the Christmas season, it’s a good opportunity to introspect and cleanse our hearts of any negative emotions we may hold towards others. Throughout December, I’m taking up the personal challenge of holding only positive, loving thoughts towards everyone—be they wise or foolish; well-kempt or disheveled. Remember that love offered to any form of life is love offered to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Whispers from Eternity, Master writes: “Let every feeling that I have glow with Thy love. Let every act of my will be impregnated with Thy divine vitality. Let every thought, every expression, every ambition be ornamented by Thee.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invite you to join me in this challenge for the rest of 2022: to feel God’s love flowing through you in each moment of the day. This is the greatest gift you can give to the world. And who knows? God may come in hidden form to receive it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your sister in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Letter to God</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-letter-to-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-letter-to-god/</guid>
      <description>Dear God,
This has been a particularly eventful year, and it seems fitting that I should write You a note of gratitude.
My heart is very full, and words seem insufficient. I know that You don’t need my words of thanks any more than the sun needs to be praised for sending forth its rays, but for my own sake let me recognize how much love You shower on me.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Dear God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a particularly eventful year, and it seems fitting that I should write You a note of gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My heart is very full, and words seem insufficient. I know that You don’t need my words of thanks any more than the sun needs to be praised for sending forth its rays, but for my own sake let me recognize how much love You shower on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, thank you for this enlightened path and for the wonderful teachers You have sent. Let me thank You above all for Master and for Swamiji, who have molded my life and blessed my humble self-effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for Devi, my friend and life companion. What a joy and fulfilment our life together has been. And thank you for the joy that comes from our son and grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-letter-to-god.png&#34;  alt=&#34;a letter to god&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Divine Mother, for giving us so many loving friends. Everywhere we go You are wearing a different disguise, waiting for us with a warm smile and a new experience. Thanks, also, for the constant support and beautiful examples of discipleship with which you’ve surrounded us. What wonderful times we’ve had this last year: amazing food, interesting trips, and let’s not forget all the jokes and laughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for the many outward gifts You have given us: of health, energy, and enthusiasm. I’m grateful, too, for having sufficient finances so that we not only have enough to live simply and comfortably, but also enough to share with others and to give back to You in remembrance that You are the giver of all that we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful, too, for all the tests that You’ve provided. This year, with all the travel, has been particularly helpful in stripping away so many unnecessary necessities. The constant changes have helped me drop those unwanted habits that managed to creep in, and establish new and better ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all these outward signs pale in comparison with Your inward gifts. Thank you for the peace of mind and the expansion of love that I feel when my mind begins to become still. Thank you for the inward yearning to reunite with You and for the techniques, especially Kriya, that bring me closer with each meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, thank you for the growing realization that it is all You. You are playing all the parts and doing all the deeds. It is, in a strange way, You writing this note of appreciation to Yourself. As “I” mentioned at the beginning, words seem insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With deepest gratitude and appreciation,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Global Circle of Love</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-global-circle-of-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-global-circle-of-love/</guid>
      <description>This is a special moment in time for Jyotish and me. Yesterday we had our last public satsang in Mumbai after nearly four months of traveling, teaching, and sharing love with friends in Assisi and India. By the time you read this, we will be returning to Ananda Village.
In many ways, this trip has been life-changing. Seeing the waves of devotion to Yoganandaji spreading throughout the world, we realize how blessed we’ve been to be a part of this great work started by Swami Kriyananda over fifty years ago.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This is a special moment in time for Jyotish and me. Yesterday we had our last public satsang in Mumbai after nearly four months of traveling, teaching, and sharing love with friends in Assisi and India. By the time you read this, we will be returning to Ananda Village.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this trip has been life-changing. Seeing the waves of devotion to Yoganandaji spreading throughout the world, we realize how blessed we’ve been to be a part of this great work started by Swami Kriyananda over fifty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-global-circle-of-love.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a global circle of love&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thousands of new students are studying Master’s teachings in person and online, and thousands more are taking discipleship and initiation into Kriya Yoga. What touched us the most, however, was seeing the divine love for others that is being offered by Ananda devotees throughout the world. Here are three stories that we heard during our travels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was told to us by Mahiya, one of the leaders of Ananda Assisi. It took place at Terre di Luce (Lands of Light), their beautiful organic gardens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer, Satya, a Kriyaban friend, came to help us in the kitchen. He brought his parents with him: Adamo, ninety-two years old, and Eleonora, in her eighties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Satya did his service in the kitchen, they would sit on the sofas and just be. Often people would sit with them, making conversation and expressing kindness. Satya had told them nothing about this path, and they had no idea what Ananda was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eleonora has dementia, but Adamo was fully aware of everything. He loved it here, and wanted to participate in everything! When Satya tried to leave them at the nearby house he had rented, Adamo would have nothing of it—he wanted to be at Terre di Luce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every afternoon after lunch we have a chanting circle before we start our service. We would often chant to the Guru or to Divine Mother in Sanskrit. The fact that it was all in a strange language didn’t matter to Adamo—he would never miss the chanting circle! After one circle he said, “This place is a paradise. I want to stay here forever. Here you are all friends, and everybody loves and respects one another. You can’t find that in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks after Satya and his parents went back to Rome, Adamo left his body. We had an Astral Ascension Ceremony for him in which everyone shared deeply how much this wonderful soul loved Ananda. We all felt that his wish of “wanting to stay at Ananda forever,” or in the presence of the Masters that he felt here, had come true: He was now in the astral world in the loving hands of our Masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what Terre di Luce is for me and why I love it here. I see it as a place where people come and experience love and friendship which transforms them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories of kindness and compassion from our travels in India are too numerous to tell (I’ll share a few more in the recorded commentary), but two others especially stand out. India was hit very hard by the pandemic, with many deaths and inadequate supplies of medicine, oxygen, and hospital beds. Our center leaders told us that they were often performing eight to ten Astral Ascension Ceremonies per week for members or their loved ones who had passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two dear Kriyaban friends of ours, Dr. Mansi and Dr. Amar, shared stories about serving together on the Covid ward in a hospital in Pune. They’re a married couple, with two teenaged daughters and his parents living with them. In spite of these responsibilities, they served for months on end, often with just a few hours of sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the hospital began filling up with Covid patients who occupied all the beds and spilled out into the hallways, Dr. Amar felt some hesitation about working in such close proximity to infected people. He thought, “I don’t want to catch the disease and bring it home to my family.” In answer, he heard a voice within him say, “Would you hesitate to help your own children? These people are all your children!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this divine guidance, he served wholeheartedly throughout the pandemic. Both he and Dr. Mansi did contract Covid, but their children and parents were never infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the pandemic, when the deaths began overwhelming even the crematoriums, Dr. Mansi was exhausted and hit an emotional wall. One day in particular she saw many deaths not only of the elderly, but also of young men who were the sole support of their families. She returned home in the evening exhausted and with a heavy heart. As she closed her eyes for a few minutes, she had a remarkable dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it Master appeared in the hospital dressed in silvery-white robes, bustling here and there attending to the patients. He turned to her and said, “The disease is caused by bad karma brought on by people’s negative thoughts. We can’t stop the disease, but we must stay very busy trying to help everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mansi then began shaping balls of mud into babies. When she held them, they were living children; when she put them down they were only mud once more. “Don’t you see?” Master said. “When Divine Mother touches them, they come alive. Otherwise they are dead. Don’t grieve, my daughter.” After this dream, Mansi was able to continue in her service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, in these stories you can see the beauty of living for God and serving Him in others. Our lives have been changed by witnessing such self-offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behind the Stern Facade</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/behind-the-stern-facade/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/behind-the-stern-facade/</guid>
      <description>We recently heard a remarkable story about Sri Yukteswar. Many devotees have a little difficulty relating to him, since he seems a bit forbidding. Perhaps it is because in Autobiography of a Yogi, Paramhansa Yogananda writes about him in his role as both teacher and disciplinarian, a job he took very seriously, especially knowing that he was preparing Master for a world-changing role.
But the grandson of Tulsi Bose, Master’s close friend, told us that when Sri Yukteswar visited their home he was completely different.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We recently heard a remarkable story about Sri Yukteswar. Many devotees have a little difficulty relating to him, since he seems a bit forbidding. Perhaps it is because in Autobiography of a Yogi, Paramhansa Yogananda writes about him in his role as both teacher and disciplinarian, a job he took very seriously, especially knowing that he was preparing Master for a world-changing role.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/behind-the-stern-facade.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;behind the stern facade&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the grandson of Tulsi Bose, Master’s close friend, told us that when Sri Yukteswar visited their home he was completely different. He was a kind, lovable, grandfatherly figure who usually had sweets to offer to the many children who gathered around him. I, myself, had an experience where I felt his sweetness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were about to begin a Kriya Initiation in Chennai, India, and the pictures on the altar were all garlanded. As I was bowing to each of our Masters, I mentally prayed to Sri Yukteswar to help me relate to him more deeply. The instant the prayer formed in my mind, the garland around his photo fell off, and I was given the opportunity to lovingly re-garland him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is the remarkable story related to us by Nayaswami Aditya, our center leader in Pune:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bhuvan Pal Singh joined the online classes in Pune during the first wave of Covid and became a Kriyaban. I immediately recognized him as someone who felt like an old friend. He was sincere, with deep yearning and humility, and asked many questions to refine his spiritual practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bhuvan’s lifelong yearning had been to leave everything and go to the Himalayas, but he found himself supporting his entire extended family of thirty-five people, something he did quite happily and very well. During the first wave of the pandemic he took retirement from his successful corporate career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Bhuvan began his Kriya practice, he was diagnosed with a rare malignant cancer of the muscles of his right forearm. Expert advice from the best doctors in the country informed him that little could be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With tears in his eyes Bhuvan related this story: “One day I was undergoing a PET scan to assess the spread of the tumor in my body and found myself alone in a hospital room. As I sat there I prayed to the Masters, “I am feeling very alone.” I instantly had a vision of the form of Sri Yukteswarji in front of me. As his life-size form slowly moved towards me, it shrunk in size until he became very small and entered into my body through my spiritual eye. From within I heard Swami Sri Yukteswarji say, ‘Bhuvan, don’t feel alone or afraid, for I am in every cell of your body.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bhuvanji continued his daily Kriya practice, and although he followed the suggested treatments, his health deteriorated over the months and on 26 January 2022 he left his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days later, his wife, Anupama, had the following experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was awakened early one morning by the sound of the main door of our house being unfastened. As I opened my eyes, I saw a bright yellow light falling on the door, and curious to see what this light was, I moved towards it. Just then I heard and saw my husband, in physical form, seated in the living room in meditative pose, his gaze uplifted. He said to me, ‘Anupama, don’t move. I’m exiting now.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I stood still, and watched my husband exit into that light. A couple of hours after this experience I got a call from my niece in New Delhi. She told me that the previous night she had dreamt that she saw a bright yellow light fall on our house, especially on the main door. In the dream she saw her uncle Bhuvan enter that light.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anupama has kindly given Nayaswami Aditya permission, and we thank her for allowing us to share this sacred experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Swamiji’s passing Devi and I had a “Nadi” reading from an ancient book of prophecy. During that reading we were told that Yogananda was watching out for us minute by minute and second by second. This applies to all of us who have opened our hearts to this great line of masters. Yoganandaji, as Swami Kriyananda explained, was a Blissavatar (incarnation of divine joy). Yoganandaji described Sri Yukteswar as a gyanavatar (incarnation of wisdom). In fact, in God’s light all His qualities merge into one, and in our hour of need we, too, will find that God’s light is in every cell of our body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bring Me a Mustard Seed</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/bring-me-a-mustard-seed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/bring-me-a-mustard-seed/</guid>
      <description>The woman sobbed inconsolably as she pressed the body of her dead child to her bosom. A sympathetic neighbor, on seeing her so overwhelmed with grief, said, “A saint has come to visit our village. Perhaps he can perform a miracle and bring your child back to life.”
Gathering the body of her child in her arms, the woman rushed to the feet of Buddha, for it was indeed he to whom the neighbor had been referring.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The woman sobbed inconsolably as she pressed the body of her dead child to her bosom. A sympathetic neighbor, on seeing her so overwhelmed with grief, said, “A saint has come to visit our village. Perhaps he can perform a miracle and bring your child back to life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gathering the body of her child in her arms, the woman rushed to the feet of Buddha, for it was indeed he to whom the neighbor had been referring. “Sir,” she sobbed, holding up the lifeless little form, “Can you bring my child back to life?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a heart filled with compassion and wisdom, Buddha replied, “My daughter, first bring me a mustard seed from a home that has not known death and suffering.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desperately she went from house to house, but alas at each one she heard a similar story: “We have lost our beloved father.” “Our dear son passed away last month.” “Since our mother who cared for us died there is no one to look after us.” On and on she went throughout the village, even to the huts in the outlying areas, but nowhere could she find anyone who had not known death and loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, exhausted, she returned to Buddha with no mustard seed. Touching his feet, she said, “Lord, now I have understood. Death and suffering visit us all.” Buddha then blessed her, her grief lifted, and her heart was comforted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saints of all religions teach that everything in life is transitory. All human suffering is caused by seeking permanence in an impermanent world. Only through inner detachment can we find lasting peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Globally, we now find ourselves in a world filled with suffering, as environmental, social, financial, and political tensions move us toward an uncertain future. How can we find comfort in such times?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jyotish and I are now in Pune, India, where last weekend the Ananda Center here hosted an inspiring and powerful daylong spiritual fair attended by many hundreds of people. The keynote talk we’d been asked to give was entitled, “Stand Unshaken: How to Face Change with Courage.” Here are four points that we shared to help people deal with uncertainty, change, and loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, when difficulties come, don’t ask self-pityingly, “Why me?” Ask rather, &lt;strong&gt;“What am I supposed to learn from this?”&lt;/strong&gt; All of life’s experiences, whether individually or societally, are given to us to expand our awareness. If we can depersonalize our suffering, and try to see the bigger picture, everything becomes a source of greater understanding and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, when going through challenges, try to find ways to be of service to others. We have a devotee friend in India who lost his teenaged son to leukemia; two weeks later his father passed away from Covid. What was his response to such grief? He called his nearby Ananda Center and asked, “What can I do to help others?” He became a part of our twenty-four-hour hotline to bring comfort to those experiencing grief and fear during the pandemic. Through his service, he found acceptance of his own loss.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/bring-me-a-mustard-seed.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;bring me a mustard seed&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, of great importance: practice meditation. Through this discipline we can develop inner detachment that will enable us to weather any outer storm. Peace of mind, awareness of a reality greater than our own ego, inner strength: all these and more are the fruits of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, deepen your devotion and your faith in God. The plan for this world is rooted in God’s love for us all. Whatever challenges come your way, try to remember that God, with infinite love and patience, is bringing every one of us the experiences we need to find soul freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a letter that Paramhansa Yogananda wrote to one of his disciples, Kamala Silva, he says, “No matter what dark territories you have to pass through, look steadily at the Polestar of his Presence. He knows you are trying to reach Him, only keep trying. Once you convince Him, you will be there. The way is long, let’s hurry to His place. With unceasing blessings, Swami Yogananda.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the grieving mother, we can find no place in this world that is without sorrow and suffering. And so, “Let us hurry to His place.” It is only there that we will find true peace and joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Return of the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-return-of-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-return-of-the-light/</guid>
      <description>“They’re coming! Our king and queen are coming! Ram, our beloved God, and Sita, our beautiful queen, are finally coming home!” Thus rejoiced the happy citizens of Ayodhya centuries ago when Ram and Sita returned. After long years away, the living light was returning to Ayodhya, and the people were placing lamps along the road to celebrate the occasion.
This event, central to the Ramayana (one of two great spiritual epics of India), has inspired people for thousands of years.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“They’re coming! Our king and queen are coming! Ram, our beloved God, and Sita, our beautiful queen, are finally coming home!” Thus rejoiced the happy citizens of Ayodhya centuries ago when Ram and Sita returned. After long years away, the living light was returning to Ayodhya, and the people were placing lamps along the road to celebrate the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event, central to the Ramayana (one of two great spiritual epics of India), has inspired people for thousands of years. Even today the victory of light over darkness fills a deep soul-longing in the heart of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diwali, the Festival of Light, is celebrated throughout India. Lights can be seen everywhere: strings of it decorating balconies and windows, candles placed in doorways and windows and on the altars of homes, and fireworks bursting like stars in the night sky. It’s not only in India that Diwali is celebrated. In New York City it is an official public holiday, given that there are over 200,000 people of Indian origin living there. Diwali is celebrated in the White House and, of course, in the U.K., which now has the first prime minister of Indian origin. The light of Diwali is, indeed, spreading around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, these outward displays are what might be called “social Diwali.” Spiritual Diwali is our daily return to the light in the spiritual eye, which can be experienced in every meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout long cycles of time, this theme—the triumph of light over darkness—has recurred in many different forms. For much of the Western world, it is celebrated at Christmas time, when the Christ was born. Each race and culture recognizes and celebrates light in its own special way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-return-of-the-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the return of the light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This holy season is a good time to open our hearts, to recognize and give thanks to the people and events that have been channels for God’s light and love to us. For many of our readers, our “Diwali” is the coming of Paramhansa Yogananda, often experienced when we first read Autobiography of a Yogi. Take a moment to reflect on how God has come into your life, and offer prayers of gratitude. Meditate for a while on all the people—family, friends, and teachers—who have been channels of Divine Mother’s love to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that Devi and I try to do in these weekly essays is to share little moments of inspiration that occur in our lives. As a Diwali gift we were given a small book, 365 Quotes by Gandhi, and I thought it would be nice to share with you a few rays of Gandhi’s light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You may never know what results come of your actions, but if you do nothing there will be no results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whenever you are confronted with an opponent, conquer him with love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The day the power of love overrules the love of power, the world will know peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Diwali talk that Swami Kriyananda gave in India in 2004, he urged everyone to fully open themselves to God’s light. That, however, is not enough. He went on to say that we should also strive to see the light of God in everyone we meet, and that we must actively spread God’s love to a world that desperately needs it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let each of us be a channel of light and live every day as if it were Diwali, a new dawning of the divine light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I See No Stranger</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/i-see-no-stranger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/i-see-no-stranger/</guid>
      <description>The beautiful plaque on the wall of our friends’ home caught my eye. We were in Chandigarh staying with a Sikh family who are fellow disciples of Paramhansa Yogananda. They welcomed us with such graciousness and warmth that we soon felt totally at home.
The most prominent feature of the plaque that had drawn my attention was a striking drawing of the Golden Temple at Amritsar, the most sacred site for the Sikhs.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The beautiful plaque on the wall of our friends’ home caught my eye. We were in Chandigarh staying with a Sikh family who are fellow disciples of Paramhansa Yogananda. They welcomed us with such graciousness and warmth that we soon felt totally at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most prominent feature of the plaque that had drawn my attention was a striking drawing of the Golden Temple at Amritsar, the most sacred site for the Sikhs. What stood out the most for me, however, was a small poem at the bottom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I see no stranger, I see no enemy; I look upon all with goodwill. . . .
The one Beloved dwells in all. Beholding this wonder, I bloom with joy.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;These words were written nearly five hundred years ago by Guru Arjan Dev, the fifth guru in the Sikh lineage. It was he who built the holy temple at Amritsar, and who created the first rendition of the Sikh holy book, the &lt;em&gt;Guru Granth Sahib&lt;/em&gt;, which is housed there. This sacred text is a collection of his own poetry, and that of others in the line of ten Sikh gurus, as well as a number of Hindu and Muslim saints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uplifted by the drawing of the magnificent temple and those beautiful words, I was then stunned to read about the conclusion of this great soul’s life: In 1606 Guru Arjan was tortured to death by the invading Mughal emperor Jahangir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How little the world has changed,” I thought. Here we are still today with Hindu against Muslim, Muslim against Christian, Christian against Jew; with racism against Blacks; with one political party against the other; with one nation against another: the list could go on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can this ever end? It is only by the upliftment of consciousness. In the teachings of India, the term “maya” is used to denote “delusion.” To bring everything into manifestation, God divided His infinite consciousness into pairs of opposites, creating light and darkness, good and evil, joy and sorrow, male and female.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The literal meaning of “maya” is the “measurer,” that which divides the undifferentiated whole into seemingly different parts. The tension created by these dichotomies keeps us engrossed in the play of life, until our souls tire of the endless cycling between conflicting opposites. Then we crave to realize the underlying unity of all things, in which we see the One Consciousness behind the many forms.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/i-see-no-stranger.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;i see no stranger&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do believe that, contrary to current appearances, the human race is moving toward this higher perspective. Personal and global suffering are helping us to see that when one is oppressed, we all are oppressed; when one loses his security or freedom, we all lose it. This awareness must come in time, because in essence we are not separate one from another. God manifested each of us out of His own consciousness; we are all equally parts of Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, a friend gave us an original edition of Paramhansa Yogananda’s book of poetry, &lt;em&gt;Songs of the Soul&lt;/em&gt;, which was signed by him personally. His inscription reads: “There is one breath that enlivens all strange lands and strangers. Under one sky we live watched by One Father. With my blessings, Swami Yogananda, Oct. 20, 1924.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May we all awaken to that consciousness in which, blessed by one Father, we see no strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With hope,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Sacred Gift</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-sacred-gift/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-sacred-gift/</guid>
      <description>Devi wrote recently about our pilgrimage to sacred sites in Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore. On our last day in Serampore a very special gift was given to us.
This city is on the banks of the Ganges and was the location of Sri Yukteswar’s ashram, where Paramhansa Yogananda spent the better part of ten years in training with his beloved guru. During that period, Yogananda often visited the family of his elder brother, Anantalal Ghosh, who also resided in Serampore.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi wrote recently about our pilgrimage to sacred sites in Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore. On our last day in Serampore a very special gift was given to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This city is on the banks of the Ganges and was the location of Sri Yukteswar’s ashram, where Paramhansa Yogananda spent the better part of ten years in training with his beloved guru. During that period, Yogananda often visited the family of his elder brother, Anantalal Ghosh, who also resided in Serampore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had lunch with members of the Ghosh family. We have known Durlov and his son Ishan for years, having first met them many years ago with Swami Kriyananda. At the end of the meal we withdrew to a private patio where they presented us with an extremely precious plate that had been in the family for well over one hundred years. Here is a description given to us by Ishan of this sacred relic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The object which we gave you is a plate made of stone. My father heard from his grandmother, that is, the wife of Anantalal Ghosh, that this plate was there when she was married. That means it must have been bought by either Guruji’s parents or someone else in the family in or before the year Anantalal Ghosh was married. Plates like this are usually used in Indian families for offering food to the gods. Usually, they rest at family altars, and so was the case with this plate as well. However, when Paramhansa Yogananda became a sanyasi, it was not possible for him to accept food at home, since all of the kitchen plates were somehow in touch with meat or fish. Therefore, he was offered food instead on plates from the altar; the plates in which food has been offered to the gods; the plate which we gave you. When Paramhansa Yogananda came back to India, he had his meals on these plates as always. This plate has been there in our family for more than a hundred years, and we gifted it to you since we feel that more people should have the opportunity to drink from its spiritual vibrations. We are so pleased that the gods gave us the opportunity to forward such priceless spiritual vibrations into your hands. We are so pleased that you accepted it with such deep reverence and joy.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-sacred-gift.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a sacred gift&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Presently the plate rests on the lap of a statue of Master that sits in our meditation room in Delhi. We will soon place it along with other sacred objects where visitors and pilgrims can meditate and feel the holy vibrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plate also embodies a deep spiritual lesson for us all. Food is a symbol of the gift of life from Divine Mother, and Yogananda would only eat if the food had first been offered back to God. But everything is a gift from Divine Mother, and God-offering should be applied to all aspects of life. Yogananda spoke of this truth poetically in his beautiful poem “God! God! God!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first rise from slumber, the day ahead should be offered to God. When we break our fast, we should be aware that the very food we eat is a form of Divine Mother. If, during our working hours, the spotlight of our mind ever keeps returning to God, our work can be transformed into sacred service. Giving God our worries, our memories, and our dreams transforms the mundane into the sacred. Ultimately, it is our love above all that must be purified through offering it to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually, all that we “own,” and all that we think we “are,” must be offered into God’s light. He will receive our offerings, purify them, and then playfully join us in a life free from attachment to the delusion of “I” and “mine.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t is interesting that the essence of the spiritual path is somehow magically condensed into a single sacred plate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pink Man</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/pink-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/pink-man/</guid>
      <description>My major field of study in college was cultural anthropology. One of my professors shared some interesting experiences he’d had during a year in which he lived with a remote tribe in New Guinea. These people were so inaccessible that they’d never seen a Westerner before.
At first they just ignored him or stared at him suspiciously as though he were a new variety of albino snake or toad. After weeks of such treatment, he would withdraw into his tent, read Shakespeare, and try to affirm, “I am an educated, intelligent human being who is part of an advanced civilization.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;My major field of study in college was cultural anthropology. One of my professors shared some interesting experiences he’d had during a year in which he lived with a remote tribe in New Guinea. These people were so inaccessible that they’d never seen a Westerner before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first they just ignored him or stared at him suspiciously as though he were a new variety of albino snake or toad. After weeks of such treatment, he would withdraw into his tent, read Shakespeare, and try to affirm, “I am an educated, intelligent human being who is part of an advanced civilization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little by little the tribe’s people saw that he meant them no harm, and they allowed him to enter into their daily life. As he began to learn their language and culture, he realized that what they’d been calling him all along was “Pink Man.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After more time had passed, he no longer had to affirm who he had been, but could accept that he was now a different version of himself. After a year, “Pink Man” returned to his university and wrote an ethnography of the tribe that had opened his eyes to another worldview and helped change how he thought about himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the professor’s experience, I realized that what interested me was not so much the customs and languages of other peoples, but the opportunity to expand one’s self-definition by immersing in a different reality. Fortunately, God showed me a better way to do this through the spiritual path and discipleship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inner self-transformation is never easy, no matter how you approach it. In trying to transcend self-limitations and old ways of thinking, we find ourselves clinging to the familiar, even if it no longer serves our aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/pink-man.png&#34;  alt=&#34;pink man&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Paramhansa Yogananda’s unparalleled explanation of the Bhagavad Gita, he tells us that the challenges Arjuna faces before the battle of Kurukshetra are allegorical. Each character, friend or foe, is symbolic of an inner quality that lives within each of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those on the opposing side, the Kauravas, are his relatives and mentors, although they represent such things as material desire, ego, habits, and attachment. As the great warrior Arjuna surveys the Kaurava army before the battle begins, he becomes discouraged, drops his bow, and says to his charioteer, Krishna, “These are my kinsmen. I cannot kill them. Therefore, I will not fight.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji explains that this is the inner battle we all must face. We fear killing old patterns and habits, because we’re not sure who we will become when the familiar is gone. Yet unless we take up the fight, we can never discover our own higher Self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the remainder of the Gita, Krishna explains to Arjuna that the true Self is never lost, but through spiritual effort, its energy is transmuted into a higher expression. “The soul is never touched; it is immutable, all-pervading, calm, unshakable; its existence is eternal.” (Chapter 2:24)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Jyotish and I enter our second month of traveling to Ananda centers in Italy and India, the process of personal transformation and letting go of the familiar is something we face daily. What a joy to offer oneself up to the process, allowing God to guide us toward inner freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether through the example of “Pink Man” overcoming the fear of loss of self-identity, or Arjuna transcending the reluctance to fight old mental tendencies, we need to take the leap of faith. It’s by surrendering the self to God that we go beyond our limitations and find who and what we really are: a spark of the Divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steps to Happiness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for The Times of India, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called The Speaking Tree, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt;, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called &lt;em&gt;The Speaking Tree&lt;/em&gt;, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016. Friends encouraged me to share it once again. I, too, thought you might enjoy seeing it, even if for a second time. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;five-essential-steps-to-happiness&#34;&gt;Five Essential Steps to Happiness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “I once met a very successful and wealthy man, who said to me, ‘I’m disgustingly healthy, and disgustingly wealthy.’ ‘However,’ I replied, ‘you are not “disgustingly happy,” are you?’ He admitted he was not. Soon afterward, he became a student of this path.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness is something that everyone searches for but very few are able to find. Here are five key steps that lead to permanent happiness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must want to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to accept guidance to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to apply self-discipline in order to follow the guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to shift the focus to making inner, not outer, changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need truly to accept that both happiness and unhappiness are choices we make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look more closely at these five steps.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/steps-to-happiness.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;steps to happiness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t everyone want to be happy? Yes, and no. On a deep level, of course, everyone wants happiness. Paramhansa Yogananda said, in fact, that this desire is the fundamental motivation of every living thing. But on a conscious level, very few people seek happiness. Rather, they seek those things they think will make them happy: money, possessions, relationships, power, fame, etc. The problem with this way of thinking is that nothing outside ourself can ever make us happy. Only we have that power. Why not, then, seek happiness itself, rather than the will-o’-the-wisps that society dangles before us? Happiness lies within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to look for happiness in the right way. At first, many of the ingredients seem counterintuitive, or even counterproductive: non-attachment; serving others; letting go of instinctive patterns such as judgmental reactions, anger, jealousy, and the like. Finding happiness requires, in fact, that we transcend the very self that is doing the seeking. We need a guide who is more advanced to lead us along the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for self-discipline is obvious, but actually to train our will is not easy. Paramhansa Yogananda said, “True freedom is the ability to do what is good and right.” Swami Kriyananda’s mother once described a self-indulgent relative as having a “whim of steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to change ourself, again, should be obvious, but most people put much more energy into trying to change others or change their environment than into making inner changes. You will begin to improve only after you accept that the improvement you seek starts within. And that there, too, is where it ends. You can exert at most a gentle influence on others. Remember, they have the God-given right to their own free will. Never make your own happiness dependent upon the behavior of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a joy appropriate to every situation, even those we think of as unpleasant or disastrous. If you can once really grasp that happiness is a choice, you will have learned one of the most important lessons of all existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, true happiness is a spiritual quest, and comes from the expansion of consciousness. We must expand heart and mind until we break the chains of ego. These shackles keep us bound, and doom us to the vacillating waves of delusion that keep true happiness forever beyond our reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine happiness,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Celebration of God</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-celebration-of-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-celebration-of-god/</guid>
      <description>A small group of us just returned from a glorious trip to Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore—all places known for their holiness, and filled with events sacred to our line of gurus. Everywhere we saw and experienced the joyful celebration of God in many things that is characteristic of life in India, a celebration not somber and serious, but filled with exuberance.
The evening we arrived in Varanasi, we visited the ashram of Ananda Moyi Ma, the great woman saint about whom Yoganandaji writes in Autobiography of a Yogi.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A small group of us just returned from a glorious trip to Varanasi, Kolkata, and Serampore—all places known for their holiness, and filled with events sacred to our line of gurus. Everywhere we saw and experienced the joyful celebration of God in many things that is characteristic of life in India, a celebration not somber and serious, but filled with exuberance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evening we arrived in Varanasi, we visited the ashram of Ananda Moyi Ma, the great woman saint about whom Yoganandaji writes in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt;. We meditated there on the balcony overlooking the Ganges next to the room where Ma did puja to her beloved image of Krishna, and in her small bedroom. As we sat quietly, a small boy appeared and began doing cartwheels, laughing all the while. How pleased Ma must have been, I thought, to have so much joy expressed before her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early the next morning we visited the home of Lahiri Mahasaya, where he lived, initiated people into Kriya, and left his body. Though the building is locked, there is a large stone bench across the narrow lane on which we sat to meditate. Despite the steady stream of people walking to work, children on their way to school, and noisy motorcycles, we felt a deep inner stillness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, I opened my eyes to see that many of those passing by stopped at Lahiri’s door and touched it to take his blessings. A motorcycle driven by a father with his three children on their way to school also stopped, and each one took blessings. What a wonderful way to start the school day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our time in Kolkata was one long celebration with Yoganandaji and his disciples. Our wonderful center leaders there, Dithi and Alok, along with a team of devotees, have renovated the house of Master’s boyhood friend, Tulsi Bose. It’s quite near to Master’s family home, and it is at the Bose house that Guruji spent most of his days as a teenager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Made holy by visits from great saints like Sri Yukteswar, Ananda Moyi Ma, and Vivekananda, and by the many holy relics from Babaji and our line of gurus, the house is beautifully kept now, with all the relics carefully placed in glass cases. Here we all chanted and meditated with the Kolkata devotees, and felt awash with joy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-celebration-of-god.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a celebration of god&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next we stopped at the Ghosh family home at 4 Gurpar Road, and were lovingly hosted by Master’s great-nephew, Somnath, and his wife Sarita. After meditating in the little attic room where Yoganandaji tells us he “first found God,” we were served a delicious homemade lunch. One of our group said, “It felt like a family reunion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few more days of public events in Kolkata, we took a beautiful boat ride on the Ganges at twilight to Serampore. It is here, on the riverbank, that the banyan tree still stands where Babaji appeared to Sri Yukteswar and where Sri Yukteswar’s ashram is located. As we walked to our hotel, we stopped to pray at the holy tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time of year, it is customary to celebrate Durga Puja, a ten-day holiday in honor of Durga, the goddess of strength, determination, victory, and wisdom. As part of the festival, large images of Durga are fashioned out of clay, beautifully painted and decorated, and then immersed in the Ganges to let her dissolve back into the Infinite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we prayed at the banyan tree, many groups of people carrying their images of Durga released her into the river lovingly, laughingly, joyfully. What a beautiful moment it was!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many blessings have come thus far on our trip, but the main insight I want to share with you is this: The path to God can be a celebration, a joyful release of all that we are into the infinite arms of God. Yes, we need determination to continue, but don’t forget to celebrate God’s presence every step of the way. This is what draws us closer to Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and blessings to you,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Body Touched That Sod</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/my-body-touched-that-sod/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/my-body-touched-that-sod/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I are once again in India after an absence of more than three years. There is a palpable sense of the Divine here, which Paramhansa Yogananda highlighted on March 7, 1952, as he uttered the last words of his incarnation. Swami Kriyananda recounted that momentous event in The New Path:
Master was scheduled to speak after the banquet. His brief talk was so sweet, so almost tender, that I think everyone present felt embraced in the gossamer net of his love.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I are once again in India after an absence of more than three years. There is a palpable sense of the Divine here, which Paramhansa Yogananda highlighted on March 7, 1952, as he uttered the last words of his incarnation. Swami Kriyananda recounted that momentous event in The New Path:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master was scheduled to speak after the banquet. His brief talk was so sweet, so almost tender, that I think everyone present felt embraced in the gossamer net of his love. Warmly he spoke of India and America, and of their respective contributions to world peace and true human progress. He talked of their future cooperation. Finally he read his beautiful poem, “My India.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout his speech I was busy recording his words, keeping my eyes on my notebook. He came to the last lines of the poem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Where Ganges, woods, Himalayan caves, and men dream God.

I am hallowed; my body touched that sod!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sod became a long-drawn-out sigh. Suddenly from all sides of the room there came a loud cry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though we have been here for only a few days, on some subtle plane I, too, feel hallowed that my feet are touching this sacred land. One can feel an elusive holiness in the very air of this land. Swami Kriyananda writes, “God chooses those who choose Him.” Over and again through the long mists of time, great souls who have inhabited India have chosen God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor is it only the great saints who focus their lives around a relationship with the Divine. The head of our charitable work in Brindaban, which takes care of thousands of widow-mothers, told us this story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the care workers came upon an elderly lady who was quite upset, muttering to herself, “He hasn’t eaten for two days, and I’m getting quite hungry. I am going to have to get a stick and beat him until he agrees to eat. I don’t know what to do with that naughty Krishna.” She had made a vow, you see, to feed her beloved Krishna before she would take food herself.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/my-body-touched-that-sod.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;my body touched that sod&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda on the Ganges during his return trip to India in 1935.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master starts his great book, &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt;, with these words, “The characteristic features of Indian culture have long been a search for ultimate verities and the concomitant disciple-guru relationship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, it is September 12th, the anniversary of Swami Kriyananda meeting Yogananda. Swamiji showed us, in the clearest possible way, how to draw God’s grace. As he knelt for the first time at his guru’s feet, he uttered those simple, yet life-changing words that draw God’s love: “I want to be your disciple.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those enchanted words are, of course, only the first step: an affirmation that starts the process of transformation. They must then be reinforced by the discipline of discipleship, by a daily practice of meditation, and by deep self-offering. This, too, Swami Kriyananda modeled for us in every imaginable way. His discipleship to Master became the very core of his self-definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can all choose to do the same. That devotee of Krishna offered her love in the form of physical food. But yogis must offer the ego itself to God. Over time, as we do so, the veils of separation become ever more transparent. Then, our lives, too, become hallowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let It Shine</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-it-shine/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-it-shine/</guid>
      <description>Today is our last day in the Ananda community near Assisi. In a few days we’ll be flying to India to greet friends whom we haven’t seen for three years and to experience the expansion of Ananda’s work there. Our time in Assisi has been filled with blessings as we’ve shared together with our gurubhais the joy of a life in God.
It’s especially heartening to see the dedicated young people and families who are moving here.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Today is our last day in the Ananda community near Assisi. In a few days we’ll be flying to India to greet friends whom we haven’t seen for three years and to experience the expansion of Ananda’s work there. Our time in Assisi has been filled with blessings as we’ve shared together with our gurubhais the joy of a life in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s especially heartening to see the dedicated young people and families who are moving here. There seems to be a new generation of spiritually advanced souls being born who aren’t impressed with the razzle-dazzle of the world, but are seeking higher values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours was telling us about a group of children whose families have recently moved to Assisi and who have asked him to teach them meditation. One twelve-year-old girl told him that she’d been reading Swami Kriyananda’s &lt;em&gt;Art and Science of Raja Yoga&lt;/em&gt;, and had written a school paper on Patanjali’s &lt;em&gt;Yoga Sutras&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m very interested in the yamas and niyamas,” the girl told our friend, “and especially in the principle of non-lying. Before we moved here, when I was with my friends at school, I would pretend to be interested in clothes so that they would accept me. Now I realize after coming to Ananda that I was lying to myself, because that isn’t really who I am.” What a profound insight, something that most people never realize!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hearing this story reminded me of an experience I myself had had shortly after coming to Ananda Village in 1969. In the first days after arriving, I felt a great sense of freedom that I didn’t quite understand. Then one day the words clarified in my mind: “I don’t have to play games anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understood that I could be myself without trying to impress others according to their standards—ones that I didn’t share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a gift of the spiritual path: to discover and accept our own uniqueness, and let it determine the course of our life.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-it-shine.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let it shine&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a gift of the spiritual path: to discover and accept our own uniqueness, and let it determine the course of our life. As the young girl who was exploring non-lying discovered, self-honesty requires courage, but only then are we able to live our life with authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were speaking with another friend at Assisi, and told her about the man at Frankfurt airport that I wrote about in an earlier blog. He had looked very penetratingly at Jyotish and me and said, “You have to accept your own light so that other people have the courage to accept theirs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After hearing this story, Sahaja got a surprised look in her eyes, and got up and left the room. She soon returned holding a small carved wooden angel that she’d had on her altar for many years. It contained an excerpt from the writings of Marianne Williamson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our deepest fear is not that we are inadequate. Our deepest fear is that we are powerful beyond measure. It is our light, not our darkness, that most frightens us. We ask ourselves, “Who am I to be brilliant, gorgeous, talented, fabulous?” Actually, who are you not to be? You are a child of God. Your playing small does not serve the world. There is nothing enlightening about shrinking so that other people won’t feel insecure around you. We are all meant to shine, as children do. We were born to make manifest the glory of God that is within us. It’s not just in some of us; it’s in everyone. &lt;strong&gt;And as we let our own light shine, we unconsciously give other people permission to do the same&lt;/strong&gt;. As we are liberated from our own fear, our presence automatically liberates others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember that it isn’t for our own aggrandizement that we accept the divine light within us. As Christ told his followers: “Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father who is in heaven.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we can stand in humility, bathed in God’s light within and without, then we experience the truth of who we really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing you the joy of Self-discovery,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let God Decide</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-god-decide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-god-decide/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I have been spending a month at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, where there is great reverence for St. Francis. Paramhansa Yogananda, too, honored him, calling him his “patron saint.”
A few years after Ananda’s arrival in Italy, word began to reach Swami Kriyananda, who was residing here at the time, that the Bishop of Assisi had been issuing warnings against us. Apparently, Church authorities had come to consider our presence there a threat.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I have been spending a month at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, where there is great reverence for St. Francis. Paramhansa Yogananda, too, honored him, calling him his “patron saint.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years after Ananda’s arrival in Italy, word began to reach Swami Kriyananda, who was residing here at the time, that the Bishop of Assisi had been issuing warnings against us. Apparently, Church authorities had come to consider our presence there a threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda, being a very forthright person, decided to have a talk with him. In many ways they turned out to be kindred souls: both of them highly intelligent, well educated, and sincere in their spirituality. After spending some time discussing spiritual matters, Swamiji was about to take his leave. As he was at the door the Bishop said, “I enjoyed our time together and really like you. Too bad you aren’t a Christian.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji, knowing that it would be useless to argue, replied with a twinkle in his eye, “You say I am not a Christian, and I say I am. Let’s let Jesus decide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thought, “Let’s let God decide,” should be like a mantra, a compass that guides our life. It is a shorthand way of saying, “Not my will, nor your will, but God’s will.” For devotees of this path, we might translate it as, “What would Master do?” or, “What does my own higher Self advise for me?” How many arguments could be avoided if we let this attitude guide us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda put it this way: “Learning to love our relatives is simply a training in stretching our consciousness. It is a preliminary practice in loving all others as we do our relations, whom we think of as our own. We have to learn to look on family and strangers alike, because all are children of God. He has given you certain family members with whom you are practicing stretching your consciousness. When the husband serves the wife, and she serves him, each with the desire to see the other happy, Christ Consciousness—God’s loving Cosmic Intelligence that permeates every atom of creation—has begun to express itself through their consciousness. Whenever you do something for someone else, without any selfish motive, you have stepped into the sphere of Christ Consciousness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we align our heart and mind with those of the stretched consciousness of a master, we have a polestar to guide us. If we could simply remember to ask the question, “What do you advise?” most problems in life, and especially in relationships, could be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I have recently finished a ten-class course, How to Develop Harmonious Relationships. In it we explore all facets of relationships of every kind: personal and intimate ones as well as others such as friendships and those that are work-related.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-god-decide.png&#34;  alt=&#34;let god decide&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all relationships are expressions of the Christ consciousness, but the more we are caught up in desires, attachments, and ego, the more conflicts arise. Human emotions, especially negative ones, are a labyrinth with no exit. The only real solution is to rise above the limiting walls of ego into the free skies of higher consciousness. How? By remembering to ask God or a master, “What do you advise here?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking is one part of the picture. Listening for His response is the other part. God won’t intrude on our free will, so we must first be truly ready to accept His advice. Then we must allow our minds and emotions to become still. He loves us as His very own, and is waiting for us to turn to Him. When we do, He will answer us with a soft and loving whisper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you are about to argue a point, follow Swami Kriyananda’s model and say, perhaps with a twinkle in your eye, “Let’s let God decide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In His all-embracing love,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Only Knew ...</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-only-knew/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-only-knew/</guid>
      <description>“If you only knew how much God loved you, you would die for joy.” These words from St. Jean Vianney, a French saint of the nineteenth century, have always inspired and motivated me spiritually.
Jyotish and I are visiting Ananda’s community and retreat center outside of Assisi now, and are staying in the lovely guest apartment of two good friends, Shantidev and Radhika. On the wall in one of the rooms is a print of a beautiful Indian painting called, “Enter the Spiritual World.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“If you only knew how much God loved you, you would die for joy.” These words from St. Jean Vianney, a French saint of the nineteenth century, have always inspired and motivated me spiritually.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/if-you-only-knew.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;if you only knew&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Jyotish and I are visiting Ananda’s community and retreat center outside of Assisi now, and are staying in the lovely guest apartment of two good friends, Shantidev and Radhika. On the wall in one of the rooms is a print of a beautiful Indian painting called, “Enter the Spiritual World.” It depicts Krishna tenderly embracing one of his devotees in a pastoral setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked Shantidev what the story was behind the painting, and here is what he recounted. The devotee being embraced is Gopal Kumar, who, in a past incarnation, had been one of the gopis with Krishna in Brindaban. Through subsequent lives of spiritual seeking, Gopal Kumar had become a great yogi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now he had reached the stage where all he wanted was to achieve union with God. In his quest he traveled throughout the three worlds—causal, astral, and physical—to find what he was seeking. Still, his life’s burning goal eluded him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally he arrived in Goloka Brindaban, the dimension where Krishna resides in the spiritual realm. Here, after many incarnations of separation, he beheld Krishna once again. There was an immediate mutual recognition; Krishna enfolded his dear devotee, Gopal Kumar, in a loving embrace. And just then, to everyone’s alarm, Krishna fainted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the devotees gasped, not knowing what had befallen their beloved Lord. They fanned him and rubbed his feet, and eventually Krishna returned to consciousness. He explained that he had been so full of ecstasy and joy to meet Gopal Kumar again after their long separation that he had lost consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a beautiful thought to reflect upon: &lt;em&gt;that God is even more ecstatic than we are when one of His lost children returns home&lt;/em&gt;. Jean Vianney described the transcendent joy that comes to that devotee who knows God’s love, and Krishna shows us the completion of divine union: God’s joy is even greater than our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is life’s tests and challenges that help us to feel God’s love more deeply. Recently while in Assisi, Jyotish and I contracted Covid, which fortunately was a very mild case. Now we are almost totally recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During our illness, we received such an outpouring of love, support, and prayers from friends around the world that we were deeply touched. As we read the many notes, we were moved at how God’s love for us is sometimes expressed outwardly through divine friendship. Often when we need it the most, we get glimpses of how much we are loved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Gopal Kumar, let’s continue on our journey to find Oneness with God. One day, we will know the fullness of His love and merge with it into ecstasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guiding Principles</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/guiding-principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/guiding-principles/</guid>
      <description>Swami Kriyananda gave us two principles which, like moral compass points, guide the Ananda communities. The first is something he saw when visiting the Maharaja of Cooch Behar. The family motto read: Yato dharma, tato jaya. This sloka from the great epic, the Mahabharata, means, “Where there is adherence to righteousness, there is victory.” This ancient “compass point” is the polestar that has allowed India to navigate the turbulent tides of time.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda gave us two principles which, like moral compass points, guide the Ananda communities. The first is something he saw when visiting the Maharaja of Cooch Behar. The family motto read: &lt;em&gt;Yato dharma, tato jaya&lt;/em&gt;. This sloka from the great epic, the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt;, means, “Where there is adherence to righteousness, there is victory.” This ancient “compass point” is the polestar that has allowed India to navigate the turbulent tides of time. If we hold fast to this principle, it will align our actions with the subtle laws of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda’s second principle guides our actions in this world: “People are more important than things.” This helps us get our priorities right, and is especially important for managing groups of people, such as businesses and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, giving classes and satsangs, and meeting with friends. It’s been over three years since we last visited, and the changes here are quite amazing. The community and teaching center are extraordinarily vibrant, with people coming from all over Europe, and many moving here. Perhaps Europe is a little ahead of the curve, seeing more clearly the results of all the disruptions—from both pandemic and warfare—that are happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to do everything we can to avoid having our lives shaken up, but Divine Mother knows what She is doing. Swami Kriyananda saw that as long as the world was stable, it would trudge along in its familiar ruts, complacent and resistant to change. Divine Mother is making the world less safe, shaking us out of our grooves and forcing us to take a deeper look at our priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of days after we arrived, we met with a small group of future leaders. The difficulties of the last few years were a main topic of conversation. Because the leaders here responded to this crisis by strictly adhering to Ananda’s twin principles, everything is flourishing now. Politicians have fanned the flames of separation with fear and anger, but at Ananda, holding fast to dharma and kindness has allowed the troubled waters to bring people together with great purpose, cooperation, and kindness. One person at the satsang used a phrase that I had never heard but will never forget. She called the virus “Saint Covid,” because of all the beneficial changes and spiritual growth that it’s produced.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/guiding-principles.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;guiding principles&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a palpable sense of grace here at Ananda Europa. As &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt; tells us, Jesus appeared to the great master, Babaji, in the Himalayas and asked him to send someone to bring the high teachings of the East, especially meditation, to the West. Paramhansa Yogananda was that chosen ambassador. He, in turn, ignited the heart of Swami Kriyananda, and the result is the worldwide work of Ananda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I walked these hills, I had a deep sense that a circle had been completed. The steps go like this: 1) Jesus asks Babaji to send these ancient teachings to the West. 2) Yogananda fulfills that wish. 3) He blesses Swami Kriyananda as his disciple. 4) Swamiji founds an Ananda community here in Assisi, which is widely considered to be the very heart of Christendom. 5) Now at the Ananda community, Babaji and Jesus sit side by side on the high altar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a lovely sense of completion. The Masters work in very long rhythms to bring about the spiritual evolution of the planet. The current situation is not the disaster that it may appear on the surface to be. It is, rather, one of the steps needed for our awakening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let our hearts be grateful for everything that comes to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In gratitude,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Can See It, You Can Do It</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it/</guid>
      <description>The throngs of excited travelers moved quickly past us as they dragged their luggage and children along in search of their departure gates. We were in the Frankfurt airport with a long layover waiting for our connecting flight to Rome, and then on to Assisi. We would be spending the next month in Assisi, sharing with our Ananda spiritual family as well as with devotees from all over Europe.
While we waited for our flight, we were frantically studying Italian so that we might have some semblance of facility to converse with our friends.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The throngs of excited travelers moved quickly past us as they dragged their luggage and children along in search of their departure gates. We were in the Frankfurt airport with a long layover waiting for our connecting flight to Rome, and then on to Assisi. We would be spending the next month in Assisi, sharing with our Ananda spiritual family as well as with devotees from all over Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we waited for our flight, we were frantically studying Italian so that we might have some semblance of facility to converse with our friends. Intently focused as we were, we were surprised when a man suddenly stood before us. He impressed us with the clear, strong energy which shone in his eyes and in the radiance of his smile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been watching you from across the room,” he said, “and when I saw your beautiful smiles, I just had to come over to talk with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He began asking us about our lives, and strangely it felt like we were old friends, picking up where we had left off at some other time. He was sincerely interested when we told him about Ananda, the path that we follow, and how we came to dedicate our lives to a spiritual search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pierre (our new/old friend) was an American, but he’d been living abroad for the past fifteen years serving as head basketball coach at the Tony Parker Academy, one of the finest athletic academies in Lyon, France. “We coach people from all walks of life—from undefeated pro teams, to high school kids looking for a career in basketball, to people who simply need help and encouragement,” he told us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He listened thoughtfully as we explained how we teach meditation to help people find their own highest potential. Then he looked at us intently, and said, “That’s what I do, too, but in a different way. I’ll tell you a story about how I work with people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the story he shared. Pierre had been working with a group of autistic children, using basketball to help them develop self-confidence. The children loved coming to his class, where they were learning how to overcome fears and limitations. All of them had improved in their skills except for one little girl, who remained withdrawn and unable to shoot a basket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the gymnasium where they practiced, the front row was an impressive stretch of plush, red-velvet seats which were reserved for VIPs. Pierre had been told by his boss not to let the children use these seats, so as to keep them pristine for the “very important people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But seeing how hard the kids had worked and how much they had achieved, he said to them at their last class, “If you can make a basket, then you can sit in one of those red-velvet seats.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No sooner had he said this than he realized he had made a terrible mistake. The withdrawn girl would not be able to make a basket, and she would feel even more alienated from the others. One by one each child went to the free-throw line, and one by one they each made a basket. Bursting with happiness, they took a seat in one of the fancy chairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally it was the turn of the special child. She tried several times and failed. Then Pierre took the ball from her, and said, “Now close your eyes, and see yourself making a basket.” After a short time, he asked her, “Did you make it?” “No,” was her reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Try again,” he encouraged her. “Did you make it now?” Still “no.” After repeating this several more times, she finally was able to say with amazement, “I made it!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only then did Pierre hand her the ball, and for the first time in her young life, the girl made a basket. The whole class cheered jubilantly for her, and she took her place in one of the special seats—truly a VIP.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;if you can see it you can do it&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After sharing this story, Pierre looked at us deeply and said, “Tell the people that you teach that if they can see it, they can do it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, we share Pierre’s love and wisdom with you. No matter how impossible the search for God may seem at times, if you see your soul embraced in His light with enough concentration and aspiration, you will be able to achieve that which you most ardently seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and love from Assisi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Thy Will Be Done</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-thy-will-be-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-thy-will-be-done/</guid>
      <description>A friend of ours told us that she has always believed in and used the power of prayer. Since childhood, however, her prayers have gradually become simpler and more focused. Now she repeats only a single prayer every day and for every situation: “Lord, let Thy will be done.” This was also the final prayer of Jesus just before his crucifixion. One might call it the ultimate prayer of all great souls.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours told us that she has always believed in and used the power of prayer. Since childhood, however, her prayers have gradually become simpler and more focused. Now she repeats only a single prayer every day and for every situation: “Lord, let Thy will be done.” This was also the final prayer of Jesus just before his crucifixion. One might call it the ultimate prayer of all great souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This prayer provides several profound benefits. For one thing, it allows one truly to follow Yogananda’s advice to “remain even-minded and cheerful in all circumstances.” A second, more important benefit is that complete self-offering is the most fertile soil in which deep devotion and faith can grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are caught in the labyrinth of our ego we see only a very distorted reality, filtered through the lens of our moods, desires, and attachments. The distortions of the mind due to the turbulence of the heart are depicted beautifully in a song, “Both Sides Now,” by Joni Mitchell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Rows and floes of angel hair
And ice cream castles in the air
And feather canyons everywhere
I’ve looked at clouds that way

But now they only block the sun
They rain and snow on everyone
So many things I would have done
But clouds got in my way

I’ve looked at clouds from both sides now
From up and down, and still somehow
It’s cloud illusions I recall
I really don’t know clouds at all
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The song goes on to address the themes of love and life in much the same way, with one’s positive and negative moods distorting perception until the inevitable conclusion is: &lt;em&gt;I really don’t know love at all, and I really don’t know life at all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t this everyone’s dilemma—clouds get in our way? A blossoming of love, faith, and clarity is the real benefit of the prayer, &lt;em&gt;Let Thy will be done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-thy-will-be-done.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let thy will be done&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda put it this way: “Faith must be cultivated. It cannot be achieved by mere wishful thinking. If you throw yourself off a mountaintop with the affirmation, ‘God will protect me,’ just see if He does! He expects you to use the common sense He has given you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He will take care of you, surely, if you do your best always, act sensibly, and leave the results in His hands. Faith, however, must be watered by inner experience, like a plant. The more you actually experience the care He takes of you, the more you will come to rely on Him—not fanatically, but naturally, in the divine way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also said, “God doesn’t always answer your prayers in the way that you expect, but, if your faith in Him never wavers, He will grant you far more than you expect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I embark today on our long journey to Italy and India. There are countless unknowns ahead of us, as there are for everyone, every day. Ultimately, anxiety about the future simply takes away our joy. It make a lot more sense to just relax and say lovingly to Divine Mother, “Let Thy will be done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the loving arms of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Changes?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-changes/</guid>
      <description>Our two large suitcases lay partially full on the floor. For the past two weeks, we’d been slowly filling them with clothes and travel items for our trip to Ananda centers in Italy and India. We’ll be gone for three and a half months, so planning what to bring for different climes and times has been a bit challenging.
I could feel that my mind was beginning to churn as I weighed different options for what to bring, and tried to form a mental image of all the places to which we’d be going.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Our two large suitcases lay partially full on the floor. For the past two weeks, we’d been slowly filling them with clothes and travel items for our trip to Ananda centers in Italy and India. We’ll be gone for three and a half months, so planning what to bring for different climes and times has been a bit challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could feel that my mind was beginning to churn as I weighed different options for what to bring, and tried to form a mental image of all the places to which we’d be going. Movement, time, space—it began to seem a bit overwhelming to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I remembered a story about a woman who traveled from England to India to visit a great saint there — Ramana Maharshi. Upon meeting him, she said, “I’ve come all the way from London to see you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You haven’t moved at all,” was his startling reply. “The world around you has moved, but your own center has never changed.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-changes.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what changes&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He was telling her that on the deepest level our consciousness is unmoving and not affected by any outer change. Yoganandaji wrote in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt; that divine sight is center everywhere, circumference nowhere. Every point of the universe can be perceived as the center. You are the center of the universe, and someday you will be able to experience this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda once said, “You don’t really move. Space itself is a delusion. You seem to go from here to your home, to India, to Europe, but the world is really moving around you, as far as the perception of it is concerned. You were never moving, but you put yourself at your periphery, so it seems that you were moving all the time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He went on to say, “The same thing is true for time. You have been living a very long time, and yet you haven’t been living in time at all, except as you have persuaded yourself that it is real. It’s only an illusion in our consciousness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I thought about these vast concepts, my mind began to slow down. I sat to meditate, and realized that soon I would be traveling around the world, but that I would be bringing my Self with me wherever I went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I knew from past experience that the days of our journey would pass quickly. In the blink of an eye, the next thing I would experience would be sitting in our little meditation room once again. Time and space — they really don’t exist as we usually perceive them. We may be dreaming them, but our souls aren’t bound by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji wrote: “God made man immortal. The plan was for him to remain on earth as an immortal. He was to behold the drama of change with a changeless, immortal consciousness and, after seeing the dance of change on the stage of changelessness, he was to return to the bosom of eternal blessedness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silently I offered a prayer of gratitude for the constant guidance of our great teachers, who illumine our lives with their wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have to get back to those suitcases&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Words Can Change Your Life</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/three-words-can-change-your-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/three-words-can-change-your-life/</guid>
      <description>Two travelling monks came upon a stream swollen and roiling due to the recent rains. A woman in distress asked if they could help her. “I must get across the stream to my family,” she said, “but I’m afraid to wade into such turbulent water.”
One of the monks picked her up, carried her safely across to the other side, and set her down. The two companions then continued on their journey.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Two travelling monks came upon a stream swollen and roiling due to the recent rains. A woman in distress asked if they could help her. “I must get across the stream to my family,” she said, “but I’m afraid to wade into such turbulent water.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the monks picked her up, carried her safely across to the other side, and set her down. The two companions then continued on their journey. After several miles the second monk said, “I can’t believe you did that, knowing as you do that it is against the rules of our order to look at a woman, much less touch her.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first monk smiled and replied, “Brother, brother, I set her down on the other side of the stream an hour ago, but you’ve been carrying her for all these miles.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us suffer from the second monk syndrome — we carry a negative mental dialogue about something we should have set down long ago. It might be the memory of some long-ago hurt or a time we felt betrayed. Or it might be something more recent, an argument or a nagging worry. Whatever the root cause of the negative mental loop, it creates unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how can we set it down? Here is a short phrase, a kind of modern mantra, that will help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;let-it-go&#34;&gt;Let it Go.&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/three-words-can-change-your-life.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;three words can change your life&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every time you discover your mind caught in the negative loop, mentally repeat, &lt;strong&gt;“Let it Go, Let it Go.”&lt;/strong&gt; After a time—two weeks according to neuroscientists — you will have created a new neural pathway. Now, when something triggers your negative pattern, you can choose to &lt;strong&gt;Let it Go&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda called these neural pathways “brain grooves.” He explained, “Attention is the needle that forms the grooves of mental good or bad habits. It is by deep attention to an evil experience or a good experience that a bad or good habit is formed in the brain.” At another time he said, “Bad karmic tendencies cannot be overcome by concentrating on them, but by developing their opposite good tendencies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technique, of replacing the negative thoughts with positive ones, works in nearly all circumstances of daily life. For devotees, however, its real power comes in meditation. If you find restless thoughts or worries disrupting your concentration, immediately repeat your modern mantra, &lt;strong&gt;“Let it Go.”&lt;/strong&gt; Do it with power: The deeper your intention, the quicker you will see results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stopping negative patterns is only half the battle—we need also to create a positive flow. For this, a second phrase is helpful. I suggest &lt;strong&gt;“I am Free.”&lt;/strong&gt; We can think of it this way: We can use &lt;strong&gt;Let it Go&lt;/strong&gt; to stop the unwanted train of thought and put our mental gears in neutral. Now we can move forward by repeating, &lt;strong&gt;“I am Free.”&lt;/strong&gt; Let this phrase continue until it fills your thoughts and you feel a deep sense non-attachment spreading in your consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa ends his magnificent poem, &lt;em&gt;“Samadhi,”&lt;/em&gt; with these words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Myself, in everything, enters the Great Myself.
Gone forever, fitful, flickering shadows of mortal memory.
Spotless is my mental sky, below, ahead, and high above.
Eternity and I, one united ray.
A tiny bubble of laughter, I
Am become the Sea of Mirth Itself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;With a bubble of laughter,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts Archive</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/archive/</guid>
      <description>An archive of all posts.</description>
      <content></content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
