<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>prayer on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/prayer/</link>
    <description>Recent content in prayer on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/prayer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Finding Your Dharma</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-your-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-your-dharma/</guid>
      <description>This week we’ve been having a wonderful gathering for Inner Renewal Retreat, whose theme has been “Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation.” The Temple of Light here at Ananda’s Expanding Light Retreat has been packed with several hundred residents and guests; another three thousand five hundred people are enrolled online. (If you’re interested in watching the classes and other events, you can still receive a free link.)
One of the most frequently asked questions on this topic is “How do I know what my dharma is?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This week we’ve been having a wonderful gathering for Inner Renewal Retreat, whose theme has been “Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation.” The Temple of Light here at Ananda’s Expanding Light Retreat has been packed with several hundred residents and guests; another three thousand five hundred people are enrolled online. (If you’re interested in watching the classes and other events, you can still receive a free link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most frequently asked questions on this topic is “How do I know what my dharma is?” Let’s talk about two different aspects of this: the longer rhythms or patterns that govern our lifetime as a whole, and the situations that arise from moment to moment as our life unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While our ultimate destiny is Self-realization, there is also the dharma of any particular life as determined by our past karma. Swami Kriyananda wrote: “The duty [dharma] of every man is that which is particularly his own, ordained for him by karmic bonds he himself has forged, and must untie to release himself from attachment to ego.” Each one of us has a unique journey to soul freedom through the maze of our past karma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once many years ago after a Kriya Initiation, Swamiji shared with a small group an amazing experience he had had during the ceremony. “As each person came up for the blessing,” he told us, “I could feel his unique path to liberation.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/finding-your-dharma.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;finding-your-dharma&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For devotees, the dharmic life pattern is something we should patiently allow to unfold, without forcing the circumstances and without undo anxiety. I had a good friend who was torn over the issue of whether she should marry or become a monastic. After a year of stressing over this, she finally asked Swamiji what he felt her dharma was. His response was: “Your karma could go either way. Let’s see what happens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So she waited. After five years, she had become unattached on a deep level. By that point, she was ready to accept her dharma (whatever it might be), and get on with her life. Again, she asked Swamiji what her dharma was, and this time he answered, “You should marry.” Circumstances were such that she was happily married within a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Master’s disciples said, “Your own will surely come to you. In fact, you cannot avoid it.” Our dharma for a lifetime—especially the outward role we are to play—is most often determined by past karmic forces that we cannot control, and often are not even aware of consciously. But if we give our life to God in discipleship, service, and devotion, and wait patiently for His guidance, the right life path will open before us. The challenge is in following our dharma once it becomes clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For there is the problem of discerning dharmic responses to the myriad of questions that arise in daily life: What, in each case, is the right action to take? The best place to start is to tackle the problems closest at hand using these criteria: 1) address the situation with the best energy you have; 2) do it without attachment to the results; and 3) ask for the inner guidance of the guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master gave us this marvelous prayer: “I will reason, I will will, I will act, but guide Thou my reason, will, and activity to the right path in everything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with the battles you are confident of winning. For example, if you are a lazy person, it would be unwise to decide, “I’m going to run a marathon and will get up every day at 6:00 a.m. to run for an hour.” It would be much better to start with a smaller goal that you can accomplish: “I’m going to walk for thirty minutes three days a week.” Conquer the negative habit of laziness by taking doable steps, and keep building on your strengths, until one day you may run that marathon. This is the way of victory over past karma by practicing right action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna says: “To do one’s own duty even unsuccessfully is better than to do someone else’s successfully.” (3:35) It is important, therefore, if we are to discover and follow our unique path of dharma, that we not be attached to the results of our actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad karma is merely energy that has been misdirected. Through meditation, right action, and divine grace, we can follow our dharma, break the bondage of karma, and achieve freedom in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With enthusiasm and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turn Within</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/turn-within/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/turn-within/</guid>
      <description>The holidays have ended, and with it the flurry of outward activity. Now is a good time to turn within, but first a little humor, a balm for the soul.
A few years ago we read this true story. A grandmother found it increasingly challenging to buy suitable gifts for her grandchildren as they got older. Finally, she decided that it would be best if she just gave them money and allowed them to choose for themselves what they wanted.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The holidays have ended, and with it the flurry of outward activity. Now is a good time to turn within, but first a little humor, a balm for the soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago we read this true story. A grandmother found it increasingly challenging to buy suitable gifts for her grandchildren as they got older. Finally, she decided that it would be best if she just gave them money and allowed them to choose for themselves what they wanted. Accordingly, she wrote out a check for each grandchild along with a card that said, “This year you can get your own gift. Love, Grandma.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine her horror when a month later she found on her desk a neat little stack of unsent checks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether from chagrin, or from opportunity, now is the time to turn within. If we continue to allow our energy and attention to be pulled toward outward distractions, we will lose sight of the deeper purpose of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda wrote in Autobiography of a Yogi, “Man is a soul, and has a body. When he properly places his sense of identity, he leaves behind all compulsive patterns. So long as he remains confused in his ordinary state of spiritual amnesia, he will know the subtle fetters of environmental law.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/turn-within.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;turn-within&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“God is harmony: the devotee who attunes himself will never perform any action amiss. His activities will be correctly and naturally timed to accord with astrological law. After deep prayer and meditation he is in touch with his divine consciousness; there is no greater power than that inward protection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to see ourselves as a soul rather than an ego, we need stillness of both mind and heart. At this time of year even the seasons are cooperating; the trees have withdrawn their sap, the seeds are dormant, the weather is whispering, “Stay inside, be still.” It would be wise to listen to God’s voice as expressed in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bible there appear these wonderful, immortal words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;To everything there is a season, and a time for every purpose under heaven:
A time to be born, and a time to die;
A time to plant, and a time to pluck what is planted;
A time to kill, and a time to heal;
A time to break down, and a time to build up;
A time to weep, and a time to laugh;
A time to mourn, and a time to dance; . . .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;For Devi and me, our last outward engagement will be celebrating Yogananda’s birthday on January 5th and an international event for Master the following day. Then, picture us scurrying home an hour or so later and settling into seclusion for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage everyone reading this to set aside time—be it a day, a week, or longer—and go within. Shift the momentum of your life-force from outward activity to inner realization. Even if a complete break from your normal routine isn’t feasible, you can gain much of the benefit of a seclusion with these three simple steps. Try this for a week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditate longer and deeper than usual.&lt;/strong&gt; The essence of seclusion is turning the mind toward God alone. This can only happen if we reverse the natural flow of our attention and desires from the outer world of matter to the inner one of Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disconnect:&lt;/strong&gt; If possible, go on a one-week fast from all of those devices that connect you to unsettling news. If you can’t manage a complete fast, at least go on a diet and limit your intake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the mind turned toward God:&lt;/strong&gt; When you’re not meditating, let the mind be filled with inward chanting, or a simple mantra. Limit your reading to only a little, and then only spiritually uplifting material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paraphrasing the Bhagavad Gita, “Even a little practice of turning within will free you from dire fears, colossal suffering, and compulsive patterns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards God alone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Shawl of Gold</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-shawl-of-gold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-shawl-of-gold/</guid>
      <description>Many of you reading this blog will have heard Swami Kriyananda’s beautiful song, “The Shawl of Gold.” But few of you will have heard the rest of the story. This is how it was revealed to me in my meditation.
Angelica, for that was the young girl’s name, had been wandering alone and hungry for nearly a week. The old lady who had let her sleep in the storeroom in exchange for her services had died recently, and her ramshackle house had been closed and shuttered.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Many of you reading this blog will have heard Swami Kriyananda’s beautiful song, “The Shawl of Gold.” But few of you will have heard the rest of the story. This is how it was revealed to me in my meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angelica, for that was the young girl’s name, had been wandering alone and hungry for nearly a week. The old lady who had let her sleep in the storeroom in exchange for her services had died recently, and her ramshackle house had been closed and shuttered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This night, Christmas Eve, had surely been the strangest of her young life. The night before, perhaps from hunger or loneliness, she had been disturbed by two odd dreams. In the first, Jesus had appeared and told her that just as he had been rejected three times, so must she. The second dream was sweeter, but so very strange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This evening she had wandered the streets desperate to find some sort of work. The first man she’d asked had not even bothered to glance her way. The second had raised his cane to strike her. Then, as she ran to the church, the third man had shouted at her so angrily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she had stumbled away in terror, she happened upon this poor boy, even younger and more desperate than she, and gave him her shawl. Then, a strange warm breeze had come, and the threadbare shawl had turned to gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as she hugged the poor boy, hoping to give him some comfort, though she had received so little herself in her young life, a beautiful woman stood before them. It was as if she were so filled with light that her body could not contain it and it spilled out all around her. “Come with me, my children. For I, too, know suffering,” the woman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She led them to a house and told them to knock. As the door opened, a woman knelt, with tears and wonder in her eyes, and hugged them to her bosom. “Come in, come in,” she whispered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They gratefully followed her into a warm room. Resting on the fireplace mantle was a statue of the woman who had led them here. Even more amazing, there was a photo of the man with long hair, orange robes, and shining eyes who had come into her second dream.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-shawl-of-gold.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the-shawl-of-gold&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Who is that man?” the girl asked. “He is my Master,” the woman replied. Angelica then told the woman of her dream: “I was alone and scared, in a dark room. Then I saw a circle of light on the floor which began to spread, and that man emerged out of the center of it. He knelt before me and said in the gentlest of voices, ‘If you will open your heart to me, I can then enter and take care of you.’ As the dream began to withdraw, I awoke suddenly with a glowing warmth in my heart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The woman began to weep. “He appeared also to me in my meditation, and told me, ‘I have heard your prayers and known your grief. Tonight, your heart will be healed.’ Then, in a vision, I saw the two of you just as clearly as I see you now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I had no idea what to make of this strange experience, but as I left my meditation, I felt an urge to cook the favorite Christmas feast of my two children who died of the flu last year. I thought it was only to keep my mind and heart occupied, but now I see that it had a much deeper purpose.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, taking each of the children by the hand, she led them to a table filled with foods they had never tasted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let us eat together tonight and, if you will stay, we will eat together every night for as long as we live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Christ’s love,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Pray</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/how-to-pray/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/how-to-pray/</guid>
      <description>Paramhansa Yogananda came to the West with a God-ordained mission: to bring teachings and techniques to help people attain higher consciousness. With wisdom and foresight, Master and the others in our line of gurus saw that a time of global upheaval was coming to the world. Out of compassion, Yoganandaji brought twofold gifts to help us deal with the impending suffering: 1) spiritual tools to achieve God contact, and 2) divine blessings to help us find the courage, faith, and strength to face what lies ahead.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda came to the West with a God-ordained mission: to bring teachings and techniques to help people attain higher consciousness. With wisdom and foresight, Master and the others in our line of gurus saw that a time of global upheaval was coming to the world. Out of compassion, Yoganandaji brought twofold gifts to help us deal with the impending suffering: 1) spiritual tools to achieve God contact, and 2) divine blessings to help us find the courage, faith, and strength to face what lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends, global upheaval is no longer only a vision of the future; it is already upon us. Hatred, violence, destruction, and warfare are rife. What can we do to help bring light into the world and reestablish peace and harmony in human hearts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power of prayer is one of the greatest instruments for positive change. And so I want to share what Yoganandaji taught about making our prayers more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/how-to-pray.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;how-to-pray&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;pray-from-your-heart&#34;&gt;Pray from Your Heart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to speak the inner language of prayer with calm, sincere words that spring from your heart. This is not an emotionally wrought state of mind, but one that has the quiet, open trust of a child lovingly asking his mother for help. This kind of intimate conversation with God unfailingly draws His response. Yogananda said, “When you pray to God, pray from your heart. Heartfelt prayer lends power to your thoughts. It focuses them, and centers them in God. Without sincerity, that focus will be lacking.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pray-with-confidence&#34;&gt;Pray with Confidence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you pray, cast aside doubts and limiting thoughts. Offer your prayers, not with a sense of entitlement, but with quiet confidence and faith that God wants to help you. Yoganandaji told us, “Never pray with the attitude of a beggar. You are God’s child. Pray with utter confidence that He is listening. Utter faith, and love: these are the most important elements in prayer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pray-with-concentration&#34;&gt;Pray with Concentration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before praying, calm the heart and quiet the mind through meditation. Then, when your thoughts are still, concentrate at the spiritual eye and project your prayers with a laser-like focus. Don’t become tense, but with relaxed, one-pointed energy keep holding your prayer up to God. Do it repeatedly, until you begin to feel His presence. Master said, “God answers all prayers, but restless prayers He answers only a little bit. Get control over your mind. When you can pray with concentration, the Lord will know that you mean what you are saying. Then, He will answer you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-peace-and-harmony-prayer&#34;&gt;The Peace and Harmony Prayer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master gave one of his direct disciples the inspiration for a powerful tool for healing conflict: what we’ve come to call “The Peace and Harmony Prayer.” It can be used to heal discord between individuals and between nations. In this context, we encourage you to use it for global healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prayer is quite simple. Visualize the world bathed in light, and for one minute repeat the words: “Lord, fill this world with peace and harmony, peace and harmony.” Then visualize yourself in light, and pray for fifteen seconds: “Lord, fill me with peace and harmony, peace and harmony.” You can use this prayer, or any other that resonates with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friend, we invite you to join in prayer with your brothers and sisters in God throughout the world. With devotion, confidence, and concentration, let’s offer our united prayers for world peace. As Christ says in the Bible, “Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you. . . . And all things, whatsoever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye shall receive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and hope,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Inner Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-inner-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-inner-light/</guid>
      <description>When Swami Kriyananda gave me the spiritual name, Jyotish, he said that it means “Inner Light.” Seeing light in the forehead during meditation has always been a cornerstone of my practice, which is probably why he chose this name for me.
Yogananda explains that one of the hidden teachings of the Bhagavad Gita is that each character, good and bad, symbolizes a different psychological trait within our psyche. Each quality we express in this life has been trained by the same teacher—Dronacharya (past habit).</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;When Swami Kriyananda gave me the spiritual name, Jyotish, he said that it means “Inner Light.” Seeing light in the forehead during meditation has always been a cornerstone of my practice, which is probably why he chose this name for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda explains that one of the hidden teachings of the Bhagavad Gita is that each character, good and bad, symbolizes a different psychological trait within our psyche. Each quality we express in this life has been trained by the same teacher—Dronacharya (past habit). Yogananda says, “No matter how many times a man suffers from very powerful attacks of sense-habits and restlessness-producing material desires, he finds that the meditation-born, occult soldiers of this life and past lives still come to his aid.” One of the greatest generals in the spiritual battle is Dhumata (Calm Inner Light), who arranges our pure discriminative faculties for spiritual battle. Though the Gita appears on its surface to be a mere philosophical discourse, when we meditate we can actually experience the realities it describes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people, even beginners, are able to see some kind of light in the forehead during meditation. This is because light is an innate aspect of our spiritual essence and is reawakened by any spiritual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When his mind becomes very calm and focused, the meditator can see the spiritual eye as a golden ring enclosing a deep-blue field with a silvery-white five-pointed star at its center. Seeing the spiritual eye clearly is challenging, and many people get disheartened if they can’t. Don’t get discouraged. Any perception of the inner light, even as only a kind of ephemeral opalescence, is extremely beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-inner-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the inner light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The inner light can deepen our meditation in many ways. Typically, we begin our meditation by praying to God and our line of gurus. Unfortunately, this is often done absentmindedly. It will be much more effective if you first take a few moments to center yourself and connect to the light and energy in the spiritual eye. Then, as you pray, clearly visualize each of the masters, especially their eyes. It adds even more power if you also feel and direct devotional gratitude to each of them from the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After your prayer, move on to the practice of watching the breath. First, feel the cool and warm currents of the inhalation and exhalation high in the nasal area. As you get calmer and more focused, feel that each breath is awakening and energizing the inner light in your forehead and prefrontal cortex of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the inner light has been awakened, it can become a kind of “home base.” When your mind wanders, bring it back to the inner light. For me, this is the best and fastest cure for restless thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When practicing other techniques, especially Kriya Yoga, use the inner light as a reference point, continually returning to it and strengthening its power. At the end of all techniques, focus there as deeply as possible. The spiritual eye is the gateway through which the deep meditator exits the body and enters Christ consciousness, experiencing his unity with everything in existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner light is useful also throughout the day. Swami Kriyananda advised that when relating to others, especially if giving advice, we should feel love and goodwill arising in the heart and being projected from our forehead to the spiritual eye of the other person. This will connect us soul-to-soul and make possible much deeper communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner light is, indeed, one of our greatest allies in our spiritual journey. In his great book of prayers, Whispers from Eternity, Yogananda wrote the following: “My eyes are enthralled, O Father, with the beauty of earthly flowers, with life’s passing scenes, and with the sailing, silent clouds. Everywhere, all I see hints at Thy hidden presence. Open that eye in me which sees only Thee. With that gaze may I behold Thee above, beneath, all around, within, and outside me. Teach me in all things to see only Thee. Open in me that eye which beholds everywhere Thy hidden but ever subtly reigning wonder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He further suggests, “This demand, especially, should be repeated mentally with deep concentration until the prayer-thought becomes fixed in your superconsciousness by the conviction born of deep faith.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May the inner light guide each of us back to our one true home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Matters in the End</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-matters-in-the-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-matters-in-the-end/</guid>
      <description>A poignant quote from Buddha came to us recently: “In the end only three things matter. How much you loved, how gently you lived, and how gracefully you let go of things not meant for you.”
Often we live locked up in self-focused goals and desires. Yet, as we depart from this incarnation, goals must be relinquished and desires discarded. Those desires we fail to abandon will inevitably pull us back into another incarnation, and another, and another.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A poignant quote from Buddha came to us recently: “In the end only three things matter. How much you loved, how gently you lived, and how gracefully you let go of things not meant for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we live locked up in self-focused goals and desires. Yet, as we depart from this incarnation, goals must be relinquished and desires discarded. Those desires we fail to abandon will inevitably pull us back into another incarnation, and another, and another. The solution is disarmingly simple: Expand our heart’s energy by directing it toward God and the benefit of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda explained that the heart is the center of the primordial feeling element (chitta). He added that we perceive and respond to the world primarily through feeling rather than intellect. Ultimately, to find liberation we must still the mind and, especially, neutralize the whirlpools of likes and dislikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy in the “switching station” of the heart is constantly seeking fulfillment. This quest can lead us toward worldly attachments and sensory experiences, or towards the divine joy of God. When our energy is funneled downward and outward, we set ourselves up for anxiety and disappointment. As Yogananda put it, “Delusion always breaks its promises.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best strategies to channel the energy positively is to think of the welfare of others. When we embarked on Ananda’s work in San Francisco, we started a small restaurant/bookstore. The manager, a single woman, had to close the store late at night and then take a bus through a very run-down area of town. Often sharing the bus with drunks and drug addicts, she dreaded the nightly ride home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As she explained her dilemma to Swami Kriyananda, he first explored the standard solutions: Could she drive home? Could she take a taxi? Could someone else drive her? All of these proved either impractical or too expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami said, “All right, then, I suggest that you do this: When you get on the bus, pick out one person who appears to need help and pray for him the whole way home. If that person gets off, choose another.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later she told Swamiji that the bus ride home had transformed into her favorite part of the day. Her prayers for others had shifted her heart’s energy from isolation and fear to connection and joy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-matters-in-the-end.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what matters in the end&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Love is fundamental, but almost as important is gratitude. By being grateful for the circumstances and people in our lives, we open a positive flow of energy from the heart up to the spiritual eye. It’s virtually impossible to harbor negativity when we’re feeling grateful. We don’t have to express it outwardly—we can just silently allow the feeling of thankfulness to reverberate in the heart. Begin by being grateful for things that are easy to accept. Then train yourself also to feel appreciation for challenging situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda wrote, “Teach me to look upon all that happens in my life with a pleased, interested attitude, that at the end of each episode, no matter how sad or difficult, I may exclaim: “Ah, that was a good show, full of thrills, suspense, and excitement! I am happy to have seen it, and I have learned much from it for my own benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we find it challenging to hold such a high attitude, we can at least strive toward it. Some years ago, while experiencing a difficult period, I wrote an affirmation to help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I am grateful for my life exactly as it is.
I am thankful for this day;
I welcome every hour.
Thank you, God. Thank you, God.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have the potential to expand our heart and let it become a channel for the infinite love of God. If we do our best, we can face our final review and say, “I loved greatly, lived gently, and gracefully let go of those things that kept me from Thee, Lord.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In love and gratitude,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Message in a Strange Encounter</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter/</guid>
      <description>The winter’s night was very cold and windy, and I huddled by the little stove in my camper reading the Bible by the light of a kerosene lamp. In the early years of Ananda our dwellings were simple—without electricity, running water, phones, or any way to communicate with others.
But we were more than happy to live in whatever was available—campers, teepees, old delivery trucks—just to be part of Ananda. Here we could dedicate our lives to God as well as help Swami Kriyananda fulfill Yoganandaji’s dream of world brotherhood colonies.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The winter’s night was very cold and windy, and I huddled by the little stove in my camper reading the Bible by the light of a kerosene lamp. In the early years of Ananda our dwellings were simple—without electricity, running water, phones, or any way to communicate with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we were more than happy to live in whatever was available—campers, teepees, old delivery trucks—just to be part of Ananda. Here we could dedicate our lives to God as well as help Swami Kriyananda fulfill Yoganandaji’s dream of world brotherhood colonies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this particular night as I was reading, I was startled to hear a loud pounding on the door. I cautiously opened it, and there on the cinder block step stood a strange man with a wild look in his eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I need to come in,” he said in a demanding voice. Offering silent prayers to God for protection, I stood aside and let him enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sat down on one of the two benches at my little table. “I’m hungry. What do you have to eat?” he again demanded. (More silent prayers on my part.) I offered him some food which he ate voraciously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m thirsty. What can I drink?”(Still more silent prayers.) I placed some water before him, which he quickly gulped down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeming to relax a bit he said, “I like it here. It’s nice and warm.” After a pause he added, “I have these big sores on my arms.” He rolled up one of his sleeves and showed me open, oozing sores on his arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(“Please God, resolve this quickly,” I fervently prayed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more moments passed. Then he suddenly stood up and said, “Thank you. I have to go now,” and quickly departed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Totally baffled by what had just happened, I sat stunned for a few minutes. Then taking a few deep breaths, I continued reading the Bible. These were the first words that my eyes fell upon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;For I was hungry, and ye gave me meat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink; I was a stranger, and ye took me in;

Naked, and ye clothed me; I was sick, and ye visited me; I was in prison, and ye came unto me.

Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, and fed thee? or thirsty, and gave thee drink? . . .

And the King shall answer and say unto them, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto me.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;“God,” I asked inwardly, “was it really You who came in the form of that desperate man?” I never saw the stranger again. To this day I’ve suspected that the encounter was God’s way of showing me that He Himself receives any act of kindness we express to others.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-message-in-a-strange-encounter.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the message in a strange encounter&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now as we approach the Christmas season, it’s a good opportunity to introspect and cleanse our hearts of any negative emotions we may hold towards others. Throughout December, I’m taking up the personal challenge of holding only positive, loving thoughts towards everyone—be they wise or foolish; well-kempt or disheveled. Remember that love offered to any form of life is love offered to God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Whispers from Eternity, Master writes: “Let every feeling that I have glow with Thy love. Let every act of my will be impregnated with Thy divine vitality. Let every thought, every expression, every ambition be ornamented by Thee.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invite you to join me in this challenge for the rest of 2022: to feel God’s love flowing through you in each moment of the day. This is the greatest gift you can give to the world. And who knows? God may come in hidden form to receive it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your sister in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Thy Will Be Done</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-thy-will-be-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-thy-will-be-done/</guid>
      <description>A friend of ours told us that she has always believed in and used the power of prayer. Since childhood, however, her prayers have gradually become simpler and more focused. Now she repeats only a single prayer every day and for every situation: “Lord, let Thy will be done.” This was also the final prayer of Jesus just before his crucifixion. One might call it the ultimate prayer of all great souls.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours told us that she has always believed in and used the power of prayer. Since childhood, however, her prayers have gradually become simpler and more focused. Now she repeats only a single prayer every day and for every situation: “Lord, let Thy will be done.” This was also the final prayer of Jesus just before his crucifixion. One might call it the ultimate prayer of all great souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This prayer provides several profound benefits. For one thing, it allows one truly to follow Yogananda’s advice to “remain even-minded and cheerful in all circumstances.” A second, more important benefit is that complete self-offering is the most fertile soil in which deep devotion and faith can grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are caught in the labyrinth of our ego we see only a very distorted reality, filtered through the lens of our moods, desires, and attachments. The distortions of the mind due to the turbulence of the heart are depicted beautifully in a song, “Both Sides Now,” by Joni Mitchell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Rows and floes of angel hair
And ice cream castles in the air
And feather canyons everywhere
I’ve looked at clouds that way

But now they only block the sun
They rain and snow on everyone
So many things I would have done
But clouds got in my way

I’ve looked at clouds from both sides now
From up and down, and still somehow
It’s cloud illusions I recall
I really don’t know clouds at all
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The song goes on to address the themes of love and life in much the same way, with one’s positive and negative moods distorting perception until the inevitable conclusion is: &lt;em&gt;I really don’t know love at all, and I really don’t know life at all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t this everyone’s dilemma—clouds get in our way? A blossoming of love, faith, and clarity is the real benefit of the prayer, &lt;em&gt;Let Thy will be done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-thy-will-be-done.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let thy will be done&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda put it this way: “Faith must be cultivated. It cannot be achieved by mere wishful thinking. If you throw yourself off a mountaintop with the affirmation, ‘God will protect me,’ just see if He does! He expects you to use the common sense He has given you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He will take care of you, surely, if you do your best always, act sensibly, and leave the results in His hands. Faith, however, must be watered by inner experience, like a plant. The more you actually experience the care He takes of you, the more you will come to rely on Him—not fanatically, but naturally, in the divine way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also said, “God doesn’t always answer your prayers in the way that you expect, but, if your faith in Him never wavers, He will grant you far more than you expect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I embark today on our long journey to Italy and India. There are countless unknowns ahead of us, as there are for everyone, every day. Ultimately, anxiety about the future simply takes away our joy. It make a lot more sense to just relax and say lovingly to Divine Mother, “Let Thy will be done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the loving arms of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Short Memory</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-short-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-short-memory/</guid>
      <description>“Are you there, God? Are you listening to my prayers? Do you even know what I’m going through?”
I think we all have thoughts like these from time to time—especially when we’re facing challenges in life. To keep our faith strong, it’s important to remember those times—and we’ve all had them—when our prayers have in fact been answered.
Recently a friend told me about a trip she’d taken in which she encountered one hurdle after another.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“Are you there, God? Are you listening to my prayers? Do you even know what I’m going through?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we all have thoughts like these from time to time—especially when we’re facing challenges in life. To keep our faith strong, it’s important to remember those times—and we’ve all had them—when our prayers have in fact been answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend told me about a trip she’d taken in which she encountered one hurdle after another. The final blow came when she was driving home alone at night from the airport and realized she had a flat tire. Not knowing what to do, she was about to panic when a friend “coincidentally” drove by. He stopped his car and helped her change the tire; soon she was on her way home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her story reminded me of an incident in my own life that happened about fifteen years ago—one that I’d forgotten. A friend of mine had been diagnosed with widespread cancer. To slow the disease’s advance, she began receiving intravenous chemotherapy. A group of her friends would take turns driving her to the chemo sessions, and would sit with her throughout the day until she was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marilyn (this was her name) was a quiet, gentle soul who was a devoted follower of Yoganandaji. She never complained about her diagnosis, the treatments, the changes they wrought on her body, nor the upheaval the disease caused in her life. She passed away peacefully about a year after this story took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that particular day, Marilyn had finished her latest chemotherapy session, and I was driving her back to Ananda Village. It was late afternoon; exhausted from the treatment, Marilyn reclined in the passenger seat and drifted off to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were a few miles away from Ananda on a rural road, when suddenly I heard the dreaded “thump, thump, thump,” and knew we had a flat tire. I pulled over to the side of the road, and not knowing how to change a tire nor seeing anyone around, inwardly I offered a desperate prayer for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just at that moment, an old, beat-up pickup truck pulled over in front of us. Two disreputable-looking characters with long, greasy hair and dirty clothes came over to the car. Since I didn’t know what to expect, I cautiously rolled my window down a crack. To my great relief one of them said, “Looks like you ladies can use a little help.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order, they changed the tire and were on their way. I was sitting in stunned silence, when Marilyn opened her eyes and quietly asked, “What happened?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think God just heard my prayer,” was my quiet reply.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-short-memory.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a short memory&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Left to right) Jitendra Mazumdar, companion on the “penniless test” at Brindaban; Lalita-da, Master’s cousin; Swami Kebalananda, Master’s saintly Sanskrit tutor; and Master, as a high school youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most beautiful and powerful chapters in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt; is “Two Penniless Boys in Brindaban,” in which Yoganandaji’s eldest brother, Ananta, challenges him to put his faith in God to a test. Ananta proposes that young Yoganandaji travel to the nearby city of Agra with a friend, Jitendra, but with no money and no return ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complete the test, they must not beg, reveal their predicament to anyone, nor miss any meals. Further, the boys must see the sights of Agra and return home by train before midnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps feeling some remorse for sending two young boys on such a journey, the skeptical Ananta added: “If by any chance or grace you pass successfully through the Brindaban ordeal, I shall ask you to initiate me as your disciple.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are familiar with the rest of the story. While still on the train to Brindaban, they were approached by two strangers who invited them to lunch at their ashram. The meal turned out to be a sumptuous repast prepared for two princes, patrons of the ashram who at the last minute were unable to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they were leaving the ashram, replete from their elaborate banquet, Jitendra complained, “A fine mess you have got me into! Our luncheon was only accidental good fortune! How can we see the sights of this city, without a single pice between us? And how on earth are you going to take me back to Ananta’s?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda’s reply was one we all need to remember: “You forget God quickly, now that your stomach is filled.” His account continues, “My words, not bitter, were accusatory. &lt;strong&gt;How short is human memory for divine favors! No man lives who has not seen certain of his prayers granted.&lt;/strong&gt;” (If you haven’t read the Autobiography, I’ll let you discover for yourself how the story ends.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, how short our memory is for the graces we have received. As you finish reading these words, I suggest that you take a moment to recall an instance in your own life of an answered prayer, or a feeling of certainty of God’s love for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great saints tell us that God’s blessings, guidance, and protection are always with us. It is we who too often forget them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking always to remember,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
