<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>saint on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/saint/</link>
    <description>Recent content in saint on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/saint/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bring Me a Mustard Seed</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/bring-me-a-mustard-seed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/bring-me-a-mustard-seed/</guid>
      <description>The woman sobbed inconsolably as she pressed the body of her dead child to her bosom. A sympathetic neighbor, on seeing her so overwhelmed with grief, said, “A saint has come to visit our village. Perhaps he can perform a miracle and bring your child back to life.”
Gathering the body of her child in her arms, the woman rushed to the feet of Buddha, for it was indeed he to whom the neighbor had been referring.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The woman sobbed inconsolably as she pressed the body of her dead child to her bosom. A sympathetic neighbor, on seeing her so overwhelmed with grief, said, “A saint has come to visit our village. Perhaps he can perform a miracle and bring your child back to life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gathering the body of her child in her arms, the woman rushed to the feet of Buddha, for it was indeed he to whom the neighbor had been referring. “Sir,” she sobbed, holding up the lifeless little form, “Can you bring my child back to life?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a heart filled with compassion and wisdom, Buddha replied, “My daughter, first bring me a mustard seed from a home that has not known death and suffering.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desperately she went from house to house, but alas at each one she heard a similar story: “We have lost our beloved father.” “Our dear son passed away last month.” “Since our mother who cared for us died there is no one to look after us.” On and on she went throughout the village, even to the huts in the outlying areas, but nowhere could she find anyone who had not known death and loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, exhausted, she returned to Buddha with no mustard seed. Touching his feet, she said, “Lord, now I have understood. Death and suffering visit us all.” Buddha then blessed her, her grief lifted, and her heart was comforted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saints of all religions teach that everything in life is transitory. All human suffering is caused by seeking permanence in an impermanent world. Only through inner detachment can we find lasting peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Globally, we now find ourselves in a world filled with suffering, as environmental, social, financial, and political tensions move us toward an uncertain future. How can we find comfort in such times?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jyotish and I are now in Pune, India, where last weekend the Ananda Center here hosted an inspiring and powerful daylong spiritual fair attended by many hundreds of people. The keynote talk we’d been asked to give was entitled, “Stand Unshaken: How to Face Change with Courage.” Here are four points that we shared to help people deal with uncertainty, change, and loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, when difficulties come, don’t ask self-pityingly, “Why me?” Ask rather, &lt;strong&gt;“What am I supposed to learn from this?”&lt;/strong&gt; All of life’s experiences, whether individually or societally, are given to us to expand our awareness. If we can depersonalize our suffering, and try to see the bigger picture, everything becomes a source of greater understanding and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, when going through challenges, try to find ways to be of service to others. We have a devotee friend in India who lost his teenaged son to leukemia; two weeks later his father passed away from Covid. What was his response to such grief? He called his nearby Ananda Center and asked, “What can I do to help others?” He became a part of our twenty-four-hour hotline to bring comfort to those experiencing grief and fear during the pandemic. Through his service, he found acceptance of his own loss.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/bring-me-a-mustard-seed.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;bring me a mustard seed&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, of great importance: practice meditation. Through this discipline we can develop inner detachment that will enable us to weather any outer storm. Peace of mind, awareness of a reality greater than our own ego, inner strength: all these and more are the fruits of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, deepen your devotion and your faith in God. The plan for this world is rooted in God’s love for us all. Whatever challenges come your way, try to remember that God, with infinite love and patience, is bringing every one of us the experiences we need to find soul freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a letter that Paramhansa Yogananda wrote to one of his disciples, Kamala Silva, he says, “No matter what dark territories you have to pass through, look steadily at the Polestar of his Presence. He knows you are trying to reach Him, only keep trying. Once you convince Him, you will be there. The way is long, let’s hurry to His place. With unceasing blessings, Swami Yogananda.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the grieving mother, we can find no place in this world that is without sorrow and suffering. And so, “Let us hurry to His place.” It is only there that we will find true peace and joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Saint and the Scorpion</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-saint-and-the-scorpion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-saint-and-the-scorpion/</guid>
      <description>There is a story about a saint who was peacefully meditating under a tree along the banks of the Ganges. At a certain point he heard a rustling overhead and opened his eyes to see a large scorpion moving along a branch overhanging the river.
When the creature reached the end of the branch, it fell into the water below. Filled with compassion, the saint waded into the river to rescue it.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;There is a story about a saint who was peacefully meditating under a tree along the banks of the Ganges. At a certain point he heard a rustling overhead and opened his eyes to see a large scorpion moving along a branch overhanging the river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the creature reached the end of the branch, it fell into the water below. Filled with compassion, the saint waded into the river to rescue it. Cupping his hands together, he lifted the drowning scorpion and placed him gently on the river’s bank. In return for his kindness, the scorpion stung him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unperturbed, the saint then returned to the peace of his meditation. Again he heard a rustling overhead, again the scorpion plunged into the water, and again the saint rescued him, only to be stung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this happened a third time, a passerby who had been observing the drama could no longer contain himself. Approaching the saint, he asked, “Sir, why do you continue to rescue the scorpion, when each time he stings you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well,” the saint replied, his eyes luminous with divine love, “you see, it is the nature of the scorpion to sting. He cannot help himself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That may be so, reverend sir, but knowing this, why do you continue to rescue him?” the passerby asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You see, my child, I too cannot help myself. It is my nature to help him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story provides us with a valuable lesson in how to live. Each of us encounters “human scorpions” filled with venom and spite whose sting can cause us suffering. But whether insect or human being, such creatures are driven by instinct or the compulsions of past karma, and have no choice but to sting whenever they feel threatened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saint, by choosing to attune his consciousness to God’s love, had the freedom to express that love under all circumstances. Like the saint, we, too, can choose to align our actions with divine love and peace, no matter what is happening around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first this choice requires an act of will, as the ego tries to protect itself. With repeated effort and determination, however, the choice becomes “second nature.” Unlike the scorpion driven by instinct, we find that the higher path, illumined by a constant flow of divine grace, opens clearly before us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, all decisions in life then become very simple. As a great saint once said, “We have but one decision to make in life: whether to think of God or not.” All the rest are details.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-saint-and-the-scorpion.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the saint and the scorpion&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Uniting our efforts, we can create a great realm of light that can guide the world forward into a new era of peace and harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently we are enjoying the inspiration of our annual Spiritual Renewal Week at Ananda Village. Friends from all over the world have joined us in a wonderful celebration of Master’s blessings and teachings. The theme for the week is “Uplift Yourself—Uplift the World,” exploring how raising our own consciousness improves not only ourselves but the world around us as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the saint, we can choose to express divine love and forgiveness no matter how the world behaves. Then we build an inner fortress of higher consciousness which is impenetrable to the forces of darkness. Uniting our efforts, we can create a great realm of light that can guide the world forward into a new era of peace and harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and blessings in God and Guru,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
