<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pray on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/pray/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pray on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/pray/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Nail in the Board</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-nail-in-the-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-nail-in-the-board/</guid>
      <description>All of us have habits or tendencies that bring us suffering. Though repeatedly we may try to change these patterns, they follow us around like a cloud of gnats. This is the result of the law of karma: Every action we take is a cause that has an effect, an effect that sometimes follows us even from lifetime to lifetime. These effects can be good or bad, freeing or binding, depending on the action involved.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;All of us have habits or tendencies that bring us suffering. Though repeatedly we may try to change these patterns, they follow us around like a cloud of gnats. This is the result of the law of karma: Every action we take is a cause that has an effect, an effect that sometimes follows us even from lifetime to lifetime. These effects can be good or bad, freeing or binding, depending on the action involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When confronted with the effects of our past bad actions, how should we respond? It is natural, and good, to do what we can to minimize those effects. If we have poor health, we can take steps to improve it such as seeing a doctor, taking medication, improving our diet, or exercising appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In themselves, however, steps like these will not eliminate the underlying cause. To do that, as anyone aspiring to soul freedom must, we need to use the power of our mind to resist old patterns. At the same time, we should seek to replace bad habits with good ones. It’s like putting up a protective cloth over our mental garden so that the seeds of bad karma cannot germinate. Past karma then has much less power to harm us. Moreover, those karmic seeds, starved of nourishment from repetition of past bad actions, wither and die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most effective of all is to meditate. Each time we meditate deeply, beneficial changes take place in the patterns of our brain. Here is a meditation technique that Paramhansa Yoganandaji gives us to destroy the seeds of past karma.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-nail-in-the-board.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the-nail-in-the-board&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, meditate upon the thought “I and my Father are one,” trying as you do so to feel great peace and joy in your heart. When joy comes, mentally affirm: “Father, Thou art with me. I command Thy power within me to cauterize my brain cells of wrong habits and past seed tendencies.” Finally, affirm and pray: “I command my brain cells to change, to destroy the grooves of bad habits that have made a puppet out of me. Lord, burn them up in Thy divine light.” Do this technique repeatedly with great concentration, and over time you will feel ever freer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda gave us an image that is very helpful in destroying the effects of our past actions. He said rooting out old karma is like trying to pull a nail out of a board. Using the prongs of a hammer, we keep pulling, but cannot know how much of the nail remains in the board. We do not know when, but one day, after continued effort, the nail pops out. The karma is over, and we are free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours recently told us an illustrative story. He was directing a team of people on a new project. Unfortunately, one person on the team was resistant to our friend’s guidance; he was openly critical and challenging, even hostile. Our friend reacted negatively, and though he didn’t show it, was resentful. Some old karma had come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praying deeply to God to be able to lead the team impartially and effectively, our friend was preparing to meet with the team. Just as he was getting in the car, he felt the karma lift: “like a nail coming out of a board,” he said. He felt inwardly free, and the project moved forward harmoniously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda wrote, “Don’t blame God or anyone else if you are suffering from disease, financial problems, or emotional upsets. You created the cause of the problem in the past and must make a greater determination to uproot it now.” So let’s face the self-created challenges that come to us in life, until, with indomitable will, we realize that nothing can keep us bound in our journey towards soul freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>During the Day</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/during-the-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/during-the-day/</guid>
      <description>We are often asked, “How can I keep the peace and joy I feel in meditation during the demands and distractions of daily activity?” This is, in fact, one of life’s ever-present tests. Another way of phrasing this question is, “How can I keep my energy flowing in a positive direction, in tune with my higher aspirations, so that the world does not pull me down?”
Here are some solutions to this great challenge:</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We are often asked, “How can I keep the peace and joy I feel in meditation during the demands and distractions of daily activity?” This is, in fact, one of life’s ever-present tests. Another way of phrasing this question is, “How can I keep my energy flowing in a positive direction, in tune with my higher aspirations, so that the world does not pull me down?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some solutions to this great challenge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;during-activity&#34;&gt;During Activity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we must act, let us do our best to act properly. What constitutes proper action? We can learn much from the example of great teachers such as Patanjali, Jesus, and Buddha. Indeed, the essence of all spiritual teaching is that we should act in attunement with God or His saints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are unsure about a contemplated course of action, just ask, “Will this move me toward God or away from Him (or Her)?” The mere act of asking that question is half the battle. If we but ask, we will often feel an inward guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for when we are busily engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pray to God during the day:&lt;/strong&gt; before meals, before work, before interacting with others. It only takes a moment, and will keep the spotlight of your mind turned toward your higher Self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Control what you can:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure that the music you listen to is uplifting. A market owner was plagued by rough characters hanging around in his parking lot. His solution was brilliant. He played classical music through loudspeakers; they couldn’t stand the uplifting vibrations, and left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The same is true for the rough characters that inhabit the darker recesses of our mind. Drive them away with good vibrations.&lt;/strong&gt; Keep your environment clean and colors pure. With the movies you watch or books you read, imagine that God is sitting beside you, because He is. Choose your companions wisely; good company is vital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the breath to calm the mind.&lt;/strong&gt; Before or during tense situations, keep your posture erect and take a few deep, slow breaths. It will both center your mind and give you space to act rather than react.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;during-idle-moments&#34;&gt;During Idle Moments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have many times during the day when we are not engaged: between tasks, waiting in line, riding in a car. These are precious moments. The goal at these times is to practice the presence of God, conversing with Him as you would with a close friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some specific suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chant inwardly or repeat a mantra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the breath—you can even practice Hong-Sau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pray for those around you, or give them a smile and some positive energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remind yourself that everyone and everything you are seeing is God alone. As you gaze about, repeat to yourself, “I see only Thee, Lord.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most important of all, remember to relax and enjoy the day. Life is a long and winding road, and if we don’t enjoy the ride we will end up grim and bitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/during-the-day.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;during the day&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;when-youre-able-to-withdraw&#34;&gt;When You’re Able to Withdraw&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are times during the day when we are able to be completely still. The goal during these times is to retract the life force, bringing it inward and upward. We recently read this very powerful practice recommended by Yogananda: “The great work now before you is to practice going up and down the spine, chanting Aum at each center. In that way you will gain more than by reading all the books—practice going up and down the spine and get acquainted with those currents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often during the day you cannot control what is happening around you, but you can always control yourself. It is not difficult to practice any of these suggestions. The great challenge is to remember to do so during a busy day. If you forget, don’t despair. To paraphrase Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, “Even a little practice of the remembrance of the Divine will save us from dire fears and colossal suffering.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
