<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wisdom on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/wisdom/</link>
    <description>Recent content in wisdom on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/wisdom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Curious Tail</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-curious-tail/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-curious-tail/</guid>
      <description>As I walked along a forest path at Ananda’s Meditation Retreat one morning, I observed an unusual drama unfold before me. Crouched a few yards ahead was Lottie, a fluffy little gray cat who kept the Retreat’s kitchen free from mice. Her gaze was concentrated on something in front of her, and by her intense crouching pose, I could tell she was about to pounce on it.
But moments before she sprang, I saw something shoot off nearly ten yards ahead and lie wriggling in the path.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;As I walked along a forest path at Ananda’s Meditation Retreat one morning, I observed an unusual drama unfold before me. Crouched a few yards ahead was Lottie, a fluffy little gray cat who kept the Retreat’s kitchen free from mice. Her gaze was concentrated on something in front of her, and by her intense crouching pose, I could tell she was about to pounce on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But moments before she sprang, I saw something shoot off nearly ten yards ahead and lie wriggling in the path. Quietly drawing closer to find out what was happening, I saw that Lottie now held in her jaws the small, limp body of a lizard: a brown skink. These lizards have a remarkable ability to project their tail when attacked. Sure enough, the detached tail was what I’d seen thrashing around farther down the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confused by the movement, Lottie dropped the skink, which began creeping into the underbrush, and ran after the tail. After holding the bony appendage in her mouth for a few moments, the cat realized that she’d been tricked, and ran back to catch the lizard, which was still in sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much to my amazement, this spectacle repeated itself: the detached tail, still thrashing around, caused Lottie to drop the lizard once again and run after it. The second time, however, the little lizard was quicker and escaped to freedom, leaving Lottie with only a bony snack for all her efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching this singular drama play out before me, my mind was in a whirl. I continued on my way to the Retreat’s dining room for breakfast, and shared the story there with my friend Seva. “Surely there’s some spiritual lesson in this,” I said to her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without missing a beat, Seva replied with one word: “Detachment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As amusing as this story is, there is in fact a deep message in it for all of us. Non-attachment is one of the fundamental attitudes on the spiritual path. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are firmly held in the jaws of suffering, it’s important to cut loose that which is holding us back: that unfulfilled desire, or unattainable possession, or unsatisfied expectation of how others should treat us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also should seek inwardly to release things of a positive nature to which we’re attached—our possessions, our friends, our children, our spouse. This doesn’t mean that we reject them or give them the cold shoulder; rather, we should try to see them not as ours, but as gifts on loan to us from God. Then everything in life becomes much sweeter, as we begin to perceive God’s presence behind everything.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-curious-tail.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a curious tail&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;how to be nonattachedIs this easy? Of course not, but it is effective. Every time we inwardly detach from something troubling us or to which we’re clinging, we gain control over our happiness and our lives. In his book Affirmations for Self-Healing, Swami Kriyananda wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Nothing is ours. No one belongs to us. Mentally, we should make a bonfire of our love for God, and cast into it all attachments, all desires, all hopes and disappointments.

It helps mentally to examine one’s heart every evening, and liberate it anew of all desires. Pluck out from your heart any burrs of new attachments that you find clinging there. Cast them joyfully into the fire of devotion.

Pray to God energetically, “I destroy all my attachments. They are no longer mine, Lord. I am free in Thee!”
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here Swamiji offers us practical tools to aid in this process of detachment. Ultimately the choice is very simple: cling to your old attachments or find freedom in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, brown skink lizards do grow back a new tail. But for us, may our tale end when we replace all of our attachments with the one attachment to God alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards inner freedom,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behind the Stern Facade</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/behind-the-stern-facade/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/behind-the-stern-facade/</guid>
      <description>We recently heard a remarkable story about Sri Yukteswar. Many devotees have a little difficulty relating to him, since he seems a bit forbidding. Perhaps it is because in Autobiography of a Yogi, Paramhansa Yogananda writes about him in his role as both teacher and disciplinarian, a job he took very seriously, especially knowing that he was preparing Master for a world-changing role.
But the grandson of Tulsi Bose, Master’s close friend, told us that when Sri Yukteswar visited their home he was completely different.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We recently heard a remarkable story about Sri Yukteswar. Many devotees have a little difficulty relating to him, since he seems a bit forbidding. Perhaps it is because in Autobiography of a Yogi, Paramhansa Yogananda writes about him in his role as both teacher and disciplinarian, a job he took very seriously, especially knowing that he was preparing Master for a world-changing role.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/behind-the-stern-facade.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;behind the stern facade&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But the grandson of Tulsi Bose, Master’s close friend, told us that when Sri Yukteswar visited their home he was completely different. He was a kind, lovable, grandfatherly figure who usually had sweets to offer to the many children who gathered around him. I, myself, had an experience where I felt his sweetness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were about to begin a Kriya Initiation in Chennai, India, and the pictures on the altar were all garlanded. As I was bowing to each of our Masters, I mentally prayed to Sri Yukteswar to help me relate to him more deeply. The instant the prayer formed in my mind, the garland around his photo fell off, and I was given the opportunity to lovingly re-garland him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is the remarkable story related to us by Nayaswami Aditya, our center leader in Pune:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bhuvan Pal Singh joined the online classes in Pune during the first wave of Covid and became a Kriyaban. I immediately recognized him as someone who felt like an old friend. He was sincere, with deep yearning and humility, and asked many questions to refine his spiritual practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bhuvan’s lifelong yearning had been to leave everything and go to the Himalayas, but he found himself supporting his entire extended family of thirty-five people, something he did quite happily and very well. During the first wave of the pandemic he took retirement from his successful corporate career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Bhuvan began his Kriya practice, he was diagnosed with a rare malignant cancer of the muscles of his right forearm. Expert advice from the best doctors in the country informed him that little could be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With tears in his eyes Bhuvan related this story: “One day I was undergoing a PET scan to assess the spread of the tumor in my body and found myself alone in a hospital room. As I sat there I prayed to the Masters, “I am feeling very alone.” I instantly had a vision of the form of Sri Yukteswarji in front of me. As his life-size form slowly moved towards me, it shrunk in size until he became very small and entered into my body through my spiritual eye. From within I heard Swami Sri Yukteswarji say, ‘Bhuvan, don’t feel alone or afraid, for I am in every cell of your body.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bhuvanji continued his daily Kriya practice, and although he followed the suggested treatments, his health deteriorated over the months and on 26 January 2022 he left his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days later, his wife, Anupama, had the following experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was awakened early one morning by the sound of the main door of our house being unfastened. As I opened my eyes, I saw a bright yellow light falling on the door, and curious to see what this light was, I moved towards it. Just then I heard and saw my husband, in physical form, seated in the living room in meditative pose, his gaze uplifted. He said to me, ‘Anupama, don’t move. I’m exiting now.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I stood still, and watched my husband exit into that light. A couple of hours after this experience I got a call from my niece in New Delhi. She told me that the previous night she had dreamt that she saw a bright yellow light fall on our house, especially on the main door. In the dream she saw her uncle Bhuvan enter that light.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anupama has kindly given Nayaswami Aditya permission, and we thank her for allowing us to share this sacred experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Swamiji’s passing Devi and I had a “Nadi” reading from an ancient book of prophecy. During that reading we were told that Yogananda was watching out for us minute by minute and second by second. This applies to all of us who have opened our hearts to this great line of masters. Yoganandaji, as Swami Kriyananda explained, was a Blissavatar (incarnation of divine joy). Yoganandaji described Sri Yukteswar as a gyanavatar (incarnation of wisdom). In fact, in God’s light all His qualities merge into one, and in our hour of need we, too, will find that God’s light is in every cell of our body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bring Me a Mustard Seed</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/bring-me-a-mustard-seed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/bring-me-a-mustard-seed/</guid>
      <description>The woman sobbed inconsolably as she pressed the body of her dead child to her bosom. A sympathetic neighbor, on seeing her so overwhelmed with grief, said, “A saint has come to visit our village. Perhaps he can perform a miracle and bring your child back to life.”
Gathering the body of her child in her arms, the woman rushed to the feet of Buddha, for it was indeed he to whom the neighbor had been referring.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The woman sobbed inconsolably as she pressed the body of her dead child to her bosom. A sympathetic neighbor, on seeing her so overwhelmed with grief, said, “A saint has come to visit our village. Perhaps he can perform a miracle and bring your child back to life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gathering the body of her child in her arms, the woman rushed to the feet of Buddha, for it was indeed he to whom the neighbor had been referring. “Sir,” she sobbed, holding up the lifeless little form, “Can you bring my child back to life?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a heart filled with compassion and wisdom, Buddha replied, “My daughter, first bring me a mustard seed from a home that has not known death and suffering.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desperately she went from house to house, but alas at each one she heard a similar story: “We have lost our beloved father.” “Our dear son passed away last month.” “Since our mother who cared for us died there is no one to look after us.” On and on she went throughout the village, even to the huts in the outlying areas, but nowhere could she find anyone who had not known death and loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, exhausted, she returned to Buddha with no mustard seed. Touching his feet, she said, “Lord, now I have understood. Death and suffering visit us all.” Buddha then blessed her, her grief lifted, and her heart was comforted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saints of all religions teach that everything in life is transitory. All human suffering is caused by seeking permanence in an impermanent world. Only through inner detachment can we find lasting peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Globally, we now find ourselves in a world filled with suffering, as environmental, social, financial, and political tensions move us toward an uncertain future. How can we find comfort in such times?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jyotish and I are now in Pune, India, where last weekend the Ananda Center here hosted an inspiring and powerful daylong spiritual fair attended by many hundreds of people. The keynote talk we’d been asked to give was entitled, “Stand Unshaken: How to Face Change with Courage.” Here are four points that we shared to help people deal with uncertainty, change, and loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, when difficulties come, don’t ask self-pityingly, “Why me?” Ask rather, &lt;strong&gt;“What am I supposed to learn from this?”&lt;/strong&gt; All of life’s experiences, whether individually or societally, are given to us to expand our awareness. If we can depersonalize our suffering, and try to see the bigger picture, everything becomes a source of greater understanding and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, when going through challenges, try to find ways to be of service to others. We have a devotee friend in India who lost his teenaged son to leukemia; two weeks later his father passed away from Covid. What was his response to such grief? He called his nearby Ananda Center and asked, “What can I do to help others?” He became a part of our twenty-four-hour hotline to bring comfort to those experiencing grief and fear during the pandemic. Through his service, he found acceptance of his own loss.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/bring-me-a-mustard-seed.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;bring me a mustard seed&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, of great importance: practice meditation. Through this discipline we can develop inner detachment that will enable us to weather any outer storm. Peace of mind, awareness of a reality greater than our own ego, inner strength: all these and more are the fruits of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, deepen your devotion and your faith in God. The plan for this world is rooted in God’s love for us all. Whatever challenges come your way, try to remember that God, with infinite love and patience, is bringing every one of us the experiences we need to find soul freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a letter that Paramhansa Yogananda wrote to one of his disciples, Kamala Silva, he says, “No matter what dark territories you have to pass through, look steadily at the Polestar of his Presence. He knows you are trying to reach Him, only keep trying. Once you convince Him, you will be there. The way is long, let’s hurry to His place. With unceasing blessings, Swami Yogananda.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the grieving mother, we can find no place in this world that is without sorrow and suffering. And so, “Let us hurry to His place.” It is only there that we will find true peace and joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Can See It, You Can Do It</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it/</guid>
      <description>The throngs of excited travelers moved quickly past us as they dragged their luggage and children along in search of their departure gates. We were in the Frankfurt airport with a long layover waiting for our connecting flight to Rome, and then on to Assisi. We would be spending the next month in Assisi, sharing with our Ananda spiritual family as well as with devotees from all over Europe.
While we waited for our flight, we were frantically studying Italian so that we might have some semblance of facility to converse with our friends.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The throngs of excited travelers moved quickly past us as they dragged their luggage and children along in search of their departure gates. We were in the Frankfurt airport with a long layover waiting for our connecting flight to Rome, and then on to Assisi. We would be spending the next month in Assisi, sharing with our Ananda spiritual family as well as with devotees from all over Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we waited for our flight, we were frantically studying Italian so that we might have some semblance of facility to converse with our friends. Intently focused as we were, we were surprised when a man suddenly stood before us. He impressed us with the clear, strong energy which shone in his eyes and in the radiance of his smile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been watching you from across the room,” he said, “and when I saw your beautiful smiles, I just had to come over to talk with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He began asking us about our lives, and strangely it felt like we were old friends, picking up where we had left off at some other time. He was sincerely interested when we told him about Ananda, the path that we follow, and how we came to dedicate our lives to a spiritual search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pierre (our new/old friend) was an American, but he’d been living abroad for the past fifteen years serving as head basketball coach at the Tony Parker Academy, one of the finest athletic academies in Lyon, France. “We coach people from all walks of life—from undefeated pro teams, to high school kids looking for a career in basketball, to people who simply need help and encouragement,” he told us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He listened thoughtfully as we explained how we teach meditation to help people find their own highest potential. Then he looked at us intently, and said, “That’s what I do, too, but in a different way. I’ll tell you a story about how I work with people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the story he shared. Pierre had been working with a group of autistic children, using basketball to help them develop self-confidence. The children loved coming to his class, where they were learning how to overcome fears and limitations. All of them had improved in their skills except for one little girl, who remained withdrawn and unable to shoot a basket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the gymnasium where they practiced, the front row was an impressive stretch of plush, red-velvet seats which were reserved for VIPs. Pierre had been told by his boss not to let the children use these seats, so as to keep them pristine for the “very important people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But seeing how hard the kids had worked and how much they had achieved, he said to them at their last class, “If you can make a basket, then you can sit in one of those red-velvet seats.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No sooner had he said this than he realized he had made a terrible mistake. The withdrawn girl would not be able to make a basket, and she would feel even more alienated from the others. One by one each child went to the free-throw line, and one by one they each made a basket. Bursting with happiness, they took a seat in one of the fancy chairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally it was the turn of the special child. She tried several times and failed. Then Pierre took the ball from her, and said, “Now close your eyes, and see yourself making a basket.” After a short time, he asked her, “Did you make it?” “No,” was her reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Try again,” he encouraged her. “Did you make it now?” Still “no.” After repeating this several more times, she finally was able to say with amazement, “I made it!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only then did Pierre hand her the ball, and for the first time in her young life, the girl made a basket. The whole class cheered jubilantly for her, and she took her place in one of the special seats—truly a VIP.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;if you can see it you can do it&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After sharing this story, Pierre looked at us deeply and said, “Tell the people that you teach that if they can see it, they can do it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, we share Pierre’s love and wisdom with you. No matter how impossible the search for God may seem at times, if you see your soul embraced in His light with enough concentration and aspiration, you will be able to achieve that which you most ardently seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and love from Assisi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Changes?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-changes/</guid>
      <description>Our two large suitcases lay partially full on the floor. For the past two weeks, we’d been slowly filling them with clothes and travel items for our trip to Ananda centers in Italy and India. We’ll be gone for three and a half months, so planning what to bring for different climes and times has been a bit challenging.
I could feel that my mind was beginning to churn as I weighed different options for what to bring, and tried to form a mental image of all the places to which we’d be going.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Our two large suitcases lay partially full on the floor. For the past two weeks, we’d been slowly filling them with clothes and travel items for our trip to Ananda centers in Italy and India. We’ll be gone for three and a half months, so planning what to bring for different climes and times has been a bit challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could feel that my mind was beginning to churn as I weighed different options for what to bring, and tried to form a mental image of all the places to which we’d be going. Movement, time, space—it began to seem a bit overwhelming to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I remembered a story about a woman who traveled from England to India to visit a great saint there — Ramana Maharshi. Upon meeting him, she said, “I’ve come all the way from London to see you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You haven’t moved at all,” was his startling reply. “The world around you has moved, but your own center has never changed.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-changes.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what changes&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;He was telling her that on the deepest level our consciousness is unmoving and not affected by any outer change. Yoganandaji wrote in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt; that divine sight is center everywhere, circumference nowhere. Every point of the universe can be perceived as the center. You are the center of the universe, and someday you will be able to experience this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda once said, “You don’t really move. Space itself is a delusion. You seem to go from here to your home, to India, to Europe, but the world is really moving around you, as far as the perception of it is concerned. You were never moving, but you put yourself at your periphery, so it seems that you were moving all the time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He went on to say, “The same thing is true for time. You have been living a very long time, and yet you haven’t been living in time at all, except as you have persuaded yourself that it is real. It’s only an illusion in our consciousness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I thought about these vast concepts, my mind began to slow down. I sat to meditate, and realized that soon I would be traveling around the world, but that I would be bringing my Self with me wherever I went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I knew from past experience that the days of our journey would pass quickly. In the blink of an eye, the next thing I would experience would be sitting in our little meditation room once again. Time and space — they really don’t exist as we usually perceive them. We may be dreaming them, but our souls aren’t bound by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji wrote: “God made man immortal. The plan was for him to remain on earth as an immortal. He was to behold the drama of change with a changeless, immortal consciousness and, after seeing the dance of change on the stage of changelessness, he was to return to the bosom of eternal blessedness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silently I offered a prayer of gratitude for the constant guidance of our great teachers, who illumine our lives with their wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have to get back to those suitcases&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
