<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>happiness on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/happiness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in happiness on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s Time to Simplify</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/its-time-to-simply/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/its-time-to-simply/</guid>
      <description>“How can we prepare ourselves for a future that looks so uncertain?” This question was asked during a recent satsang we had with Ananda’s online Virtual Community, and it seemed an important one to discuss.
Swami Kriyananda gave a series of talks which he entitled, “Building Spiritual Power Against Troubled Times.” This is one of the answers to the question of preparing for the future. Our only real security comes by building spiritual power through deepening our devotion and faith in God, the basis for an inward knowing that His protection is always with us.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“How can we prepare ourselves for a future that looks so uncertain?” This question was asked during a recent satsang we had with Ananda’s online Virtual Community, and it seemed an important one to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda gave a series of talks which he entitled, “Building Spiritual Power Against Troubled Times.” This is one of the answers to the question of preparing for the future. Our only real security comes by building spiritual power through deepening our devotion and faith in God, the basis for an inward knowing that His protection is always with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This power is not ours for the mere asking, however, but needs to be developed by deep, regular meditation and increased attunement with the guru. As our awareness of God’s presence in our life deepens, our trust in His protection and guidance increases as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji gave us a powerful affirmation to use in times of uncertainty: “I will go forth in perfect faith in the power of Omnipresent Good to bring me what I need at the time I need it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, the story of Ananda has been a living testimony to the truth of this statement. God and Guru have stepped in repeatedly to rescue us and provide what was needed in even the most dire of circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a second way to prepare for an uncertain future: &lt;strong&gt;Simplify Your Life&lt;/strong&gt;. The more we can free ourselves from the burden of too many possessions, the easier it is to release the thought that security comes from things. Then we can move forward easily into whatever the future may bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at your home and work environment and ask yourself, “What do I really need?” During a period of our life when Swamiji sent us away on many assignments, we moved thirteen times in fourteen years. To make this doable, we would regularly go through our possessions and ask about each one, “Do I use this? Do I love it?” If the answer to either of these questions was “yes,” we would keep it. If not, then out it would go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was actually a wonderful process, and although we have had a consistent home base for some years now, that approach to our possessions stays with us still. In fact, we usually have a small pile of things that no longer pass this test which we lovingly give to others. But remember that it’s not having possessions that’s the problem. It’s our attachment to those things that binds us to the fear of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you stop defining your security according to outer possessions or circumstances, you find a surprising degree of inner freedom. Yoganandaji wrote: “Seek happiness more in your mind and less in the acquisition of things. Be so happy in your mind that nothing that comes can possibly make you unhappy. Then, you can get along without things you have been accustomed to. Be happy knowing you have acquired the power not to be negative. Know, too, that you will never again become so materially minded that you forget your inner happiness, even if you become a millionaire.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a delightful story of a wandering sadhu whose only possessions were a loincloth and a blanket. Once a curious passerby asked him how he could get by with so little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprised, the saintly sadhu answered, “What do you mean? I have everything I need—a roof over my head, a comfortable bed and pillow, and ample clothes to keep me warm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puzzled, the passerby asked, “Where do you have these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saint replied: “When it rains, I put the blanket over a tree branch, and that is my roof. When it’s time to sleep, I arrange the blanket into a nice bed, and when I’m cold, I wrap the blanket around me. I have all that I need.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/its-time-to-simplify.png&#34;  alt=&#34;it&amp;#39;s time to simplify&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The inner freedom and joy of this sadhu can be a model for us all. Master said, “Happiness blooms naturally in the hearts of those who are inwardly free. It flows spontaneously, like a mountain spring after April showers, in minds that are contented with simple living and that willingly renounce the clutter of unnecessary, so-called ‘necessities’—the dream castles of a restless mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friend, to prepare for an uncertain future, remember these two things: 1) Deepen your connection with God, the source of everything; and 2) Simplify your life and realize that security and happiness lie within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards a brighter future,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steps to Happiness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for The Times of India, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called The Speaking Tree, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt;, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called &lt;em&gt;The Speaking Tree&lt;/em&gt;, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016. Friends encouraged me to share it once again. I, too, thought you might enjoy seeing it, even if for a second time. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;five-essential-steps-to-happiness&#34;&gt;Five Essential Steps to Happiness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “I once met a very successful and wealthy man, who said to me, ‘I’m disgustingly healthy, and disgustingly wealthy.’ ‘However,’ I replied, ‘you are not “disgustingly happy,” are you?’ He admitted he was not. Soon afterward, he became a student of this path.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness is something that everyone searches for but very few are able to find. Here are five key steps that lead to permanent happiness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must want to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to accept guidance to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to apply self-discipline in order to follow the guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to shift the focus to making inner, not outer, changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need truly to accept that both happiness and unhappiness are choices we make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look more closely at these five steps.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/steps-to-happiness.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;steps to happiness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t everyone want to be happy? Yes, and no. On a deep level, of course, everyone wants happiness. Paramhansa Yogananda said, in fact, that this desire is the fundamental motivation of every living thing. But on a conscious level, very few people seek happiness. Rather, they seek those things they think will make them happy: money, possessions, relationships, power, fame, etc. The problem with this way of thinking is that nothing outside ourself can ever make us happy. Only we have that power. Why not, then, seek happiness itself, rather than the will-o’-the-wisps that society dangles before us? Happiness lies within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to look for happiness in the right way. At first, many of the ingredients seem counterintuitive, or even counterproductive: non-attachment; serving others; letting go of instinctive patterns such as judgmental reactions, anger, jealousy, and the like. Finding happiness requires, in fact, that we transcend the very self that is doing the seeking. We need a guide who is more advanced to lead us along the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for self-discipline is obvious, but actually to train our will is not easy. Paramhansa Yogananda said, “True freedom is the ability to do what is good and right.” Swami Kriyananda’s mother once described a self-indulgent relative as having a “whim of steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to change ourself, again, should be obvious, but most people put much more energy into trying to change others or change their environment than into making inner changes. You will begin to improve only after you accept that the improvement you seek starts within. And that there, too, is where it ends. You can exert at most a gentle influence on others. Remember, they have the God-given right to their own free will. Never make your own happiness dependent upon the behavior of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a joy appropriate to every situation, even those we think of as unpleasant or disastrous. If you can once really grasp that happiness is a choice, you will have learned one of the most important lessons of all existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, true happiness is a spiritual quest, and comes from the expansion of consciousness. We must expand heart and mind until we break the chains of ego. These shackles keep us bound, and doom us to the vacillating waves of delusion that keep true happiness forever beyond our reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine happiness,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
