<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>happiness on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/happiness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in happiness on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Mountain or the Marketplace</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-mountain-or-the-marketplace/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-mountain-or-the-marketplace/</guid>
      <description>In a vision he had as a boy, Paramhansa Yogananda found himself standing in a crowded, noisy marketplace in an Indian village. The day was hot and dusty, as people crowded into dirty stalls and elbowed out with their purchases.
From time to time, someone would pause and gaze wistfully up at something in the distance behind Master. Then they would turn away with a sad sigh, say, “It’s much too high for me,” and turn back to the press and clamor of the marketplace.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In a vision he had as a boy, Paramhansa Yogananda found himself standing in a crowded, noisy marketplace in an Indian village. The day was hot and dusty, as people crowded into dirty stalls and elbowed out with their purchases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From time to time, someone would pause and gaze wistfully up at something in the distance behind Master. Then they would turn away with a sad sigh, say, “It’s much too high for me,” and turn back to the press and clamor of the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After watching this repeated several times, Yoganandaji turned to see what they’d all been looking at. He found rising behind him a beautiful mountain: tall, serene, and utterly removed from the world of the marketplace. His first thought was like all the others’: “It’s much too high for me.” But then, scorning that thought, he affirmed instead, “It may be too high to ascend with a single leap, but I can at least put one foot in front of the other!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With great will and determination he set out, and at last he reached the heavenly heights. For Master, this vision symbolized the plight of all humanity, who catch glimpses of a higher reality, but lack the resolve to rise above the material world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What stops us from starting the “ascent” to greater awareness?&lt;/strong&gt; Most people are simply engrossed in the marketplace. Others often give up before they begin because they think, “I’m not good enough.” Swami Kriyananda gave us helpful advice in this regard: Anything that makes you feel spiritually inadequate is the influence of Satan, the conscious power of darkness that seeks to keep souls forever bound in delusion. Forget about what you are or aren’t, and remember Yogananda’s oft-repeated words: “A saint is a sinner who never gave up!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re deterred also because we think that the climb will take more energy than we have. Basic to Yoganandaji’s teachings, as practiced in the Energization Exercises, are the concepts of will, energy, and magnetism: “The greater the will, the greater the flow of energy.” And, “The greater the flow of energy, the greater the magnetism.” By using our own willpower, we can draw on the cosmic energy all around us to enhance our own strength. With greater energy, we can magnetically draw everything we need to accomplish our goals. If we put out whatever energy we can, God will match it a hundredfold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another attitude that holds us back is the fear of failure. “What if I try, but don’t achieve my goal? Are all my efforts lost?” In the Bhagavad Gita, Arjuna asks Krishna these very questions. The Lord’s reply brings great reassurance: “O Arjuna, My son! One who performs right actions can never be destroyed. He is reborn on earth in a good and prosperous home. He recovers the yogic discrimination he attained formerly, and sets himself with even greater zeal to achieve final spiritual liberation. The power of former yoga practice is sufficient to impel, as it were, the reborn yogi on his upward path.” (from Ch. 6, 40–44)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-mountain-or-the-marketplace.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the-mountain-or-the-marketplace&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are some factors that motivate us to climb the mountain to Self-realization?&lt;/strong&gt; First, there is the inherently unfulfilling nature of the material world. Based as it is in duality, this world offers us constantly rotating cycles of pain and pleasure, success and failure, happiness and sorrow. Master spoke of the “anguishing monotony” that, after many lifetimes, comes eventually to us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we begin to think, “There must be something better that brings true, lasting fulfillment.” This is the prod from below, but there is also the pull from above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within each of us live deeper-than-conscious memories of higher states of awareness. We may have had touches of memories, flashes of a time when our soul was free and filled with joy. For in the words of a beautiful song of Swamiji’s, God ever calls to His children:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The choice is before us daily: to remain in the crowded, but spiritually empty, marketplace, or to begin the climb up the mountain to God. Kriyanandaji wrote: “The spiritual path requires courage, dedication, and the absolute conviction that only God can ever satisfy the soul’s yearning for true happiness.” The choice is really not as hard as it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Steps to Happiness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/simple-steps-to-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/simple-steps-to-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Paramhansa Yogananda said that everyone in the world is motivated by the same twin desires: “to be happy and avoid pain.” Each of us can take some simple, and yet surprisingly effective strides toward that goal. Even a series of little steps can produce great changes if we apply them consistently.
The road to happiness starts by replacing bad habits with good ones. Many people have a tendency to focus primarily on physical habits such as diet and exercise.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said that everyone in the world is motivated by the same twin desires: “to be happy and avoid pain.” Each of us can take some simple, and yet surprisingly effective strides toward that goal. Even a series of little steps can produce great changes if we apply them consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road to happiness starts by replacing bad habits with good ones. Many people have a tendency to focus primarily on physical habits such as diet and exercise. But since we have a body, mind, and soul, we need to address all three aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda wrote, “During an interview with newspapermen Master prescribed the following rules as a good daily regimen for all: ‘Morning and evening sit in introspective silence thinking of your most important engagement with the soul within. Exercise fifteen minutes. Walk thirty minutes. Study one hour. Meditate one hour and a half. Smile from within all hours.’”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/simple-steps-to-happiness.png&#34;  alt=&#34;simple-steps-to-happiness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A recent study at the University of California at Berkeley revealed some very helpful and hopeful information. Working with more than 70,000 people involved with an initiative called “The Big Joy Project,” scientists found that you can quickly gain a 25% boost in your happiness level by consciously doing “micro-acts of joy.” The study shows that these “micro-acts” led to increased feelings of hope, optimism, and happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works this way: Every day for seven consecutive days, do a small act to boost your emotional well-being. For example, make a gratitude list or keep a gratitude journal. Another practice would be to visit a sick friend or do a nice gesture for someone you know, or even better, for a stranger. Yet another micro-act would be to reframe something you think of as negative into a positive perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the benefit of this practice comes from the conscious decision to make a plan for the week, and then to carry out your daily act of “micro-joy.” What better time to start this than the day after Thanksgiving? Take a few moments right now to think about those things for which you are grateful. Write a few notes of gratitude to those who have helped or uplifted you during the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now make a plan for next week of seven daily acts of micro-joy. Doing this will help us reprogram our mental habits. Paramhansa Yogananda said, “Don’t expect to go to heaven unless you carry a portable heaven within your heart every day.” He also gave this counsel: “If you find your thoughts carried away, little by little, as prisoners of temptation, then you should train your armies of self-control. Seek good company, take right care of the body, and keep your thoughts busy with wonder and bliss of God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most important, is a daily practice of deep meditation. Sometimes meditators can become discouraged by a lack of experiences. But Master said, “Do not grieve because you do not see light or images in meditation. If you go deep into the perception of bliss you will find there the actual presence of God. Seek the Whole, not a part.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we do our part and make an effort, God will reach out to help us. One time Master blessed a disciple who was having a hard time financially. The anxiety-ridden student asked Master how he could stay so calm in the face of troubles. The Master looked at him intently and said, “Remember, the same Father who protects me, protects you. He is our common Father.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replacing bad habits with good ones is important, but the greatest thing we can do to improve happiness is to bring God into every aspect of life, and offer everything we have and are into His light. Faith and gratitude are the cures for all our ills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joyful gratitude,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s Time to Simplify</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/its-time-to-simply/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/its-time-to-simply/</guid>
      <description>“How can we prepare ourselves for a future that looks so uncertain?” This question was asked during a recent satsang we had with Ananda’s online Virtual Community, and it seemed an important one to discuss.
Swami Kriyananda gave a series of talks which he entitled, “Building Spiritual Power Against Troubled Times.” This is one of the answers to the question of preparing for the future. Our only real security comes by building spiritual power through deepening our devotion and faith in God, the basis for an inward knowing that His protection is always with us.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“How can we prepare ourselves for a future that looks so uncertain?” This question was asked during a recent satsang we had with Ananda’s online Virtual Community, and it seemed an important one to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda gave a series of talks which he entitled, “Building Spiritual Power Against Troubled Times.” This is one of the answers to the question of preparing for the future. Our only real security comes by building spiritual power through deepening our devotion and faith in God, the basis for an inward knowing that His protection is always with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This power is not ours for the mere asking, however, but needs to be developed by deep, regular meditation and increased attunement with the guru. As our awareness of God’s presence in our life deepens, our trust in His protection and guidance increases as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji gave us a powerful affirmation to use in times of uncertainty: “I will go forth in perfect faith in the power of Omnipresent Good to bring me what I need at the time I need it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, the story of Ananda has been a living testimony to the truth of this statement. God and Guru have stepped in repeatedly to rescue us and provide what was needed in even the most dire of circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a second way to prepare for an uncertain future: &lt;strong&gt;Simplify Your Life&lt;/strong&gt;. The more we can free ourselves from the burden of too many possessions, the easier it is to release the thought that security comes from things. Then we can move forward easily into whatever the future may bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at your home and work environment and ask yourself, “What do I really need?” During a period of our life when Swamiji sent us away on many assignments, we moved thirteen times in fourteen years. To make this doable, we would regularly go through our possessions and ask about each one, “Do I use this? Do I love it?” If the answer to either of these questions was “yes,” we would keep it. If not, then out it would go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was actually a wonderful process, and although we have had a consistent home base for some years now, that approach to our possessions stays with us still. In fact, we usually have a small pile of things that no longer pass this test which we lovingly give to others. But remember that it’s not having possessions that’s the problem. It’s our attachment to those things that binds us to the fear of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you stop defining your security according to outer possessions or circumstances, you find a surprising degree of inner freedom. Yoganandaji wrote: “Seek happiness more in your mind and less in the acquisition of things. Be so happy in your mind that nothing that comes can possibly make you unhappy. Then, you can get along without things you have been accustomed to. Be happy knowing you have acquired the power not to be negative. Know, too, that you will never again become so materially minded that you forget your inner happiness, even if you become a millionaire.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a delightful story of a wandering sadhu whose only possessions were a loincloth and a blanket. Once a curious passerby asked him how he could get by with so little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprised, the saintly sadhu answered, “What do you mean? I have everything I need—a roof over my head, a comfortable bed and pillow, and ample clothes to keep me warm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puzzled, the passerby asked, “Where do you have these things?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saint replied: “When it rains, I put the blanket over a tree branch, and that is my roof. When it’s time to sleep, I arrange the blanket into a nice bed, and when I’m cold, I wrap the blanket around me. I have all that I need.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/its-time-to-simplify.png&#34;  alt=&#34;it&amp;#39;s time to simplify&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The inner freedom and joy of this sadhu can be a model for us all. Master said, “Happiness blooms naturally in the hearts of those who are inwardly free. It flows spontaneously, like a mountain spring after April showers, in minds that are contented with simple living and that willingly renounce the clutter of unnecessary, so-called ‘necessities’—the dream castles of a restless mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friend, to prepare for an uncertain future, remember these two things: 1) Deepen your connection with God, the source of everything; and 2) Simplify your life and realize that security and happiness lie within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards a brighter future,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steps to Happiness</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/steps-to-happiness/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for The Times of India, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called The Speaking Tree, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I gave a program this past weekend in Gurgaon, India. We were interviewed beforehand by a reporter who works for &lt;em&gt;The Times of India&lt;/em&gt;, India’s largest newspaper, which has a reach of many millions of people. They then published an article of mine in a special section of the paper called &lt;em&gt;The Speaking Tree&lt;/em&gt;, which gives wonderful spiritual teachings. It was a reprint of a blog I’d published back in April of 2016. Friends encouraged me to share it once again. I, too, thought you might enjoy seeing it, even if for a second time. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;five-essential-steps-to-happiness&#34;&gt;Five Essential Steps to Happiness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “I once met a very successful and wealthy man, who said to me, ‘I’m disgustingly healthy, and disgustingly wealthy.’ ‘However,’ I replied, ‘you are not “disgustingly happy,” are you?’ He admitted he was not. Soon afterward, he became a student of this path.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happiness is something that everyone searches for but very few are able to find. Here are five key steps that lead to permanent happiness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must want to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to accept guidance to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to apply self-discipline in order to follow the guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to shift the focus to making inner, not outer, changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need truly to accept that both happiness and unhappiness are choices we make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look more closely at these five steps.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/steps-to-happiness.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;steps to happiness&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t everyone want to be happy? Yes, and no. On a deep level, of course, everyone wants happiness. Paramhansa Yogananda said, in fact, that this desire is the fundamental motivation of every living thing. But on a conscious level, very few people seek happiness. Rather, they seek those things they think will make them happy: money, possessions, relationships, power, fame, etc. The problem with this way of thinking is that nothing outside ourself can ever make us happy. Only we have that power. Why not, then, seek happiness itself, rather than the will-o’-the-wisps that society dangles before us? Happiness lies within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to look for happiness in the right way. At first, many of the ingredients seem counterintuitive, or even counterproductive: non-attachment; serving others; letting go of instinctive patterns such as judgmental reactions, anger, jealousy, and the like. Finding happiness requires, in fact, that we transcend the very self that is doing the seeking. We need a guide who is more advanced to lead us along the path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for self-discipline is obvious, but actually to train our will is not easy. Paramhansa Yogananda said, “True freedom is the ability to do what is good and right.” Swami Kriyananda’s mother once described a self-indulgent relative as having a “whim of steel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to change ourself, again, should be obvious, but most people put much more energy into trying to change others or change their environment than into making inner changes. You will begin to improve only after you accept that the improvement you seek starts within. And that there, too, is where it ends. You can exert at most a gentle influence on others. Remember, they have the God-given right to their own free will. Never make your own happiness dependent upon the behavior of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a joy appropriate to every situation, even those we think of as unpleasant or disastrous. If you can once really grasp that happiness is a choice, you will have learned one of the most important lessons of all existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, true happiness is a spiritual quest, and comes from the expansion of consciousness. We must expand heart and mind until we break the chains of ego. These shackles keep us bound, and doom us to the vacillating waves of delusion that keep true happiness forever beyond our reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine happiness,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
