<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>self-offering on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/self-offering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in self-offering on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/self-offering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Living in the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/living-in-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/living-in-the-light/</guid>
      <description>It is good to celebrate noteworthy events, and this is one of those milestones. You are reading blog number five hundred! Writing five hundred in a row hasn’t always been easy or convenient, but sharing a Touch of Light has been one of the greatest blessings of our lives.
This week also marks another long-standing tradition. We are just finishing Inner Renewal Retreat, a decades-long annual event designed to reawaken and reenergize our spiritual commitment.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;It is good to celebrate noteworthy events, and this is one of those milestones. You are reading blog number five hundred! Writing five hundred in a row hasn’t always been easy or convenient, but sharing a Touch of Light has been one of the greatest blessings of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week also marks another long-standing tradition. We are just finishing Inner Renewal Retreat, a decades-long annual event designed to reawaken and reenergize our spiritual commitment. This year’s theme, “Living in God’s Light,” covered four pillars of the spiritual path: sadhana, service, self-offering, and attunement. The recorded classes will be available soon, but for the thousands of you around the world who couldn’t attend, let me recap a few of the most important points from the three sessions Devi and I did during the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1, Sadhana:&lt;/strong&gt; We talked about increasing the light within through sadhana, especially meditation. The conscious mind, limited by the senses, is ill equipped to recognize our hidden spiritual nature. The purpose of sadhana is to help us awaken in superconsciousness. But to accomplish this we must withdraw the life-force from the body and the senses so that we can see our true reality behind the fringes of a restless mind. “Be still and know that I am God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We gave a fun demonstration of magnetism, illustrating that, like our spiritual reality, many forces in nature are hidden from us.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/living-in-the-light.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;living in the light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2, Seva:&lt;/strong&gt; Paramhansa Yogananda defined his path as a combination of meditation and service. In this class we discussed thirteen different principles of service from an upcoming book of mine. Here are a few that will give you a sense of the subject, and something on which to meditate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seva is a means to dissolve the ego.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are channels for the Divine to serve through us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The attitude with which we serve is more important than what we do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serving with willingness, joy, and enthusiasm increases energy and magnetism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer the fruits of service back to the Divine from whom they come.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 3, Self-Offering:&lt;/strong&gt; People typically pick up this subject from the wrong end. They think about self-offering in terms of things they must give up. Seen this way, self-offering seems to be self-denial. There is a charming true story about an exchange Yogananda had with a famous Hollywood actor, Herb Jeffries, who was a follower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actor said, “Religion keeps telling me, ‘You shan’t do this, you shan’t do that.’ I’m not interested in what I shan’t do. I want to know what I can do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda replied, “Do you smoke?” “Yes,” the actor said. To his surprise, Yogananda said, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, Master asked, “Do you drink alcohol?” “Yes, I enjoy a good drink,” was the reply. Again, Master said, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Yogananda asked, “Do you enjoy the company of women?” “YES! Indeed I do.” And yet again, “You may continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herb, relieved but confused, looked at Yogananda curiously. Master concluded, “You may do all of these things, but I have to warn you that if you take up my teachings, the desire to do them will fall away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is the essence of self-offering: All we can ever offer are limiting desires and attachments. We can no more give God our actual possessions than we can give our bank account to the sun. God will never take anything from us until we willingly offer it to Him. But He lovingly awaits the hour when we realize that all those desires, possessions, and attitudes that we cling to so fiercely are the very things that obstruct our true happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The goal of life and of all spiritual practice is to dissolve the ego.&lt;/strong&gt; All God wants from us is our love, which we offer to Him through sadhana, service, self-offering, and attunement to the guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Paramhansa Yogananda puts it, “Those who are immersed in body-consciousness are like strangers in a foreign land. Our native country is Omnipresence.” And: “The purpose of human life is to find God. That is the only reason for our existence. Job, friends, material interests—these things in themselves mean nothing. They can never provide you with true happiness, for the simple reason that none of them, in itself, is complete. Only God encompasses everything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each week we end our Sunday service with these words from Swami Kriyananda’s Festival of Light:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Lord, we offer up the little light that is in us
Into Thy blazing light of Infinity.
Grant us the grace to know Thee.
And make us ever-increasingly
Pure channels of Thy love to all.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;May we all merge into that infinite light and bliss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Global Circle of Love</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-global-circle-of-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-global-circle-of-love/</guid>
      <description>This is a special moment in time for Jyotish and me. Yesterday we had our last public satsang in Mumbai after nearly four months of traveling, teaching, and sharing love with friends in Assisi and India. By the time you read this, we will be returning to Ananda Village.
In many ways, this trip has been life-changing. Seeing the waves of devotion to Yoganandaji spreading throughout the world, we realize how blessed we’ve been to be a part of this great work started by Swami Kriyananda over fifty years ago.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This is a special moment in time for Jyotish and me. Yesterday we had our last public satsang in Mumbai after nearly four months of traveling, teaching, and sharing love with friends in Assisi and India. By the time you read this, we will be returning to Ananda Village.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this trip has been life-changing. Seeing the waves of devotion to Yoganandaji spreading throughout the world, we realize how blessed we’ve been to be a part of this great work started by Swami Kriyananda over fifty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-global-circle-of-love.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a global circle of love&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Thousands of new students are studying Master’s teachings in person and online, and thousands more are taking discipleship and initiation into Kriya Yoga. What touched us the most, however, was seeing the divine love for others that is being offered by Ananda devotees throughout the world. Here are three stories that we heard during our travels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was told to us by Mahiya, one of the leaders of Ananda Assisi. It took place at Terre di Luce (Lands of Light), their beautiful organic gardens:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer, Satya, a Kriyaban friend, came to help us in the kitchen. He brought his parents with him: Adamo, ninety-two years old, and Eleonora, in her eighties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Satya did his service in the kitchen, they would sit on the sofas and just be. Often people would sit with them, making conversation and expressing kindness. Satya had told them nothing about this path, and they had no idea what Ananda was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eleonora has dementia, but Adamo was fully aware of everything. He loved it here, and wanted to participate in everything! When Satya tried to leave them at the nearby house he had rented, Adamo would have nothing of it—he wanted to be at Terre di Luce!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every afternoon after lunch we have a chanting circle before we start our service. We would often chant to the Guru or to Divine Mother in Sanskrit. The fact that it was all in a strange language didn’t matter to Adamo—he would never miss the chanting circle! After one circle he said, “This place is a paradise. I want to stay here forever. Here you are all friends, and everybody loves and respects one another. You can’t find that in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks after Satya and his parents went back to Rome, Adamo left his body. We had an Astral Ascension Ceremony for him in which everyone shared deeply how much this wonderful soul loved Ananda. We all felt that his wish of “wanting to stay at Ananda forever,” or in the presence of the Masters that he felt here, had come true: He was now in the astral world in the loving hands of our Masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what Terre di Luce is for me and why I love it here. I see it as a place where people come and experience love and friendship which transforms them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories of kindness and compassion from our travels in India are too numerous to tell (I’ll share a few more in the recorded commentary), but two others especially stand out. India was hit very hard by the pandemic, with many deaths and inadequate supplies of medicine, oxygen, and hospital beds. Our center leaders told us that they were often performing eight to ten Astral Ascension Ceremonies per week for members or their loved ones who had passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two dear Kriyaban friends of ours, Dr. Mansi and Dr. Amar, shared stories about serving together on the Covid ward in a hospital in Pune. They’re a married couple, with two teenaged daughters and his parents living with them. In spite of these responsibilities, they served for months on end, often with just a few hours of sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the hospital began filling up with Covid patients who occupied all the beds and spilled out into the hallways, Dr. Amar felt some hesitation about working in such close proximity to infected people. He thought, “I don’t want to catch the disease and bring it home to my family.” In answer, he heard a voice within him say, “Would you hesitate to help your own children? These people are all your children!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this divine guidance, he served wholeheartedly throughout the pandemic. Both he and Dr. Mansi did contract Covid, but their children and parents were never infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the pandemic, when the deaths began overwhelming even the crematoriums, Dr. Mansi was exhausted and hit an emotional wall. One day in particular she saw many deaths not only of the elderly, but also of young men who were the sole support of their families. She returned home in the evening exhausted and with a heavy heart. As she closed her eyes for a few minutes, she had a remarkable dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it Master appeared in the hospital dressed in silvery-white robes, bustling here and there attending to the patients. He turned to her and said, “The disease is caused by bad karma brought on by people’s negative thoughts. We can’t stop the disease, but we must stay very busy trying to help everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mansi then began shaping balls of mud into babies. When she held them, they were living children; when she put them down they were only mud once more. “Don’t you see?” Master said. “When Divine Mother touches them, they come alive. Otherwise they are dead. Don’t grieve, my daughter.” After this dream, Mansi was able to continue in her service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, in these stories you can see the beauty of living for God and serving Him in others. Our lives have been changed by witnessing such self-offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Thy Will Be Done</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-thy-will-be-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-thy-will-be-done/</guid>
      <description>A friend of ours told us that she has always believed in and used the power of prayer. Since childhood, however, her prayers have gradually become simpler and more focused. Now she repeats only a single prayer every day and for every situation: “Lord, let Thy will be done.” This was also the final prayer of Jesus just before his crucifixion. One might call it the ultimate prayer of all great souls.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours told us that she has always believed in and used the power of prayer. Since childhood, however, her prayers have gradually become simpler and more focused. Now she repeats only a single prayer every day and for every situation: “Lord, let Thy will be done.” This was also the final prayer of Jesus just before his crucifixion. One might call it the ultimate prayer of all great souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This prayer provides several profound benefits. For one thing, it allows one truly to follow Yogananda’s advice to “remain even-minded and cheerful in all circumstances.” A second, more important benefit is that complete self-offering is the most fertile soil in which deep devotion and faith can grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are caught in the labyrinth of our ego we see only a very distorted reality, filtered through the lens of our moods, desires, and attachments. The distortions of the mind due to the turbulence of the heart are depicted beautifully in a song, “Both Sides Now,” by Joni Mitchell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Rows and floes of angel hair
And ice cream castles in the air
And feather canyons everywhere
I’ve looked at clouds that way

But now they only block the sun
They rain and snow on everyone
So many things I would have done
But clouds got in my way

I’ve looked at clouds from both sides now
From up and down, and still somehow
It’s cloud illusions I recall
I really don’t know clouds at all
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The song goes on to address the themes of love and life in much the same way, with one’s positive and negative moods distorting perception until the inevitable conclusion is: &lt;em&gt;I really don’t know love at all, and I really don’t know life at all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t this everyone’s dilemma—clouds get in our way? A blossoming of love, faith, and clarity is the real benefit of the prayer, &lt;em&gt;Let Thy will be done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-thy-will-be-done.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let thy will be done&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda put it this way: “Faith must be cultivated. It cannot be achieved by mere wishful thinking. If you throw yourself off a mountaintop with the affirmation, ‘God will protect me,’ just see if He does! He expects you to use the common sense He has given you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He will take care of you, surely, if you do your best always, act sensibly, and leave the results in His hands. Faith, however, must be watered by inner experience, like a plant. The more you actually experience the care He takes of you, the more you will come to rely on Him—not fanatically, but naturally, in the divine way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also said, “God doesn’t always answer your prayers in the way that you expect, but, if your faith in Him never wavers, He will grant you far more than you expect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I embark today on our long journey to Italy and India. There are countless unknowns ahead of us, as there are for everyone, every day. Ultimately, anxiety about the future simply takes away our joy. It make a lot more sense to just relax and say lovingly to Divine Mother, “Let Thy will be done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the loving arms of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
