<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>remember on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/remember/</link>
    <description>Recent content in remember on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/remember/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>During the Day</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/during-the-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/during-the-day/</guid>
      <description>We are often asked, “How can I keep the peace and joy I feel in meditation during the demands and distractions of daily activity?” This is, in fact, one of life’s ever-present tests. Another way of phrasing this question is, “How can I keep my energy flowing in a positive direction, in tune with my higher aspirations, so that the world does not pull me down?”
Here are some solutions to this great challenge:</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We are often asked, “How can I keep the peace and joy I feel in meditation during the demands and distractions of daily activity?” This is, in fact, one of life’s ever-present tests. Another way of phrasing this question is, “How can I keep my energy flowing in a positive direction, in tune with my higher aspirations, so that the world does not pull me down?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some solutions to this great challenge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;during-activity&#34;&gt;During Activity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we must act, let us do our best to act properly. What constitutes proper action? We can learn much from the example of great teachers such as Patanjali, Jesus, and Buddha. Indeed, the essence of all spiritual teaching is that we should act in attunement with God or His saints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are unsure about a contemplated course of action, just ask, “Will this move me toward God or away from Him (or Her)?” The mere act of asking that question is half the battle. If we but ask, we will often feel an inward guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for when we are busily engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pray to God during the day:&lt;/strong&gt; before meals, before work, before interacting with others. It only takes a moment, and will keep the spotlight of your mind turned toward your higher Self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Control what you can:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure that the music you listen to is uplifting. A market owner was plagued by rough characters hanging around in his parking lot. His solution was brilliant. He played classical music through loudspeakers; they couldn’t stand the uplifting vibrations, and left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The same is true for the rough characters that inhabit the darker recesses of our mind. Drive them away with good vibrations.&lt;/strong&gt; Keep your environment clean and colors pure. With the movies you watch or books you read, imagine that God is sitting beside you, because He is. Choose your companions wisely; good company is vital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the breath to calm the mind.&lt;/strong&gt; Before or during tense situations, keep your posture erect and take a few deep, slow breaths. It will both center your mind and give you space to act rather than react.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;during-idle-moments&#34;&gt;During Idle Moments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have many times during the day when we are not engaged: between tasks, waiting in line, riding in a car. These are precious moments. The goal at these times is to practice the presence of God, conversing with Him as you would with a close friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some specific suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chant inwardly or repeat a mantra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the breath—you can even practice Hong-Sau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pray for those around you, or give them a smile and some positive energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remind yourself that everyone and everything you are seeing is God alone. As you gaze about, repeat to yourself, “I see only Thee, Lord.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most important of all, remember to relax and enjoy the day. Life is a long and winding road, and if we don’t enjoy the ride we will end up grim and bitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/during-the-day.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;during the day&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;when-youre-able-to-withdraw&#34;&gt;When You’re Able to Withdraw&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are times during the day when we are able to be completely still. The goal during these times is to retract the life force, bringing it inward and upward. We recently read this very powerful practice recommended by Yogananda: “The great work now before you is to practice going up and down the spine, chanting Aum at each center. In that way you will gain more than by reading all the books—practice going up and down the spine and get acquainted with those currents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often during the day you cannot control what is happening around you, but you can always control yourself. It is not difficult to practice any of these suggestions. The great challenge is to remember to do so during a busy day. If you forget, don’t despair. To paraphrase Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, “Even a little practice of the remembrance of the Divine will save us from dire fears and colossal suffering.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let God Decide</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-god-decide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-god-decide/</guid>
      <description>Devi and I have been spending a month at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, where there is great reverence for St. Francis. Paramhansa Yogananda, too, honored him, calling him his “patron saint.”
A few years after Ananda’s arrival in Italy, word began to reach Swami Kriyananda, who was residing here at the time, that the Bishop of Assisi had been issuing warnings against us. Apparently, Church authorities had come to consider our presence there a threat.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Devi and I have been spending a month at the Ananda community near Assisi, Italy, where there is great reverence for St. Francis. Paramhansa Yogananda, too, honored him, calling him his “patron saint.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years after Ananda’s arrival in Italy, word began to reach Swami Kriyananda, who was residing here at the time, that the Bishop of Assisi had been issuing warnings against us. Apparently, Church authorities had come to consider our presence there a threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda, being a very forthright person, decided to have a talk with him. In many ways they turned out to be kindred souls: both of them highly intelligent, well educated, and sincere in their spirituality. After spending some time discussing spiritual matters, Swamiji was about to take his leave. As he was at the door the Bishop said, “I enjoyed our time together and really like you. Too bad you aren’t a Christian.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji, knowing that it would be useless to argue, replied with a twinkle in his eye, “You say I am not a Christian, and I say I am. Let’s let Jesus decide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thought, “Let’s let God decide,” should be like a mantra, a compass that guides our life. It is a shorthand way of saying, “Not my will, nor your will, but God’s will.” For devotees of this path, we might translate it as, “What would Master do?” or, “What does my own higher Self advise for me?” How many arguments could be avoided if we let this attitude guide us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda put it this way: “Learning to love our relatives is simply a training in stretching our consciousness. It is a preliminary practice in loving all others as we do our relations, whom we think of as our own. We have to learn to look on family and strangers alike, because all are children of God. He has given you certain family members with whom you are practicing stretching your consciousness. When the husband serves the wife, and she serves him, each with the desire to see the other happy, Christ Consciousness—God’s loving Cosmic Intelligence that permeates every atom of creation—has begun to express itself through their consciousness. Whenever you do something for someone else, without any selfish motive, you have stepped into the sphere of Christ Consciousness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we align our heart and mind with those of the stretched consciousness of a master, we have a polestar to guide us. If we could simply remember to ask the question, “What do you advise?” most problems in life, and especially in relationships, could be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I have recently finished a ten-class course, How to Develop Harmonious Relationships. In it we explore all facets of relationships of every kind: personal and intimate ones as well as others such as friendships and those that are work-related.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-god-decide.png&#34;  alt=&#34;let god decide&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all relationships are expressions of the Christ consciousness, but the more we are caught up in desires, attachments, and ego, the more conflicts arise. Human emotions, especially negative ones, are a labyrinth with no exit. The only real solution is to rise above the limiting walls of ego into the free skies of higher consciousness. How? By remembering to ask God or a master, “What do you advise here?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking is one part of the picture. Listening for His response is the other part. God won’t intrude on our free will, so we must first be truly ready to accept His advice. Then we must allow our minds and emotions to become still. He loves us as His very own, and is waiting for us to turn to Him. When we do, He will answer us with a soft and loving whisper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next time you are about to argue a point, follow Swami Kriyananda’s model and say, perhaps with a twinkle in your eye, “Let’s let God decide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In His all-embracing love,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Short Memory</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/a-short-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/a-short-memory/</guid>
      <description>“Are you there, God? Are you listening to my prayers? Do you even know what I’m going through?”
I think we all have thoughts like these from time to time—especially when we’re facing challenges in life. To keep our faith strong, it’s important to remember those times—and we’ve all had them—when our prayers have in fact been answered.
Recently a friend told me about a trip she’d taken in which she encountered one hurdle after another.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“Are you there, God? Are you listening to my prayers? Do you even know what I’m going through?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we all have thoughts like these from time to time—especially when we’re facing challenges in life. To keep our faith strong, it’s important to remember those times—and we’ve all had them—when our prayers have in fact been answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend told me about a trip she’d taken in which she encountered one hurdle after another. The final blow came when she was driving home alone at night from the airport and realized she had a flat tire. Not knowing what to do, she was about to panic when a friend “coincidentally” drove by. He stopped his car and helped her change the tire; soon she was on her way home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her story reminded me of an incident in my own life that happened about fifteen years ago—one that I’d forgotten. A friend of mine had been diagnosed with widespread cancer. To slow the disease’s advance, she began receiving intravenous chemotherapy. A group of her friends would take turns driving her to the chemo sessions, and would sit with her throughout the day until she was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marilyn (this was her name) was a quiet, gentle soul who was a devoted follower of Yoganandaji. She never complained about her diagnosis, the treatments, the changes they wrought on her body, nor the upheaval the disease caused in her life. She passed away peacefully about a year after this story took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that particular day, Marilyn had finished her latest chemotherapy session, and I was driving her back to Ananda Village. It was late afternoon; exhausted from the treatment, Marilyn reclined in the passenger seat and drifted off to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were a few miles away from Ananda on a rural road, when suddenly I heard the dreaded “thump, thump, thump,” and knew we had a flat tire. I pulled over to the side of the road, and not knowing how to change a tire nor seeing anyone around, inwardly I offered a desperate prayer for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just at that moment, an old, beat-up pickup truck pulled over in front of us. Two disreputable-looking characters with long, greasy hair and dirty clothes came over to the car. Since I didn’t know what to expect, I cautiously rolled my window down a crack. To my great relief one of them said, “Looks like you ladies can use a little help.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short order, they changed the tire and were on their way. I was sitting in stunned silence, when Marilyn opened her eyes and quietly asked, “What happened?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think God just heard my prayer,” was my quiet reply.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/a-short-memory.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;a short memory&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Left to right) Jitendra Mazumdar, companion on the “penniless test” at Brindaban; Lalita-da, Master’s cousin; Swami Kebalananda, Master’s saintly Sanskrit tutor; and Master, as a high school youth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most beautiful and powerful chapters in &lt;em&gt;Autobiography of a Yogi&lt;/em&gt; is “Two Penniless Boys in Brindaban,” in which Yoganandaji’s eldest brother, Ananta, challenges him to put his faith in God to a test. Ananta proposes that young Yoganandaji travel to the nearby city of Agra with a friend, Jitendra, but with no money and no return ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complete the test, they must not beg, reveal their predicament to anyone, nor miss any meals. Further, the boys must see the sights of Agra and return home by train before midnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps feeling some remorse for sending two young boys on such a journey, the skeptical Ananta added: “If by any chance or grace you pass successfully through the Brindaban ordeal, I shall ask you to initiate me as your disciple.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are familiar with the rest of the story. While still on the train to Brindaban, they were approached by two strangers who invited them to lunch at their ashram. The meal turned out to be a sumptuous repast prepared for two princes, patrons of the ashram who at the last minute were unable to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they were leaving the ashram, replete from their elaborate banquet, Jitendra complained, “A fine mess you have got me into! Our luncheon was only accidental good fortune! How can we see the sights of this city, without a single pice between us? And how on earth are you going to take me back to Ananta’s?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yogananda’s reply was one we all need to remember: “You forget God quickly, now that your stomach is filled.” His account continues, “My words, not bitter, were accusatory. &lt;strong&gt;How short is human memory for divine favors! No man lives who has not seen certain of his prayers granted.&lt;/strong&gt;” (If you haven’t read the Autobiography, I’ll let you discover for yourself how the story ends.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, how short our memory is for the graces we have received. As you finish reading these words, I suggest that you take a moment to recall an instance in your own life of an answered prayer, or a feeling of certainty of God’s love for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great saints tell us that God’s blessings, guidance, and protection are always with us. It is we who too often forget them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking always to remember,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
