<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>maya on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/maya/</link>
    <description>Recent content in maya on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/maya/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Be the Big Picture</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/be-the-big-picture/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/be-the-big-picture/</guid>
      <description>There are times when life seems to bear down on us. It’s difficult then to remain positive amidst the challenges in our life, and that we see in the lives of others, and in the world at large. Yet in this world of duality, the alternating waves of joy and sorrow are a constant. It’s how we deal with them that keeps us either forever tossed on the crashing waves of maya, or resting in the unmoving peace of God.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;There are times when life seems to bear down on us. It’s difficult then to remain positive amidst the challenges in our life, and that we see in the lives of others, and in the world at large. Yet in this world of duality, the alternating waves of joy and sorrow are a constant. It’s how we deal with them that keeps us either forever tossed on the crashing waves of maya, or resting in the unmoving peace of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a very dear friend at Ananda, Nayaswami Maria Warner, who battled cancer for many years until her passing in 2010. In the face of repeated surgeries and rounds of chemotherapy, she never lost her resilience, nor her desire to serve and seek God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the last months of her life it was discovered that the cancer had spread to her brain. As her husband, who was struggling with the thought of what lay ahead, pushed her in a wheelchair into the hospital, she looked up at him and calmly said: “Detach yourself. Control the reactive process. Live the teachings.” These profound words have become known as “Maria’s Mantra,” and have offered guidance and solace to many in the midst of their own struggles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we find the wisdom and strength to rise above life’s challenges? Try to see the bigger picture, of which we are only an infinitesimally small part. In other words, put yourself in the context of a larger scheme of things, and live in life’s longer rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Swami Kriyananda needed to have some painful dental work done, and declined anesthetic because he didn’t like the feeling of dullness it caused. He later told us that during the procedure, he thought, “I’ve had a long, rewarding life filled with many happy memories. This present pain is just one moment in the whole scheme of my life’s experiences.” Everything went smoothly, and Swamiji ended up composing music in his mind as the dentist worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also good to take time out and absorb yourself in the vast vistas of nature. Jyotish and I just spent a week by the ocean walking along beautiful coastal trails. We were filled with joy at the power of great, crashing waves, and with wonder at the amazing diversity of life in the tide pools. It was wonderfully refreshing and uplifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go into nature and gaze at scenes that expand your consciousness: mountains, the ocean, or a star-filled sky. Remember, however, that what we behold outside of us is only a reflection of what lies within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda used to enjoy describing a cartoon that he’d once seen in The New Yorker magazine. It showed a pompous businessman with his wife gazing up at the stars. She had obviously asked him a question, and his reply in the caption was: “Make me feel small? Not at all. I was just made regional manager for my company.” Life’s wonders are lost on the self-absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/be-the-big-picture.png&#34;  alt=&#34;be-the-big-picture&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To see the big picture, we must first expand our consciousness through meditation. Feel joy within, and then behold it in the beauty of flowers. Feel love within, then behold it in the great diversity of life. Feel calm expansion within, then feel the peace of the infinite reach of stars. Feel unmoving stillness within, and see it reflected in the mountains. Feel God’s limitless power, and see it in the crashing waves and ocean deeps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, however, it’s not enough only to see the big picture—we must become it. This is the way of self-transcendence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master expresses this in so much of what he has given us. There’s his chant: “I am the bubble / Make me the sea. / Wave of the sea / Dissolve in the sea.” And his poem “Samadhi” concludes with the words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A tiny bubble of laughter, I
Am become the Sea of Mirth Itself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is the whole journey of life in a nutshell: Find the tiny bubble of joy within you and expand it until you become the ocean of unlimited bliss. Then, whatever life brings, you know you are a part of something much greater, of something eternal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Minutes are More Important Than the Years</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-minutes-are-more-important-than-the-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-minutes-are-more-important-than-the-years/</guid>
      <description>The cedar beams framing the large, picture window were old and rough, filled with tiny holes and cracks. As I began to apply a wood stain to seal the beams, I could see that many coats would be needed to make them look finished. Standing high on a scaffold, I dipped my brush in the can of stain and began.
What led up to this moment was this: One morning in about 1972, Swamiji entered the dining room at the Meditation Retreat, and asked those of us finishing breakfast, “Is anyone free to help me paint the inside of my new dome?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The cedar beams framing the large, picture window were old and rough, filled with tiny holes and cracks. As I began to apply a wood stain to seal the beams, I could see that many coats would be needed to make them look finished. Standing high on a scaffold, I dipped my brush in the can of stain and began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What led up to this moment was this: One morning in about 1972, Swamiji entered the dining room at the Meditation Retreat, and asked those of us finishing breakfast, “Is anyone free to help me paint the inside of my new dome?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ananda construction crew had just completed his home. Although some finishing work such as interior painting was still needed, Swamiji was eager to move in. A group of us happily volunteered and drove over to Crystal Hermitage, ready to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This launched one of the most remarkable experiences of my life. It was about ten o’clock in the morning when each of us started our painting tasks, with Swamiji working alongside us. I chose to stain the beams framing the windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the building was new, the carpenters had chosen to use a rough cedar wood for some of the dome’s trim. After a few hours of work, Swamiji said, “Let’s take a break for lunch, and then come back and do some more.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real magic began to happen after the lunch break. I climbed back up onto the scaffolding, and continued to stain and restain the rustic beams. Glancing at the clock as we started up after lunch, I saw that the time was a little after one p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being focused on our painting, we were oblivious to the passing of time. We painted and stained, and rather than feeling tired, we were increasingly joyful to be helping Swamiji. Finally he said with his usual magnetic enthusiasm, “Well, everyone, let’s call it a day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were surprised to see that since it was dark outside now, time must have gotten away from us. Again I glanced at the clock, and to my amazement it wasn’t evening, but two a.m.! We had been so concentrated on what we were doing that we were totally unaware that more than twelve hours had passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Swamiji blessed us that day with the experience of a deep, prolonged state of concentration. That was probably how he approached everything he did, but for us it was a revelation to see how a sense of timelessness accompanied our absorbed concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For time and space are not real in themselves, but are divisions that belong to the realm of maya, or duality. In fact, the Sanskrit word “maya” means just that: “the measurer.” With a deeply concentrated mind, we can enter the state of superconsciousness, which transcends such dualities. I believe that is what happened as we painted Swamiji’s dome that day.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-minutes-are-more-important-than-the-years.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the minutes are more important than the years&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kriyanandaji often spoke of the importance of bringing “keen, alert attention” to everything that we do. The next step is deeply to focus our attention not only on what we’re doing outwardly, but inwardly on God. This is essential for deeper meditation and spiritual awakening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The minutes are more important than the years. If you fill the minutes of your life with thoughts of God, you will find the years of your life automatically saturated with the consciousness of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Never think of tomorrow. Take care of today and all the tomorrows will be taken care of. Do not wait until tomorrow to meditate. Do not wait until tomorrow to be good. Be good now. Be calm now. It will be the turning point of your life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There lies within us the latent power to focus our mind totally on God or on one of His qualities, such as love, joy, compassion, selflessness. When we do this, the rough exterior of life begins to melt away, and the heavenly gardens of the “Eternal Now” open their gates to us, changing our perspective on reality forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing, doing, one day done,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I See No Stranger</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/i-see-no-stranger/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/i-see-no-stranger/</guid>
      <description>The beautiful plaque on the wall of our friends’ home caught my eye. We were in Chandigarh staying with a Sikh family who are fellow disciples of Paramhansa Yogananda. They welcomed us with such graciousness and warmth that we soon felt totally at home.
The most prominent feature of the plaque that had drawn my attention was a striking drawing of the Golden Temple at Amritsar, the most sacred site for the Sikhs.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The beautiful plaque on the wall of our friends’ home caught my eye. We were in Chandigarh staying with a Sikh family who are fellow disciples of Paramhansa Yogananda. They welcomed us with such graciousness and warmth that we soon felt totally at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most prominent feature of the plaque that had drawn my attention was a striking drawing of the Golden Temple at Amritsar, the most sacred site for the Sikhs. What stood out the most for me, however, was a small poem at the bottom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I see no stranger, I see no enemy; I look upon all with goodwill. . . .
The one Beloved dwells in all. Beholding this wonder, I bloom with joy.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;These words were written nearly five hundred years ago by Guru Arjan Dev, the fifth guru in the Sikh lineage. It was he who built the holy temple at Amritsar, and who created the first rendition of the Sikh holy book, the &lt;em&gt;Guru Granth Sahib&lt;/em&gt;, which is housed there. This sacred text is a collection of his own poetry, and that of others in the line of ten Sikh gurus, as well as a number of Hindu and Muslim saints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uplifted by the drawing of the magnificent temple and those beautiful words, I was then stunned to read about the conclusion of this great soul’s life: In 1606 Guru Arjan was tortured to death by the invading Mughal emperor Jahangir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How little the world has changed,” I thought. Here we are still today with Hindu against Muslim, Muslim against Christian, Christian against Jew; with racism against Blacks; with one political party against the other; with one nation against another: the list could go on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can this ever end? It is only by the upliftment of consciousness. In the teachings of India, the term “maya” is used to denote “delusion.” To bring everything into manifestation, God divided His infinite consciousness into pairs of opposites, creating light and darkness, good and evil, joy and sorrow, male and female.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The literal meaning of “maya” is the “measurer,” that which divides the undifferentiated whole into seemingly different parts. The tension created by these dichotomies keeps us engrossed in the play of life, until our souls tire of the endless cycling between conflicting opposites. Then we crave to realize the underlying unity of all things, in which we see the One Consciousness behind the many forms.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/i-see-no-stranger.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;i see no stranger&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I do believe that, contrary to current appearances, the human race is moving toward this higher perspective. Personal and global suffering are helping us to see that when one is oppressed, we all are oppressed; when one loses his security or freedom, we all lose it. This awareness must come in time, because in essence we are not separate one from another. God manifested each of us out of His own consciousness; we are all equally parts of Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, a friend gave us an original edition of Paramhansa Yogananda’s book of poetry, &lt;em&gt;Songs of the Soul&lt;/em&gt;, which was signed by him personally. His inscription reads: “There is one breath that enlivens all strange lands and strangers. Under one sky we live watched by One Father. With my blessings, Swami Yogananda, Oct. 20, 1924.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May we all awaken to that consciousness in which, blessed by one Father, we see no strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With hope,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
