<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>concentration on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/concentration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in concentration on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/concentration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>One at a Time</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/one-at-a-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/one-at-a-time/</guid>
      <description>In such a chaotic world it is easy to feel overwhelmed. How do we cope with the pressures and demands? It helps if we break things down into small steps.
Mary Kretzmann, the head of our Healing Prayer Ministry, related how difficult it is to keep staff over a long period of time. People get overwhelmed by the many tragic circumstances among the prayer requests sent to Ananda each month—hundreds of them.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In such a chaotic world it is easy to feel overwhelmed. How do we cope with the pressures and demands? It helps if we break things down into small steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary Kretzmann, the head of our Healing Prayer Ministry, related how difficult it is to keep staff over a long period of time. People get overwhelmed by the many tragic circumstances among the prayer requests sent to Ananda each month—hundreds of them. She told a lovely story about how she copes with this problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young girl was walking on a beach on which thousands of starfish had washed up after a big storm. She would stop, pick up a starfish, and gently toss it back into the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while an observer approached her and said, “Why are you doing this? The beach is littered with thousands of starfish. You can’t save them all. In fact you can’t begin to make much of a difference.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The young girl stooped to pick up one more. After she threw it back into the sea, she looked up and said, “Well, I made a difference to that one.” The man nodded quietly and joined her in helping the ones they could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary applies this principle to her particular service, but it applies to so many circumstances in our lives. When we feel overwhelmed it helps to tackle the problems one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also helps to keep a sense of humor. Devi and I would often save up a good joke to tell Swami Kriyananda at our customary afternoon tea with him. I can vividly remember the look on his face as he waited with joyful anticipation for the punch line. Here is one we told him:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rather pompous minister arrived at the pearly gates. St. Peter glanced at him and told him to sit down and wait. A little while later a bedraggled man in old clothes arrived and St. Peter lit up with joy. “Joe, it is so good to see you. Your seat in heaven is waiting.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/one-at-a-time.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;one-at-a-time&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The minister, upset by this, asked, “Why does he get the red-carpet treatment while you ignore me? I’ve been doing God’s work for many decades.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Peter replied, “Well, you see, Joe was a cabdriver in New York City. A lot more people offered up sincere prayers in the back seat of his cab than ever did in your church.” I can still remember Swami roaring with laughter as his natural joy bubbled to the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t get far with problems, either in daily life or in meditation, unless we learn to concentrate on one thing at a time. It also helps to approach our problems with a little detachment. So often, when feeling overwhelmed we resort to daydreaming or fantasizing. There is a verse in Swami Kriyananda’s song, “The Christ Child’s Asleep” that captures this beautifully:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Our pleasures and pains,
Our losses, our gains
Have kept us long bound.
The ropes of yearning hemmed us ’round.
We dreamed of imposing on desert sand
Flower gardens of beauty, verdant vales of delight:
Imagination misted our sight!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, concentration, humor, and detachment are our allies. We would do well to ignore the larger issues for the moment and take things one step at a time. If it works for starfish, cabdrivers, and swamis, it will work for us too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In love and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Minutes are More Important Than the Years</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-minutes-are-more-important-than-the-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-minutes-are-more-important-than-the-years/</guid>
      <description>The cedar beams framing the large, picture window were old and rough, filled with tiny holes and cracks. As I began to apply a wood stain to seal the beams, I could see that many coats would be needed to make them look finished. Standing high on a scaffold, I dipped my brush in the can of stain and began.
What led up to this moment was this: One morning in about 1972, Swamiji entered the dining room at the Meditation Retreat, and asked those of us finishing breakfast, “Is anyone free to help me paint the inside of my new dome?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The cedar beams framing the large, picture window were old and rough, filled with tiny holes and cracks. As I began to apply a wood stain to seal the beams, I could see that many coats would be needed to make them look finished. Standing high on a scaffold, I dipped my brush in the can of stain and began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What led up to this moment was this: One morning in about 1972, Swamiji entered the dining room at the Meditation Retreat, and asked those of us finishing breakfast, “Is anyone free to help me paint the inside of my new dome?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ananda construction crew had just completed his home. Although some finishing work such as interior painting was still needed, Swamiji was eager to move in. A group of us happily volunteered and drove over to Crystal Hermitage, ready to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This launched one of the most remarkable experiences of my life. It was about ten o’clock in the morning when each of us started our painting tasks, with Swamiji working alongside us. I chose to stain the beams framing the windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the building was new, the carpenters had chosen to use a rough cedar wood for some of the dome’s trim. After a few hours of work, Swamiji said, “Let’s take a break for lunch, and then come back and do some more.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real magic began to happen after the lunch break. I climbed back up onto the scaffolding, and continued to stain and restain the rustic beams. Glancing at the clock as we started up after lunch, I saw that the time was a little after one p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being focused on our painting, we were oblivious to the passing of time. We painted and stained, and rather than feeling tired, we were increasingly joyful to be helping Swamiji. Finally he said with his usual magnetic enthusiasm, “Well, everyone, let’s call it a day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were surprised to see that since it was dark outside now, time must have gotten away from us. Again I glanced at the clock, and to my amazement it wasn’t evening, but two a.m.! We had been so concentrated on what we were doing that we were totally unaware that more than twelve hours had passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Swamiji blessed us that day with the experience of a deep, prolonged state of concentration. That was probably how he approached everything he did, but for us it was a revelation to see how a sense of timelessness accompanied our absorbed concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For time and space are not real in themselves, but are divisions that belong to the realm of maya, or duality. In fact, the Sanskrit word “maya” means just that: “the measurer.” With a deeply concentrated mind, we can enter the state of superconsciousness, which transcends such dualities. I believe that is what happened as we painted Swamiji’s dome that day.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-minutes-are-more-important-than-the-years.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the minutes are more important than the years&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Kriyanandaji often spoke of the importance of bringing “keen, alert attention” to everything that we do. The next step is deeply to focus our attention not only on what we’re doing outwardly, but inwardly on God. This is essential for deeper meditation and spiritual awakening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “The minutes are more important than the years. If you fill the minutes of your life with thoughts of God, you will find the years of your life automatically saturated with the consciousness of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Never think of tomorrow. Take care of today and all the tomorrows will be taken care of. Do not wait until tomorrow to meditate. Do not wait until tomorrow to be good. Be good now. Be calm now. It will be the turning point of your life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There lies within us the latent power to focus our mind totally on God or on one of His qualities, such as love, joy, compassion, selflessness. When we do this, the rough exterior of life begins to melt away, and the heavenly gardens of the “Eternal Now” open their gates to us, changing our perspective on reality forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing, doing, one day done,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Can See It, You Can Do It</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it/</guid>
      <description>The throngs of excited travelers moved quickly past us as they dragged their luggage and children along in search of their departure gates. We were in the Frankfurt airport with a long layover waiting for our connecting flight to Rome, and then on to Assisi. We would be spending the next month in Assisi, sharing with our Ananda spiritual family as well as with devotees from all over Europe.
While we waited for our flight, we were frantically studying Italian so that we might have some semblance of facility to converse with our friends.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The throngs of excited travelers moved quickly past us as they dragged their luggage and children along in search of their departure gates. We were in the Frankfurt airport with a long layover waiting for our connecting flight to Rome, and then on to Assisi. We would be spending the next month in Assisi, sharing with our Ananda spiritual family as well as with devotees from all over Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we waited for our flight, we were frantically studying Italian so that we might have some semblance of facility to converse with our friends. Intently focused as we were, we were surprised when a man suddenly stood before us. He impressed us with the clear, strong energy which shone in his eyes and in the radiance of his smile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been watching you from across the room,” he said, “and when I saw your beautiful smiles, I just had to come over to talk with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He began asking us about our lives, and strangely it felt like we were old friends, picking up where we had left off at some other time. He was sincerely interested when we told him about Ananda, the path that we follow, and how we came to dedicate our lives to a spiritual search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pierre (our new/old friend) was an American, but he’d been living abroad for the past fifteen years serving as head basketball coach at the Tony Parker Academy, one of the finest athletic academies in Lyon, France. “We coach people from all walks of life—from undefeated pro teams, to high school kids looking for a career in basketball, to people who simply need help and encouragement,” he told us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He listened thoughtfully as we explained how we teach meditation to help people find their own highest potential. Then he looked at us intently, and said, “That’s what I do, too, but in a different way. I’ll tell you a story about how I work with people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the story he shared. Pierre had been working with a group of autistic children, using basketball to help them develop self-confidence. The children loved coming to his class, where they were learning how to overcome fears and limitations. All of them had improved in their skills except for one little girl, who remained withdrawn and unable to shoot a basket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the gymnasium where they practiced, the front row was an impressive stretch of plush, red-velvet seats which were reserved for VIPs. Pierre had been told by his boss not to let the children use these seats, so as to keep them pristine for the “very important people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But seeing how hard the kids had worked and how much they had achieved, he said to them at their last class, “If you can make a basket, then you can sit in one of those red-velvet seats.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No sooner had he said this than he realized he had made a terrible mistake. The withdrawn girl would not be able to make a basket, and she would feel even more alienated from the others. One by one each child went to the free-throw line, and one by one they each made a basket. Bursting with happiness, they took a seat in one of the fancy chairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally it was the turn of the special child. She tried several times and failed. Then Pierre took the ball from her, and said, “Now close your eyes, and see yourself making a basket.” After a short time, he asked her, “Did you make it?” “No,” was her reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Try again,” he encouraged her. “Did you make it now?” Still “no.” After repeating this several more times, she finally was able to say with amazement, “I made it!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only then did Pierre hand her the ball, and for the first time in her young life, the girl made a basket. The whole class cheered jubilantly for her, and she took her place in one of the special seats—truly a VIP.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/if-you-can-see-it-you-can-do-it.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;if you can see it you can do it&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After sharing this story, Pierre looked at us deeply and said, “Tell the people that you teach that if they can see it, they can do it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, we share Pierre’s love and wisdom with you. No matter how impossible the search for God may seem at times, if you see your soul embraced in His light with enough concentration and aspiration, you will be able to achieve that which you most ardently seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy and love from Assisi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
