<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>memory on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/memory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in memory on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/memory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>“I Remember!”</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/i-remember/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/i-remember/</guid>
      <description>I read an intriguing article recently about scientists that are doing cutting-edge research on how memory works. Their focus is not the typical one on why memory loss occurs, but rather on why memory exists at all. In other words, these researchers are trying to discover what the mechanism is that holds and releases our memories.
We’ve all had the experience of remembering events, names, or faces from our daily life, but usually we take this ability for granted.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I read an intriguing article recently about scientists that are doing cutting-edge research on how memory works. Their focus is not the typical one on why memory loss occurs, but rather on why memory exists at all. In other words, these researchers are trying to discover what the mechanism is that holds and releases our memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all had the experience of remembering events, names, or faces from our daily life, but usually we take this ability for granted. I often enjoy trying to recall some trivial piece of information that I can’t quite access in my mind. If I sit quietly for a period of time, I sense a spark of energy, a neural impulse, starting to surface and move from the subconscious into the conscious realm. Then, like a light turning on in my brain, the answer presents itself in a calm, joyful manner, as if to say, “Ta-da!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes our memories can even predate our present incarnation, and reflect experiences from past lives. Perhaps we meet someone new and feel an instant affinity with them, or we visit a place for the first time and have the feeling that we’ve been there before. There are many documented cases of children clearly remembering from a past incarnation details which, when researched, have proven to be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda writes on the first page of Autobiography of a Yogi, “I find my earliest memories covering the anachronistic features of a previous incarnation. Clear recollections came to me of a distant life, a yogi amidst the Himalayan snows. These glimpses of the past, by some dimensionless link, also afforded me a glimpse of the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important use of memory, then, lies not in summoning up trivial facts, but in remembering the inner journey that we’ve traveled thus far to find God. It’s good to meditate on why you were drawn to the spiritual path, and on the associations you recall from the past. Though we may not consciously remember the connection, the guru-disciple relationship is eternal and guides us from lifetime to lifetime. By evoking this connection, we can draw on our past spiritual development to strengthen our future growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I had had no conscious memory of a connection with my guru, Yoganandaji, once I read his Autobiography I never looked elsewhere for spiritual guidance. Some deeper-than-conscious memory has held me to his teachings for the past fifty-five years, and I am increasingly aware that this has been my ordained path for many lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most powerful episodes from the Autobiography is when Lahiri Mahasaya, a householder working as an accountant for the British in India, is transferred to a remote outpost in the foothills of the Himalayas. Wandering in the hills above Ranikhet one day, he hears someone calling his name, and climbs up to a clearing dotted with caves. There he sees a radiant young man standing before him. Lahiri’s narrative continues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;“Lahiri, surely this cave seems familiar to you?”

As I maintained a bewildered silence, the saint approached and struck me gently on the forehead. At his magnetic touch, a wondrous current swept through my brain, releasing the sweet seed-memories of my previous life.

“I remember!” My voice was half-choked with joyous sobs. “You are my guru Babaji, who has belonged to me always! Scenes of the past arise vividly in my mind; here in this cave I spent many years of my last incarnation!” As ineffable recollections overwhelmed me, I tearfully embraced my master’s feet.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Memory can play a vital role in our search for liberation. Patanjali, the ancient authority on yoga, describes spiritual awakening as smriti, “memory.” We need to remove from our mind the obscuring fog of present identities such as being a man, a woman, an American, or an Indian. Swami Kriyananda wrote, “These waves of outward involvement need to be stilled. Once they become calm, one’s eternal reality is remembered at last.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/i-remember.png&#34;  alt=&#34;i-remember&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s strange to think that what we’ve been seeking has always been within us: the memory of who and what we really are. Yogananda described Self-realization as “the knowing in all parts of body, mind, and soul that you are now in possession of the kingdom of God; that you do not have to pray that it come to you; that God’s omnipresence is your omnipresence; and that all that you need to do is improve your knowing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we “improve our knowing,” the moment will come when we, too, will exclaim, “I remember!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With gratitude for this path to freedom,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Keeps Us Moving Towards God</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god/</guid>
      <description>“The harvest truly is plenteous, but the laborers are few.”
The traditional explanation of these words of Jesus Christ is that he’s urging his disciples to go out and convert people to his teachings. Paramhansa Yogananda interpreted Christ’s words in a different way: Christ was speaking of the inner “harvest” of divine consciousness, which few people actually seek.
Why only a few? Most people aren’t interested in a world beyond the senses.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“The harvest truly is plenteous, but the laborers are few.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional explanation of these words of Jesus Christ is that he’s urging his disciples to go out and convert people to his teachings. Paramhansa Yogananda interpreted Christ’s words in a different way: Christ was speaking of the inner “harvest” of divine consciousness, which few people actually seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why only a few? Most people aren’t interested in a world beyond the senses. Even among those who are seeking higher realities, many are daunted by the commitment and effort that the spiritual path entails. So, what are some things that can help us to keep “working the field” until we can harvest the crop of God-realization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hope&#34;&gt;Hope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within each of us lies a seed of hope that we truly can achieve our spiritual goals. Though the soil of our consciousness may sometimes seem barren and dry, if we nurture this seed, it can keep us going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master said, “I remember the day when for the first time, unlooked-for, from behind the clouds of the drudgery of routine meditating habits, the aurora of bliss suddenly burst upon my consciousness. It surpassed all my expectations. Joy indescribable!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How reassuring to think that Master, in some long-past lifetime, struggled to keep motivated! We, too, must keep alive the spark of hope that we will reach our goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;memory&#34;&gt;Memory&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Patanjali, the ancient authority on yoga, described spiritual awakening as smriti, which means “memory.” There may come moments when we experience a higher level of consciousness that somehow seems familiar. Perhaps it’s a memory from when our soul was in the astral world, or perhaps a higher state of awareness we once held. Whatever the source of this memory, we need to use it as a point of reference in our spiritual journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend shared a true story about a family whose mother had recently given birth to a second child. The older brother, who was about four years old, was jealous of this new “intruder” who was taking away his parent’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The older boy asked his mother if he could be alone with the new baby. Unsure of what the boy had in mind, the mother agreed, but stood listening outside the door of the room. Standing next to the crib where his little brother lay, the boy whispered, “I’m starting to forget what God is like. Can you help me remember?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cling to any memories you may have of God’s presence, and let them lead you forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-promise&#34;&gt;The Promise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a true guru is, in itself, the greatest blessing on our journey toward Self-realization. Inherent in the guru-disciple relationship is the promise that he or she will bring us to God. Master said, “For those who stay in tune to the end, I, or one of the other masters, will be there to usher them into the divine kingdom.” Just as Master did with his guru, Sri Yukteswar, we must hold him to his promise to bring us to God. Our part is to stay in tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;grace&#34;&gt;Grace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the guru’s grace, which transforms our consciousness and frees us from the web of our karma. Swami Kriyananda writes in The New Path of his early days with Master: “Nightly I chanted Master’s translation of a song by the great Bengali saint, Ram Proshad: ‘Will that day come to me when saying, “Mother! Mother!” my eyes will flow with tears?’ Gradually I found myself becoming transformed inwardly. I began to feel I had some cause for self-congratulation, when one day word came to me that Master had been talking with a group of the monks in Encinitas. During the course of the conversation he had remarked lovingly: ‘Look how I have changed Walter [Swamiji]!’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the desire to know God is a manifestation of His grace. A saint once said that our job is to hoist the sails of our boat, but God is the wind that blows us across the ocean of delusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, the laborers may be few, but let’s count ourselves among them. Let’s keep going until, with God’s grace, we reap the harvest of bliss, which, as Master wrote, is “enjoyable beyond imagination of expectancy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Memory</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-power-of-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-power-of-memory/</guid>
      <description>“Many have been My births, O Arjuna, and many also yours. I remember all of Mine, though you remember yours not.” These words from Sri Krishna to his disciple in the Bhagavad Gita show a divine memory of the soul’s eternal nature.
Memory, in its highest expression, is much more than remembering what is on a grocery list. It is the soul’s ability to transcend the limitations of time.
Paramhansa Yogananda spoke of the “easy resurrection of memory” through which he brought to mind past experiences with his guru, Sri Yukteswar.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“Many have been My births, O Arjuna, and many also yours. I remember all of Mine, though you remember yours not.” These words from Sri Krishna to his disciple in the Bhagavad Gita show a divine memory of the soul’s eternal nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memory, in its highest expression, is much more than remembering what is on a grocery list. It is the soul’s ability to transcend the limitations of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda spoke of the “easy resurrection of memory” through which he brought to mind past experiences with his guru, Sri Yukteswar. With a trained and heightened sense of memory, we can meld past, present, and future into the eternal now. Patanjali, the ancient authority on yoga, described spiritual awakening as smriti, which means “memory.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The yogic teachings describe three different levels of our awareness. The &lt;strong&gt;subconscious mind&lt;/strong&gt; is the repository of all of our past experiences, impressions, and thoughts. It’s the archives for our memories, not only of this life, but of all of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;conscious mind&lt;/strong&gt; is the operating system that responds to the details and challenges of daily life. It’s how we solve problems, make decisions, and plan for the future. The conscious mind draws on memories held in the subconscious to inform its decisions, so they work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;superconscious mind&lt;/strong&gt; is our higher, intuitive faculty that allows us to expand our awareness beyond the limitations of the ego. Through it, we can experience our true Self, and ultimately our oneness with God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this description, it’s easy to draw the conclusion that it’s a progression—that all we need to do is focus on the superconscious mind and forget about the “lower” levels of awareness. But it isn’t that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda said something in this regard that has always intrigued me. Superconsciousness, he wrote, is found at the thin line between the conscious and subconscious minds, rather like the horizon line between sea and sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we come to the power and importance of memory. The subconscious is much more than a dreamy, unaware state of hidden compulsions. Rather it’s an intrinsic part of our journey to enlightenment, both because it contains useful lessons from the past, and because it’s not limited to dwelling in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji spoke often about how to develop the power of memory, and how to use it properly. “Memory,” he said, “is that faculty of the conscious mind which, through the help of the subconscious mind, can recall any past conscious experience. Always awake, the subconscious mind is buried beneath the conscious mind, working during sleep and constantly memorizing experiences during the state of wakefulness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In order to perform important duties and recall valuable experiences for daily use, one must be able to work with the material recalled to the conscious mind by the power of memory. The subconscious mind can be trained to recall at will all conscious experiences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some ways Master gives to develop our memory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morning and evening, rap the scalp with the knuckles, then massage it with the fingers as taught in the Energization Exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perform every action with keen attention. Attention is the needle that cuts grooves in the memory cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night, remember in detail everything that happened during the past week. Try also to remember in detail the principal events of the month with regard to your life, your city, your country, and the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going to bed and upon awakening, command your subconscious mind to be attentive to all your activities and to store all valuable experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-power-of-memory.png&#34;  alt=&#34;the power of memory&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the proper use of memory. Yoganandaji said, “Memory was given to us to keep alive only life’s good experiences and lessons. To remember bad experiences and dwell upon them is an abuse of God’s gift to us of memory.” This doesn’t mean that we suppress bad experiences or ignore past mistakes. Rather, we should move on from painful experiences, and concentrate on filling our memory banks with positive, divine recollections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Sri Yukteswar said to a new student who doubted his own worthiness to seek God: “Forget the past. The vanished lives of all men are dark with many shames. . . . Everything in future will improve if you are making a spiritual effort now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what is the best use of this divine gift of memory? Remembering God. As I write this today, it’s the seventy-first anniversary of Yoganandaji’s mahasamadhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honor our great Guru, take some time at this very moment to remember his impact on your life. When was the first time you saw his photo? When did you first read his Autobiography of a Yogi? What was your first impression of it? If you’re a disciple, when did you realize that he was your God-given guru? Sit in stillness with these memories, and try to feel the timeless nature of your bond with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently a friend sent us a description of an experience a direct disciple of Master had with him some decades after his mahasamadhi. Yogananda appeared to him holding a white and gold book in letters of light, entitled The Book of My Life. Master held it, and told him to turn the pages and read from the book. As he turned the pages backward and forward, he saw accounts of his previous and future incarnations, in which his guru was always guiding him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though, like Arjuna, we may not consciously remember our past lives, the eternal love between guru and disciple is always there, just beneath the surface. The more we’re able to access the stored memories of our Guru’s presence, and hold the thought of him in our conscious mind, the more quickly we will be able to realize our oneness with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the joy of remembering God and Guru,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
