<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>consciousness on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/consciousness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in consciousness on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/consciousness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Children of the Light</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/children-of-the-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/children-of-the-light/</guid>
      <description>When Swami Kriyananda wrote the Festival of Light, a ceremony we read each Sunday at Ananda centers, he included an allegory depicting the journey of the soul. It ends with these thrilling words about the purpose of life:
[Evolution] had but this for its design: The birth of life, And, with life’s birth, the dawn of self-awareness: Passage through dim corridors of waking consciousness To emerge at last into infinite light— Into perfect Joy!</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;When Swami Kriyananda wrote the Festival of Light, a ceremony we read each Sunday at Ananda centers, he included an allegory depicting the journey of the soul. It ends with these thrilling words about the purpose of life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Evolution] had but this for its design: The birth of life,
And, with life’s birth, the dawn of self-awareness:
Passage through dim corridors of waking consciousness
To emerge at last into infinite light—
Into perfect Joy!

O Children of Light, forsake the darkness!
Know that, forever, you and He are one!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The theme of the evolution of consciousness is woven repeatedly throughout the great teachings of India. First there is the long, more-or-less automatic, evolution through the reincarnations prior to reaching the human form. This passage through the dim corridors of waking consciousness reaches its pinnacle in the higher animals, who can sometimes demonstrate extraordinary intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a remarkable dog in our family named Nipper. I grew up in Decorah, Iowa, and across from our house was a large park used for picnics by the residents of the town. Many Sundays would find Nipper entertaining large crowds. He had learned how to climb the steep ladder of a ten-foot slide and then slide down. This he would do repeatedly until a big audience had gathered to cheer him on. My brother and I would lurk on the outskirts of the group, secretly proud of our dog, but too embarrassed to publicly reveal our relationship with this shameless exhibitionist.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/children-of-the-light.png&#34;  alt=&#34;children-of-the-light&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Even more remarkable is the story of Koko, a gorilla who could communicate through sign language. She had a vocabulary of more than a thousand words, and understood twice that many. Koko helped people break down the delusion that only humans have intelligence, compassion, and love. Here is a link to a video showing some of her extraordinary interactions, and another to one of her with the actor/comedian, Robin Williams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next major phase of evolutionary development comes when we reach the human form. Now we have an advanced nervous system and, more importantly, an astral spine, including the chakras, which gives us the capacity to achieve enlightenment. With our heightened abilities comes also both the gift and the curse of free will. Our job now is to choose to expand our consciousness and, eventually, dissolve the ego—the sense of separation from God. To accomplish this, we must develop the extraordinary powers of our mind and will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda said, “When the ‘can’t’ disappears from your mind, divine power comes. You have to pour forth will power continuously through constructive actions. When you persist, refusing to accept failure, the object of will must materialize. In that kind of will lies God’s answer, because will comes from God, and continuous will is divine will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This determination of mind and will enables us to fulfill the objects of our desire. At first, being centered in the ego, we seek possessions, pleasure, and power. But as our consciousness evolves, so also does the focus of our desires. Master says that after countless lives we feel an “anguishing monotony”; our search turns inward, and our yearning is for God alone. While it is good to be energetic in our efforts, it is also good to relax and enjoy the process. Divine Mother is lovingly watching over us as we progress from crawling to toddling, walking, running, and, finally, soaring into the skies of awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation, of course, is central, but so is living in joy, love, and service throughout the day. Eventually the self-doubts fade, the “cant’s” disappear, and we actually live the immortal lines that Swamiji wrote: “O Children of Light, forsake the darkness! Know that, forever, you and He are one!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In God’s love and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In My Guru&#39;s Ashram</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/in-my-gurus-ashram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/in-my-gurus-ashram/</guid>
      <description>“If I entered the hermitage in a worried or indifferent frame of mind, my attitude imperceptibly changed. A healing calm descended at mere sight of my guru. Every day with him was a new experience in joy, peace, and wisdom.” So Paramhansa Yogananda describes the years he spent in the ashram of his guru, Swami Sri Yukteswar.
There is so much that we can learn from these few, simple words. The power of the guru to uplift and change our consciousness is not limited to his words or actions.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“If I entered the hermitage in a worried or indifferent frame of mind, my attitude imperceptibly changed. A healing calm descended at mere sight of my guru. Every day with him was a new experience in joy, peace, and wisdom.” So Paramhansa Yogananda describes the years he spent in the ashram of his guru, Swami Sri Yukteswar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much that we can learn from these few, simple words. The power of the guru to uplift and change our consciousness is not limited to his words or actions. The mere sight of Sri Yukteswar had a transforming effect on his young disciple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guru’s consciousness is a catalyst for our spiritual unfoldment. As disciples, our part is to strive to be more in tune and to deepen our efforts to know God. When we’re “worried or indifferent,” or experiencing any number of wrong attitudes, we have the ability to transcend them by tuning in to the guru’s consciousness, which can free us from the mental shackles that keep us bound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But,” you may be thinking, “I haven’t had the blessing of living in my guru’s ashram. I live here in a big city surrounded by materialistic consciousness. What hope is there for me to experience these divine gifts?” I’d like to share two stories of people we know who have “lived” in their guru’s ashram, despite extremely challenging outward circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/in-my-gurus-ashram.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;in-my-gurus-ashram&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first is of our friend Joe Hunt or Jairam, who has spent the last forty years in prison for a crime he didn’t commit. About thirty years ago, Jairam’s mother sent him a copy of Autobiography of a Yogi, which he read eagerly from cover to cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly afterwards, he contacted Ananda to see if it was possible for someone to visit him in prison to teach him how to meditate. Some members were able to do this, and Jairam began meditating every morning and evening on his bunk in his prison cell. After a few years, the prison officials allowed Jairam the use of a small closet as an office for some work he was doing, and it was there that Jyotish initiated him into Kriya Yoga.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can imagine that a prison environment is not ideal for the regular practice of Kriya. But through the pandemic and lockdowns, through illness and isolation, Jairam has spent hours daily meditating and doing his Kriyas. When we’ve visited him over the years, we could feel that he has “lived” in his guru’s ashram despite all the outer challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second story is about an advanced direct disciple of Yoganandaji, Kamala Silva, who spent many years with her guru, and wrote the book The Flawless Mirror. Later in her life, she was diagnosed with Alzheimer’s disease. Having no family to care for her and needing constant supervision, she was moved to an assisted living home. Members from Ananda visited her regularly, and though they expected her to be unhappy living there, they were greatly reassured to see her unwavering joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day a woman from Ananda went to see her, and was shocked to see that Kamala was now sharing a room with another woman whose face had been horribly disfigured by burns from a fire. Our friend thought, “What a pity that Kamala has to look at that damaged face every day.” Kamala, however, remarked, “Have you seen my roommate? Isn’t she beautiful?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was how Kamala saw her—as a reflection of God’s radiant light. She, too, was “living” in her guru’s ashram, there in that small room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope these stories will help you to realize that the doors to this sacred realm are always open. The choice is ours whether we want to dwell there. Living in our guru’s ashram is a state of mind, and much more: It is constantly reaching out for union with God, until we realize that the guru’s ashram has always resided in our own heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these words of Master: “O Spirit, make my soul Thy temple, but make my heart Thy beloved home where Thou wouldst dwell with me in ease and everlasting understanding.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Christmas and Courage</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/christmas-and-courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/christmas-and-courage/</guid>
      <description>Courage is an essential quality, needed for success in both everyday life and spiritual growth. Fortunately, courage is an innate quality of the soul. We cannot avoid the challenges that come to us, because they are drawn by our own karma and the soul’s longing to be free.
Paramhansa Yogananda says it this way: “Every day is a fresh opportunity on the part of the human ego to gather more and more exploits of heroism.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Courage is an essential quality, needed for success in both everyday life and spiritual growth. Fortunately, courage is an innate quality of the soul. We cannot avoid the challenges that come to us, because they are drawn by our own karma and the soul’s longing to be free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda says it this way: “Every day is a fresh opportunity on the part of the human ego to gather more and more exploits of heroism. Meet everybody and every circumstance on the battlefield of life with the courage of a hero and the smile of a conqueror. Whatever comes your way and needs attention must be considered a duty. Duty is not imposed upon man by any super-power. It is the inherent urge of life toward progression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is enlightening to contemplate the examples of great courage displayed in the lives of the great world saviors. Let’s imagine, for a moment, the courage demonstrated in the story of Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary was an unmarried teenage woman in the small village of Nazareth when the angel Gabriel appeared to her and asked her to bear a holy child. Her first act of faith and courage was to say yes to this astounding request. &lt;em&gt;Whatever comes your way and needs attention must be considered a duty.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph, who was betrothed to Mary, had to have the courage to defy the cultural norms of the day and accept her. &lt;em&gt;Every day is a fresh opportunity on the part of the human ego to gather more and more exploits of heroism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/christmas-and-courage.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;christmas and courage&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Courage reveals itself through the inner struggle needed to say yes to whatever comes our way and needs attention. There are many other examples of valor shown by the young holy couple: the difficult circumstances of the birth in a manger, the visitations of angels and the three wise men, and the courage to flee to Egypt in order to save the young savior. As Yogananda puts it, “It takes courage to renounce the known for the unknown.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these last four “Advent blogs” we’ve given a few examples of spiritual qualities, especially courage: Devi’s bravery in accepting a strange stranger into her home and giving him comfort, my challenge that we have the strength to “willingly accept whatever is mine to do,” and Devi’s challenge to have the resolve to forgive and “Bless all who ever harmed you, or ever wished you harm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, then, is a final challenge for this year. Look into your heart and find something that has “come your way, needs attention, and must be considered a duty,” but that you have been avoiding. Take on the challenge, face it head on, and conquer it, freeing yourself from its limiting cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this holy season the Masters are supporting our efforts by sending powerful blessings of grace and courage. These are their Christmas presents to each of us, wrapped in joy and tied with the bow of love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devi and I also send you our loving thoughts and encouragement, that you may experience the Christ consciousness during this season and always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
