<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>karma on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/karma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in karma on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/karma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Nail in the Board</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/the-nail-in-the-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/the-nail-in-the-board/</guid>
      <description>All of us have habits or tendencies that bring us suffering. Though repeatedly we may try to change these patterns, they follow us around like a cloud of gnats. This is the result of the law of karma: Every action we take is a cause that has an effect, an effect that sometimes follows us even from lifetime to lifetime. These effects can be good or bad, freeing or binding, depending on the action involved.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;All of us have habits or tendencies that bring us suffering. Though repeatedly we may try to change these patterns, they follow us around like a cloud of gnats. This is the result of the law of karma: Every action we take is a cause that has an effect, an effect that sometimes follows us even from lifetime to lifetime. These effects can be good or bad, freeing or binding, depending on the action involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When confronted with the effects of our past bad actions, how should we respond? It is natural, and good, to do what we can to minimize those effects. If we have poor health, we can take steps to improve it such as seeing a doctor, taking medication, improving our diet, or exercising appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In themselves, however, steps like these will not eliminate the underlying cause. To do that, as anyone aspiring to soul freedom must, we need to use the power of our mind to resist old patterns. At the same time, we should seek to replace bad habits with good ones. It’s like putting up a protective cloth over our mental garden so that the seeds of bad karma cannot germinate. Past karma then has much less power to harm us. Moreover, those karmic seeds, starved of nourishment from repetition of past bad actions, wither and die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most effective of all is to meditate. Each time we meditate deeply, beneficial changes take place in the patterns of our brain. Here is a meditation technique that Paramhansa Yoganandaji gives us to destroy the seeds of past karma.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/the-nail-in-the-board.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;the-nail-in-the-board&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First, meditate upon the thought “I and my Father are one,” trying as you do so to feel great peace and joy in your heart. When joy comes, mentally affirm: “Father, Thou art with me. I command Thy power within me to cauterize my brain cells of wrong habits and past seed tendencies.” Finally, affirm and pray: “I command my brain cells to change, to destroy the grooves of bad habits that have made a puppet out of me. Lord, burn them up in Thy divine light.” Do this technique repeatedly with great concentration, and over time you will feel ever freer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda gave us an image that is very helpful in destroying the effects of our past actions. He said rooting out old karma is like trying to pull a nail out of a board. Using the prongs of a hammer, we keep pulling, but cannot know how much of the nail remains in the board. We do not know when, but one day, after continued effort, the nail pops out. The karma is over, and we are free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of ours recently told us an illustrative story. He was directing a team of people on a new project. Unfortunately, one person on the team was resistant to our friend’s guidance; he was openly critical and challenging, even hostile. Our friend reacted negatively, and though he didn’t show it, was resentful. Some old karma had come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praying deeply to God to be able to lead the team impartially and effectively, our friend was preparing to meet with the team. Just as he was getting in the car, he felt the karma lift: “like a nail coming out of a board,” he said. He felt inwardly free, and the project moved forward harmoniously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda wrote, “Don’t blame God or anyone else if you are suffering from disease, financial problems, or emotional upsets. You created the cause of the problem in the past and must make a greater determination to uproot it now.” So let’s face the self-created challenges that come to us in life, until, with indomitable will, we realize that nothing can keep us bound in our journey towards soul freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School&#39;s in Session</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/schools-in-session/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/schools-in-session/</guid>
      <description>In most parts of the world, the school year is about to begin. Children are assembling their new backpacks, books, and clothes for the year ahead. New subjects and tests loom on the horizon. It’s an exciting time for children and their parents, though perhaps for different reasons.
Here in Assisi we were recently discussing why people on the spiritual path have so many tests. It’s for the same reasons that schoolchildren do: to see how much we’ve learned and discover what things we still need to work on.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In most parts of the world, the school year is about to begin. Children are assembling their new backpacks, books, and clothes for the year ahead. New subjects and tests loom on the horizon. It’s an exciting time for children and their parents, though perhaps for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in Assisi we were recently discussing why people on the spiritual path have so many tests. It’s for the same reasons that schoolchildren do: to see how much we’ve learned and discover what things we still need to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For we are all learning. And the School of Soul Evolution, in which we’re enrolled, has no summer vacations. It lasts from incarnation to incarnation, and continues until we have learned the karmic lessons we must in order to be free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So tests often come to devotees to raise to conscious awareness the hidden karmic patterns that cause us suffering. The tests reveal both small and big karmic blind spots, and depending on the degree of misery they bring us, we’re motivated to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Italian friend of ours (we’ll call her Maria) told us a story that illustrates this point. Along with others from Assisi, she had traveled to India to visit holy sites and to see Swami Kriyananda. At the end of the trip, everyone was packing for the return flight to Italy early the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because she had bought many gifts for friends, Maria was worried that her suitcases would exceed the weight limit. Her mind began to whirl. “Oh, dear,” she fretted, “what if they don’t allow my bags on the plane, and I get separated from my friends? What if I miss the flight, and get stranded at the airport?” As the day wore on, she grew increasingly anxious, until she was in a state of near panic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then her phone rang. It was Lila, Swamiji’s cook, saying that he wanted Maria to come over to talk. Hurriedly, she made her way to his home, and they had a brief, loving exchange. Then he said, “I have a number of salt lamps that I’d like you to bring back to Italy for me. Can you fit them into your suitcase?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swallowing her anxiety, she smiled and replied, “Of course, Swamiji.” She returned to her hotel room even more anxious than before, but somehow managed to cram the heavy lamps into her bags. Now she was certain that they exceeded the weight limit and that impending disaster loomed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you can probably guess the rest of the story. At the airport the next morning, when the ticket agent put her luggage on the scale, it was indeed well over the weight limit. Without a word, he attached the requisite tags to her bags and sent them down the conveyor belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She could only smile at the panic she’d suffered so unnecessarily. Upon reflection, she saw a pattern: How often she had allowed needless worries about the future to destroy her peace of mind. It was the heightened example of this test that helped her see the karmic tendencies of fear and anxiety that often plagued her. More importantly, it helped her see how to overcome such trials with courage and faith.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/schools-in-session.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;schools in session&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our tests come not to punish us, but to show us in bold relief where we are in error, and how to correct it. Master said, “All of life’s experiences are for our education and entertainment.” “But,” he added ruefully, “how few are either educated or entertained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So devotees are, in fact, often tested more frequently than most others, because we’ve asked God to guide us to freedom. And as we continue our education in the School of Soul Evolution, we arrive finally, at the end of each incarnation, at what Swami Kriyananda called “the final exam.” In his beautiful essay by that name, he wrote: “The most important moment of life is, in a very true sense, its last moment. For death is when we take our final exam. The thought uppermost in the mind at that time will determine whether our future takes us upward, or sideways, or downward: upward, toward greater spiritual clarity and freedom; sideways, toward further involvement in desires and worldly attachments; or (the least fortunate) downward, toward greater darkness, confusion, and ignorance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, friends, keep this in mind: Every test that comes, if we embrace it as an opportunity to overcome past karma, brings us closer to final freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Makes Us Happy</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-makes-us-happy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-makes-us-happy/</guid>
      <description>Ananda has a dear friend, Sri D. R. Kaarthikeyan. Swami Kriyananda considered him to be “my Indian brother” and, indeed, their camaraderie made them seem like two brothers. Kaarthikeyanji is a pivotal member of the Board of Directors of not only Ananda in India, but many other spiritual and humanitarian organizations as well. One of the ways this compassionate soul helps mankind is to send out inspiring and uplifting material to his vast mailing list.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Ananda has a dear friend, Sri D. R. Kaarthikeyan. Swami Kriyananda considered him to be “my Indian brother” and, indeed, their camaraderie made them seem like two brothers. Kaarthikeyanji is a pivotal member of the Board of Directors of not only Ananda in India, but many other spiritual and humanitarian organizations as well. One of the ways this compassionate soul helps mankind is to send out inspiring and uplifting material to his vast mailing list. Here is an inspiring piece we received from him last week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indian billionaire with a wealth of 291 billion dollars, Ratan Tata, was asked by a radio presenter in a phone interview: Sir, when were you the happiest in your life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ratan replied : I went through four stages of happiness in my life and finally I understood the meaning of true happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step was to accumulate wealth and resources. But that time I didn’t get the happiness I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came the second stage of accumulating valuable objects. But I realized that the effect of this is also temporary, and the shine of jewelry doesn’t last long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came the third leg of big projects. We owned 95% of the oil reserves in India and Africa. Also owned the largest steel plant in India and Asia. But here I did not reach the happiness I imagined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth step came when my friend asked me to buy wheelchairs for children with disabilities. Approximately 200 children. Upon the recommendation of a friend, I immediately bought them. But the friend insisted that I go with him and give them to the kids. Ready and at it, out there giving these kids wheelchairs with my own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw a strange glow of happiness on the faces of these children. I saw everyone just sitting in their wheelchairs, moving and playing. It was like they came to a picnic spot and shared their winning prize. I felt so happy inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I decided to leave, one of the kids grabbed me by my feet. I tried to slowly release my legs, but the child looked in front of me and squeezed them even harder. So I leaned over and said, “Kid, you need something else?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This child’s reaction not only shocked me, but completely changed my outlook on life. This child said, “I want to remember your face so that when I see you in Heaven, I can recognize you and thank you again!!!”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-makes-us-happy.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what makes us happy&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What makes us happy? There is a deep spiritual truth: It says that happiness increases as our consciousness rises and expands, and dwindles as it falls and contracts. That is why we say “up in heaven” and “down in hell.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Tata chased personal wealth, possessions, and power his consciousness shrank, and lasting happiness eluded him. But by thinking of others and acting altruistically, his consciousness expanded, and he was able to find sustained happiness. The law of expansion and contraction is one of the hidden laws of creation. It works because we are all interconnected and interdependent, and this is why a fundamental teaching for all the world’s faiths is, “Do unto others as you would have them do unto you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day we are given opportunities to put this into practice. The choice is straightforward: expand and be happy, or contract and be sad. Helping others will bring good karma to both them and us. Let’s spend more time giving out Divine Mother’s wheelchairs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramhansa Yogananda puts it beautifully in one of his prayer-demands: “I loved many things only to find that my true craving was for Thee alone. Come to me now! Be with me always!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Ways to Outwit Karma</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/four-ways-to-outwit-karma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/four-ways-to-outwit-karma/</guid>
      <description>Karma is one of the fundamental laws of the universe. Basically, it states that every thought, feeling, and action has a consequence. In the Bible, it says, “As you sow, so shall you reap.”
Once set in motion, there is normally no way to avoid the karma of past actions. But we can do much to change how severe the consequences will be. Sri Yukteswar said that the past lives of all men are dark with many shames.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Karma is one of the fundamental laws of the universe. Basically, it states that every thought, feeling, and action has a consequence. In the Bible, it says, “As you sow, so shall you reap.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once set in motion, there is normally no way to avoid the karma of past actions. But we can do much to change how severe the consequences will be. Sri Yukteswar said that the past lives of all men are dark with many shames. But that everything in the future will improve if we are making the right spiritual efforts now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are four ways to outwit our karmic consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move Away from Bad Behavior:&lt;/strong&gt; Every action or thought is like a bolt of energy. The energy once sent out will inevitably return. If we shout at someone in anger, we will often, if not always immediately, get an angry retort in return. Karmic paybacks are life’s way of teaching us the consequences of our actions and nudging us toward alignment with God’s laws. In this case, the returning karma is meant to teach us not to act out in anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bolt of angry retribution headed our way is like a car approaching us on a one-lane road. If we are still acting in the same deluded way, there will be a head-on crash. But now imagine that you have changed, and not only are no longer acting with anger, but instead are now patient and helpful when confronted. You are now moving in the same direction as your “car-mic” retribution, and the result may be just a little tap on the rear to remind you to keep making the right spiritual effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we learn to head the right way? First, become aware of how you are behaving. Awareness always precedes action. Next, take responsibility for your behavior. Finally, put out energy in the opposite direction, the direction your karma wants to push you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serve Others:&lt;/strong&gt; Service is one of the best ways to overcome karma, which is always initiated by self-interest. Simply put, when we think about ourselves, we end up creating bad karma. When we forget ourselves and think about helping others, we become freer and happier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are self-involved, even a whisper of criticism can be devastating. When our hearts are strong and expanded through thinking of others, even an angry tirade can be shrugged off or provide an opportunity to help the irate person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meditate and Do Pranayama:&lt;/strong&gt; Meditation is the fastest way to become free of ego, the root cause of all karma. All the whirlpools of karma reside in the astral spine. Meditation can neutralize those vortices. Paramhansa Yogananda said that each Kriya is the equivalent of a whole year of right living. Day by day, meditation by meditation, our astral spine is cleared of all destructive karmic tendencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may have innumerable seeds of karmic tendencies waiting for the right circumstances to sprout. But pranayama, especially Kriya Yoga, fills the spine with positive magnetism and burns up the seeds before they can be planted.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/four-ways-to-outwit-karma.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;fours ways to outwit karma&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attunement with a Guru:&lt;/strong&gt; A guru will take away much of our karma if we stay attuned. A good friend had a fascinating dream. He was walking along a beach and came upon a huge pile of sticky tar, which he knew was his past bad karma. His task was to eliminate it, but all he had for the job was a little toy plastic pail and shovel. After a great deal of effort he finally succeeded in filling his bucket one time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he began to despair of ever finishing the job, he heard a loud noise coming from the back of the pile. Curious, he went around and found Yogananda driving a tractor with a large scoop on the front. Master had a huge grin on his face as he dug into the mound of tar again and again and dumped the loads into the ocean to be dissolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rich man can easily pay the debts of a wayward child. Such is the power of attunement with a God-realized guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with a fascinating answer that Swami Kriyananda gave when asked how we can tell the difference between good and bad karma. He said good karma takes us closer to God, while bad karma takes us away. Sometimes unpleasant karma, like bitter medicine, is the best thing for us. We don’t have to enjoy it, but we would be wise to swallow it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
