<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>liberation on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/liberation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in liberation on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/liberation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Finding Your Dharma</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-your-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/finding-your-dharma/</guid>
      <description>This week we’ve been having a wonderful gathering for Inner Renewal Retreat, whose theme has been “Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation.” The Temple of Light here at Ananda’s Expanding Light Retreat has been packed with several hundred residents and guests; another three thousand five hundred people are enrolled online. (If you’re interested in watching the classes and other events, you can still receive a free link.)
One of the most frequently asked questions on this topic is “How do I know what my dharma is?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;This week we’ve been having a wonderful gathering for Inner Renewal Retreat, whose theme has been “Embrace Your Dharma—Your Path to Liberation.” The Temple of Light here at Ananda’s Expanding Light Retreat has been packed with several hundred residents and guests; another three thousand five hundred people are enrolled online. (If you’re interested in watching the classes and other events, you can still receive a free link.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most frequently asked questions on this topic is “How do I know what my dharma is?” Let’s talk about two different aspects of this: the longer rhythms or patterns that govern our lifetime as a whole, and the situations that arise from moment to moment as our life unfolds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While our ultimate destiny is Self-realization, there is also the dharma of any particular life as determined by our past karma. Swami Kriyananda wrote: “The duty [dharma] of every man is that which is particularly his own, ordained for him by karmic bonds he himself has forged, and must untie to release himself from attachment to ego.” Each one of us has a unique journey to soul freedom through the maze of our past karma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once many years ago after a Kriya Initiation, Swamiji shared with a small group an amazing experience he had had during the ceremony. “As each person came up for the blessing,” he told us, “I could feel his unique path to liberation.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/finding-your-dharma.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;finding-your-dharma&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For devotees, the dharmic life pattern is something we should patiently allow to unfold, without forcing the circumstances and without undo anxiety. I had a good friend who was torn over the issue of whether she should marry or become a monastic. After a year of stressing over this, she finally asked Swamiji what he felt her dharma was. His response was: “Your karma could go either way. Let’s see what happens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So she waited. After five years, she had become unattached on a deep level. By that point, she was ready to accept her dharma (whatever it might be), and get on with her life. Again, she asked Swamiji what her dharma was, and this time he answered, “You should marry.” Circumstances were such that she was happily married within a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Master’s disciples said, “Your own will surely come to you. In fact, you cannot avoid it.” Our dharma for a lifetime—especially the outward role we are to play—is most often determined by past karmic forces that we cannot control, and often are not even aware of consciously. But if we give our life to God in discipleship, service, and devotion, and wait patiently for His guidance, the right life path will open before us. The challenge is in following our dharma once it becomes clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For there is the problem of discerning dharmic responses to the myriad of questions that arise in daily life: What, in each case, is the right action to take? The best place to start is to tackle the problems closest at hand using these criteria: 1) address the situation with the best energy you have; 2) do it without attachment to the results; and 3) ask for the inner guidance of the guru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master gave us this marvelous prayer: “I will reason, I will will, I will act, but guide Thou my reason, will, and activity to the right path in everything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with the battles you are confident of winning. For example, if you are a lazy person, it would be unwise to decide, “I’m going to run a marathon and will get up every day at 6:00 a.m. to run for an hour.” It would be much better to start with a smaller goal that you can accomplish: “I’m going to walk for thirty minutes three days a week.” Conquer the negative habit of laziness by taking doable steps, and keep building on your strengths, until one day you may run that marathon. This is the way of victory over past karma by practicing right action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna says: “To do one’s own duty even unsuccessfully is better than to do someone else’s successfully.” (3:35) It is important, therefore, if we are to discover and follow our unique path of dharma, that we not be attached to the results of our actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad karma is merely energy that has been misdirected. Through meditation, right action, and divine grace, we can follow our dharma, break the bondage of karma, and achieve freedom in God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With enthusiasm and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Can We Give?</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-can-we-give/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-can-we-give/</guid>
      <description>There is a lovely song based on a poem by Paramhansa Yogananda. The words are:
I have nothing to offer Thee, For all things are Thine. I grieve not that I cannot give, For nothing is mine, nothing is mine. Here I lay at Thy feet, O Lord, My limbs, my life, my thoughts, and my speech, For they are Thine. For they are Thine. The heart of a devotee naturally overflows with the desire to help others.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;There is a lovely song based on a poem by Paramhansa Yogananda. The words are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I have nothing to offer Thee,
For all things are Thine.
I grieve not that I cannot give,
For nothing is mine, nothing is mine.

Here I lay at Thy feet, O Lord,
My limbs, my life, my thoughts, and my speech,
For they are Thine. For they are Thine.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The heart of a devotee naturally overflows with the desire to help others. In fact, this yearning is one of the first signs of a refined consciousness. In a sense it is that impulse that brought this world into existence in the first place. God, the only thing that really exists, is ever-existing, ever-conscious, ever-new bliss. That bliss is ever expanding and, as Swami Kriyananda put it so simply and beautifully, “It is the nature of joy to want to share itself with others. So God created a multitude of seemingly separate souls so that He could share His bliss.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each soul, being an extension of God, shares this impulse. But what do we really have to give? The first things that pop into our mind are tangible offerings: our service, our possessions, our wealth. Even a rank materialist is willing to share these, but usually just with his immediate family. This limitation is a condition that Paramhansa Yogananda called, “Us four, and no more.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master taught that one pathway to liberation is continually to enlarge the circle of those whom we think of as our own: first to friends and loved ones; then to neighbors; then to our country. But we must keep expanding our sympathies in wider and wider circles, until we see the whole world as our very own family. Ah, what a different planet this would be, one filled with peace and abundance, if people could follow that simple advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, this ideal won’t become worldwide during our present materialistic age. But you and I don’t have to be caught by the delusions of mass consciousness. We don’t have to wait for others to change. We, ourselves, can live that way now. To do so will put us in alignment with the will of God, and will bring light into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, for final liberation, a still higher way of giving is needed. We need to break the delusion of the ego, that we are this body and this personality. We need to express our eternal, soul qualities. Not long before his passing, Swami Kriyananda gave some invaluable advice to a friend, Nayaswami Aditya, one of the leaders of Ananda’s work in India. Aditya trained as a medical doctor, having grown up in the household of a physician who was always eager and willing to help alleviate suffering. And this attitude of service was passed down in his children, all of whom became in time doctors themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-can-we-give.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what-can-we-give&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One day Dr. Aditya, still active as a surgeon at the time, asked Swamiji what more he could do to help people. Swami told him, “The greatest thing you can do is to give people your bliss.” What deep and precious advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as we think of ourselves as physical beings, we should act in such a way as to expand our consciousness. It is important to share with others. But anything we give on a physical level is ephemeral and will pass away sooner or later. If, however, we give the gift of God’s eternal qualities, those offerings will last forever. No matter whether we are rich or poor, young or old, we each possess as our very own inheritance an endless supply of bliss, and love, and peace. When we connect with those in the silence of meditation, and then give them away to others, God sees that we are acting as His channels and gives us even more to distribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we become that which flows through us. Then, we can say in all sincerity, “I have nothing of my own to give, but through me YOU can give all the priceless gifts for which every soul yearns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the light of God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
