<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/energy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/energy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Stranger in a Strange Land</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/stranger-in-a-strange-land/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/stranger-in-a-strange-land/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago Jyotish and I led the Astral Ascension Ceremony for a dear friend, Judy Fox, who passed away recently. Judy was part of a small team, as were we, that Swami Kriyananda sent to Italy in the early 1980s to help start Ananda’s work there.
We landed in Northern Italy near Lake Como at a lovely summer villa that belonged to a friend and fellow disciple. Sound idyllic?</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago Jyotish and I led the Astral Ascension Ceremony for a dear friend, Judy Fox, who passed away recently. Judy was part of a small team, as were we, that Swami Kriyananda sent to Italy in the early 1980s to help start Ananda’s work there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We landed in Northern Italy near Lake Como at a lovely summer villa that belonged to a friend and fellow disciple. Sound idyllic? Perhaps, but as the months passed and temperatures dropped, living in a summer house with little heat during the coldest winter in Europe in one hundred years was a huge challenge for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, living in a different culture from what we were accustomed to, knowing very few people on whom to call, and having none of our usual comforts all reinforced the feeling that we were “stranieri,” foreigners. As time passed, we felt more and more like “strangers in a strange land” (Exodus 2:22).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamiji knew all of us well, however, and felt that we had the strength and commitment not only to survive the challenges, but to grow spiritually in the process. And so it proved. We soon realized we had one of two choices: 1) to let our energy drop, and sink into loneliness and depression; or 2) to raise our energy level and deepen our faith in God’s guiding presence with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together our small team consciously chose the second option: to keep our spirits uplifted and to look for ways to share Master’s great teachings with seekers in Europe. From these humble beginnings, Ananda now has a thriving international community outside of Assisi, Italy, as well as centers spreading throughout Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our friend Judy, who was there that first winter, had an especially joyful and ebullient nature, and helped us all to stay positive. At her Astral Ascension Ceremony, her partner of twenty-seven years, Ric, shared with us a beautiful story about her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judy met him shortly after returning to California from Italy, and told him about Master’s path and Ananda. Then (after knowing Ric for only ten days) she told him that he should visit Assisi, because: “The farther you are from home, the closer you are to God.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With those simple words, Judy captured our whole experience of that difficult first winter. With nothing familiar from which to draw, we had to tune in to another form of comfort and sense of “home”: God’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This world—which alternates between seeming welcoming and familiar to seeming unloving and foreign—can never really be our home. Why? Because on the deepest level, it’s only an impermanent illusion. We are strangers in a strange land. Our true soul home can only be found by reuniting with God, from Whom we sprang lifetimes ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So remember, when you’re going through a difficult time outside of your comfort zone and the world seems inimical and unwelcoming, think of Judy’s mantra: &lt;strong&gt;“The farther you are from home, the closer you are to God.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at those other times when life is going all your way? Recall Judy’s mantra to mind just as forcefully then. Will you rest comfortably in all that’s familiar? Will you, in Yogananda’s immortal words, “bask in the familial warmth”? Or will you embrace self-expansion and as yet uncharted waters? This choice is always before us.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/stranger-in-a-strange-land.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;stranger in a strange land&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with these stanzas from Swamiji’s beautiful song, “God’s Call Within,” which captures the essence of our soul’s search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.


Friend, how long will you wander?
Friend, as long as you seek your home
In a land where all are strangers,
Love locks her door.


Turn, turn, turn within:
In silence of soul, in cave of love
Find My abode.
 

Listen! Listen!
Whispering within your soul:
Hints of laughter, hints of joy;
Sweet songs of sadness, of quenchless yearning
For the Light,
For My love, your true home.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your fellow wanderer,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discontent to Some Extent</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/discontent-to-some-extent/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/discontent-to-some-extent/</guid>
      <description>During a recent talk in Bangalore, India, I said that most people are “discontent to some extent.” Devi liked the catchy phrase so much that she even wryly suggested we should print it on T-shirts. Personally, I think that’s going too far, but it does make a good topic for a blog.
Poetically speaking, God sings the universe into existence by chanting AUM, the vibration of duality. One of these dualities is likes and dislikes.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;During a recent talk in Bangalore, India, I said that most people are “discontent to some extent.” Devi liked the catchy phrase so much that she even wryly suggested we should print it on T-shirts. Personally, I think that’s going too far, but it does make a good topic for a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poetically speaking, God sings the universe into existence by chanting AUM, the vibration of duality. One of these dualities is likes and dislikes. As Sri Yukteswar put it, “The mere existence of a physical body signifies that its existence is made possible by unfulfilled desires.” Poetically speaking, discontent is the glue that holds creation together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the fastest (and happiest) paths to Self-realization is simply to accept things as they are. We spend so much time and effort pushing away things in the world that don’t fit our particular bundle of likes and dislikes. Wanting things to be other than they are drains us of our energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swami Kriyananda tells of an interesting revelation in this regard. This incident took place when he was living in San Francisco. His schedule was intense, with classes in different locations every evening as well as writing, correspondence, and counseling required during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One evening he was scheduled to teach a class on “Energy and Energization” in Palo Alto, California. He stopped at his parents’ house, which happened to be close to the classroom. His mother took one look at him and said, “You look exhausted. You just have to cancel that class tonight.” He knew that wasn’t possible, but compromised by taking a rest.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/discontent-to-some-extent.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;discontent to some extent&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead of falling asleep, he began to think of all the obligations that were sapping his strength. He realized that the problem wasn’t the actual work itself but rather the energy drained by his mental resistance. One by one he visualized each obligation: the classes and commute time, the correspondence, the writing, the many people asking for his guidance. As each one arose, he deeply accepted it. As he did so his energy flooded back. When he emerged from the bedroom his mother remarked, “Oh, you look so much better! You must have had a good nap.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working with him at the time as his assistant, and he told me about the experience the next day. He concluded the story with a twinkle in his eye and the comment, “It was the best class on energy I have ever given.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t just an interesting story but a life lesson. Who among us hasn’t felt resentful about our responsibilities? And, who among us hasn’t felt drained because of inner resistance? This very morning in meditation I was doing what Swamiji did that evening so many years ago. I was deeply accepting that which God has given me to do. And, like Swamiji, I emerged from our meditation room with much greater energy and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s use this holy advent season as a chance to develop new qualities and re-energize our spiritual life. Last week Devi wrote, &lt;em&gt;“I invite you to join me in this challenge for the rest of 2022: to feel God’s love flowing through you in each moment of the day. This is the greatest gift you can give to the world. And who knows? God may come in hidden form to receive it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I invite you to add this challenge. From now until the end of the year practice this: “I will willingly accept whatever is given to me as mine to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we do this we will become “more content to a great extent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
