<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>grace on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/grace/</link>
    <description>Recent content in grace on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/grace/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What Keeps Us Moving Towards God</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god/</guid>
      <description>“The harvest truly is plenteous, but the laborers are few.”
The traditional explanation of these words of Jesus Christ is that he’s urging his disciples to go out and convert people to his teachings. Paramhansa Yogananda interpreted Christ’s words in a different way: Christ was speaking of the inner “harvest” of divine consciousness, which few people actually seek.
Why only a few? Most people aren’t interested in a world beyond the senses.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;“The harvest truly is plenteous, but the laborers are few.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional explanation of these words of Jesus Christ is that he’s urging his disciples to go out and convert people to his teachings. Paramhansa Yogananda interpreted Christ’s words in a different way: Christ was speaking of the inner “harvest” of divine consciousness, which few people actually seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why only a few? Most people aren’t interested in a world beyond the senses. Even among those who are seeking higher realities, many are daunted by the commitment and effort that the spiritual path entails. So, what are some things that can help us to keep “working the field” until we can harvest the crop of God-realization?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hope&#34;&gt;Hope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within each of us lies a seed of hope that we truly can achieve our spiritual goals. Though the soil of our consciousness may sometimes seem barren and dry, if we nurture this seed, it can keep us going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master said, “I remember the day when for the first time, unlooked-for, from behind the clouds of the drudgery of routine meditating habits, the aurora of bliss suddenly burst upon my consciousness. It surpassed all my expectations. Joy indescribable!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How reassuring to think that Master, in some long-past lifetime, struggled to keep motivated! We, too, must keep alive the spark of hope that we will reach our goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;memory&#34;&gt;Memory&lt;/h2&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;what-keeps-us-moving-towards-god&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Patanjali, the ancient authority on yoga, described spiritual awakening as smriti, which means “memory.” There may come moments when we experience a higher level of consciousness that somehow seems familiar. Perhaps it’s a memory from when our soul was in the astral world, or perhaps a higher state of awareness we once held. Whatever the source of this memory, we need to use it as a point of reference in our spiritual journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend shared a true story about a family whose mother had recently given birth to a second child. The older brother, who was about four years old, was jealous of this new “intruder” who was taking away his parent’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The older boy asked his mother if he could be alone with the new baby. Unsure of what the boy had in mind, the mother agreed, but stood listening outside the door of the room. Standing next to the crib where his little brother lay, the boy whispered, “I’m starting to forget what God is like. Can you help me remember?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cling to any memories you may have of God’s presence, and let them lead you forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-promise&#34;&gt;The Promise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a true guru is, in itself, the greatest blessing on our journey toward Self-realization. Inherent in the guru-disciple relationship is the promise that he or she will bring us to God. Master said, “For those who stay in tune to the end, I, or one of the other masters, will be there to usher them into the divine kingdom.” Just as Master did with his guru, Sri Yukteswar, we must hold him to his promise to bring us to God. Our part is to stay in tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;grace&#34;&gt;Grace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the guru’s grace, which transforms our consciousness and frees us from the web of our karma. Swami Kriyananda writes in The New Path of his early days with Master: “Nightly I chanted Master’s translation of a song by the great Bengali saint, Ram Proshad: ‘Will that day come to me when saying, “Mother! Mother!” my eyes will flow with tears?’ Gradually I found myself becoming transformed inwardly. I began to feel I had some cause for self-congratulation, when one day word came to me that Master had been talking with a group of the monks in Encinitas. During the course of the conversation he had remarked lovingly: ‘Look how I have changed Walter [Swamiji]!’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the desire to know God is a manifestation of His grace. A saint once said that our job is to hoist the sails of our boat, but God is the wind that blows us across the ocean of delusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my friends, the laborers may be few, but let’s count ourselves among them. Let’s keep going until, with God’s grace, we reap the harvest of bliss, which, as Master wrote, is “enjoyable beyond imagination of expectancy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your friend in God,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take That Step!</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/take-that-step/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/take-that-step/</guid>
      <description>Driving on a stormy night to an uncertain destination is a daunting experience for all of us. It’s also a perfect analogy for the challenges on our spiritual journey.
First, we get in our car and are glad for the moment to be out of the storm. (This is our first step on the path to God, in which we have a longing to escape the turmoil of life and find peace of mind.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Driving on a stormy night to an uncertain destination is a daunting experience for all of us. It’s also a perfect analogy for the challenges on our spiritual journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we get in our car and are glad for the moment to be out of the storm. (&lt;em&gt;This is our first step on the path to God, in which we have a longing to escape the turmoil of life and find peace of mind.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we’re uncertain about driving in the storm. We even begin to question if getting to the destination is worth it, so we decide to cancel the trip. (&lt;em&gt;Some new seekers lose heart before they begin, and decide that the unknown destination of finding God and the demands of the trip are too much. They quit before they’ve even begun.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, if we’re plucky enough, we summon up the courage to start the car, turn on the headlights, and check our GPS unit to get an idea of where we’re going. (&lt;em&gt;We generate the initial energy to start the journey, then put out the positive energy that enables us to find a true guide—the guru—who can show us where we’re headed and how to get there.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the journey begins. Since the headlights enable us to see only a little distance ahead, we proceed slowly and cautiously. We hope that the road will become clearer as we continue driving. (&lt;em&gt;Each step on the spiritual path is revealed as we approach it. The techniques and teachings come into focus as we proceed.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, the storm seems to be letting up, and we begin to relax and enjoy the journey. As we draw closer to our destination, streetlights appear to guide us, the road gets wider, and the signs for our journey’s end are more frequent. (&lt;em&gt;As we continue towards our spiritual goal, the dark karma that obscured our way seems to lift. Our inner path to God becomes more brightly illumined, and reaching Him begins to seem possible.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as we approach our destination, we begin to speed up, because we see that we’re nearing the journey’s end. With a sigh of relief, we realize that the goal that for so long seemed obscure is now familiar and welcoming. (&lt;em&gt;Though the spiritual journey is seemingly filled with perils and uncertainty, as we continue the momentum builds. We realize that there was always an Unseen Passenger in the back seat silently guiding our way to our true home in God.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/take-that-step.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;take that step&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To complete the journey, we must find the faith to trust that we are never alone on the spiritual path, and that God’s grace is always with us. But we must also have the courage to take the next step, and then the next, until we arrive at our goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Yoganandaji was correcting a disciple for some behavior that needed changing. The man tried to justify himself by answering, “That’s easy for you to say—you’re a master.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoganandaji replied with great force: “And what do you think made me a master?” In other words, it’s by facing our challenges and overcoming them that we attain soul freedom. The journey may seem dark and daunting, but if we take each step in front of us, with God’s grace, we will get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master, who has the soul of a spiritual warrior, wrote a wonderful poem, “My Soul Is Marching On.” It’s filled with the determination and power to reach the journey’s end. As you read these stanzas excerpted from the poem, try to visualize him in armor of gleaming light holding a flaming sword to guide us forward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The flowers bloomed, then hid in gloom,
The bounty of the trees did cease;
Colossal men have come and gone,
But still my soul is marching on!

Darkness, death, and failures vied;
To block my path they fiercely tried.
My fight with jealous Nature’s strong,
But still my soul is marching on!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take the next step with determination, friend. Marching bravely we will reach—each one of us—the journey’s end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Devi&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Intuition Be Your Guide</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/let-intuition-be-your-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/let-intuition-be-your-guide/</guid>
      <description>I’ve come across some amazing and amusing examples of advanced souls being guided by intuition. These stories are from a book of letters from Paramhansa Yogananda to his second-most-advanced disciple, Yogacharya Oliver Black, My Dear Oliver. Here is the story of how Yogacharya met his guru:
Master said he was in Washington, D.C., and he was on his way back home to Los Angeles. A straight line for his travel would have been through Columbus, Ohio, but he said the inner voice/Divine Mother told him to come to Detroit.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I’ve come across some amazing and amusing examples of advanced souls being guided by intuition. These stories are from a book of letters from Paramhansa Yogananda to his second-most-advanced disciple, Yogacharya Oliver Black, My Dear Oliver. Here is the story of how Yogacharya met his guru:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master said he was in Washington, D.C., and he was on his way back home to Los Angeles. A straight line for his travel would have been through Columbus, Ohio, but he said the inner voice/Divine Mother told him to come to Detroit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After he got to Detroit, he didn’t know where to go or what to do. He got a telephone directory and ran his finger down the pages, leaf after leaf, until his finger stopped, and it stopped on the name of Maude Emerson. He called Maude Emerson and told her who he was—that he was Yogananda. She had in fact attended one of his lectures many years before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She explained to him that there was somebody meeting with a group in her home. He was teaching yoga to a class of about ten to twelve people. Master said, “I want to meet that man.” And she got us together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another story tells of this intuitive connection in the other direction. Yogacharya writes:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/let-intuition-be-your-guide.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;let intuition be your guide&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One morning I came to my office and I had a strange feeling or sensation, or itch, and I was scratching the back of my head, at the medulla oblongata. I went in to our treasurer’s office and said, “Well, I don’t know what’s the matter, but while I go home and get my bag, I’d like to have you get me an airplane ticket to Indianapolis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I flew to Indianapolis, and after I got there, I didn’t know what I was there for! [He took a cab to one of the two best hotels in the city.] I went in, and I went up to the counter and asked the clerk, “Is there anybody registered here by the name of Yogananda?” He looked at me and said, “No, there isn’t.” I said, “Where is this other hotel?” He said, “Oh, it’s just down the street.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got there, I went up to the counter and asked, “Is there anyone here by the name of Yogananda?” He said, “Yes, on the ninth floor.” I just went up the elevator and knocked on the door. The door opened, and there he was! Yogananda said, “I knew you would come! I knew you would come! I knew you would come!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuition develops naturally as we grow closer to God and operate more from our soul than from our ego. Intuition, you see, is the soul’s natural way of perception. We can gradually improve our intuition. First, we need to develop our ability to feel: not with emotion, but with a calm sense of knowing. Next, we need to act on our intuitive guidance, which will help it develop just as exercising a muscle helps it grow strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we saw in these two stories, they each acted on a strong feeling even though the next step had not yet been revealed. It takes faith and courage to act on intuitive guidance. Try doing it a step at a time—I wouldn’t suggest you start by buying a plane ticket. Better to wait until your intuition is more highly developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we need to deepen our meditation, and contact our soul nature. A dear friend suggested something that I will pass on to you: He told me, “I have started to keep a log of each meditation. I write down a number to indicate how much of the time my attention was focused, and I also put down a number for how deep my devotion was. Making myself accountable in this way is really helping me deepen my meditation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have started to do this as a New Year’s resolution, and can attest to its effectiveness. I can feel that it is helping me focus better, open up my intuition, and draw Master’s grace and guidance. You might want to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
