<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>devotion on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/devotion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in devotion on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/devotion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spiritual Power</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/spiritual-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/spiritual-power/</guid>
      <description>We are in Assisi, immersed in a Spiritual Renewal Week with the theme “How to Develop Spiritual Power Against Troubled Times.” There is a common misperception in which people confuse developing spiritual power with spiritual powers, the ability to perform miracles.
In today’s class one of the speakers talked about the time when Paramhansa Yogananda visited Therese Neumann, the Bavarian saint. In a chapter about this visit in Autobiography of a Yogi, Yogananda revealed that, in her elevated consciousness, Therese had transcended the need for food.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;We are in Assisi, immersed in a Spiritual Renewal Week with the theme “How to Develop Spiritual Power Against Troubled Times.” There is a common misperception in which people confuse developing spiritual power with spiritual powers, the ability to perform miracles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s class one of the speakers talked about the time when Paramhansa Yogananda visited Therese Neumann, the Bavarian saint. In a chapter about this visit in Autobiography of a Yogi, Yogananda revealed that, in her elevated consciousness, Therese had transcended the need for food. She said that she awoke one day with neither the need nor the desire to eat. In other words, this “power” came to her spontaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the guests attending the program posed the question, “Why didn’t she teach others how to do this? It seems selfish that she kept this ability to herself.” I admit that I was a little shocked by the audacity of the question. I suspect that while many might wonder quietly why the saints don’t share their secrets more openly, few would voice such a question in a class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uma, one of the teachers, gave a marvelous answer. She said that the saints and masters tell us quite openly how to develop such abilities. We just don’t like their answers or their methods. We want to be given a quick fix, but they tell us that it doesn’t work that way. Powers come naturally as our consciousness becomes expanded and elevated. In Therese’s profound connection and attunement to Jesus, she had effectively merged with him. His sufferings became hers to the extent that in her weekly trances she exhibited his wounds on her own body. So the answer to the question of how to rise above the need to eat is to become so immersed in love and devotion that hunger, along with everything else, becomes irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/spiritual-power.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;spiritual-power&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;How does one develop such powers? We don’t so much acquire them as embody them. In a sense, Jesus gave us clear instructions for how to walk on water, or heal others, or feed the masses: “Love God with all your heart, mind, soul, and strength.” As long as we, the ego, want powers, they will elude us. But as the ego dissolves, God, the only power in the universe, will use us as He wills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many years ago we heard a miraculous story from Malka, an Indian friend of ours. After visiting Ananda Village on a pilgrimage, she headed to New York to spend time with her sister. One evening, she fell down some stairs and crushed her arm. At the hospital she was told that she would need emergency surgery. The injuries were so extensive, however, that the surgeon didn’t know if he could knit the shattered bones together, or if he would have to amputate her arm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understandably distraught, she sleeplessly awaited her impending surgery. Amidst her pain and fear, Swami Kriyananda walked into her room. Gently stroking her arm, he assured her, “Don’t worry, Malka. Everything will be fine.” At his soothing words, she fell into a peaceful sleep. The morning surgery was a success, and when we saw her a year later, she joyfully waved her arm in the air to demonstrate the complete healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remarkable feature of the story is that Swami Kriyananda was in California the entire time. When we told him about it, he said, “I have no conscious knowledge of doing that.” But then he added a very deep teaching about the essence of spiritual power: “The soul can act independently of the ego. Nor does it need the ego’s permission to do so.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another way of saying that when we transcend the limitations of ego, God can work wonders through us. Our part is to cooperate with His grace by developing limitless love and the deep desire to help others. Once we fully allow God to flow through us, we will have both spiritual power and, if needed, spiritual powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In His love and joy,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where the Answers Live</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/where-the-answers-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/where-the-answers-live/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever lost something and searched for it everywhere? Of course you have! So have we all. You may hunt here and there, but finally a moment comes when you realize, “I’ve been looking in the wrong place.” Unfortunately, we look in the wrong place not only for things but, more importantly, for the answers to our deepest questions.
The answers to important questions lie more in the heart than in the head.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever lost something and searched for it everywhere? Of course you have! So have we all. You may hunt here and there, but finally a moment comes when you realize, “I’ve been looking in the wrong place.” Unfortunately, we look in the wrong place not only for things but, more importantly, for the answers to our deepest questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answers to important questions lie more in the heart than in the head. Swami Kriyananda told us that true wisdom comes from a combination of pure feeling and discrimination. God has given us both discrimination (buddhi) and feeling (chitta) to navigate this world. But in this age, our purified feeling nature “burns low, and is ill attended.” In such an imbalanced age we can rarely see clearly until we are uplifted by the warm currents of the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is from the heart that intuitive answers whisper to us. After his first great experience of cosmic consciousness, Paramhansa Yogananda said, “I cognized the center of the empyrean as a point of intuitive perception in my heart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuitive answers can only come once we are calm. Recently an elderly friend of ours had lost a container of protein powder. Not only she, but many of her friends searched high and low with no success. Finally, she said, “Let’s ask Master for the answer.” After they had centered themselves for a few minutes she declared, “Look on the shelf in my bedroom closet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve already looked there,” they protested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let’s look again,” she said, undeterred. Sure enough, there it was. It had fallen over behind some clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding something like protein powder is a relatively trivial thing, but the intuitive heart also holds the solutions to more vital questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your heart knows your true purpose.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your intuition already knows your unique pathway to spiritual freedom. If you can calm the restless thoughts and listen sensitively to the deep feelings in your heart you will know your purpose in life. Once you have clarity on this, all else will begin to fall into place as you set out on a journey of wonder and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ananda Village just celebrated its fifty-third anniversary on July 4th, a date we share with the founding of America. In the beginning, only Swamiji discerned the true purpose of Ananda: not political, but spiritual freedom. He said, “Since we are all seeking the same goal, it will be easier if we gather together and support one another in our quest.” He then set about gathering a small group of those attuned to Yogananda’s ray and willing to work together. Since our founding a half-century ago, that little group has grown into a worldwide army of truth seekers.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/where-the-answers-live.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;where the answers live&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your heart knows how to connect to others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world filled with polarity and conflict, we need to prioritize loving connections with one another. Divine Mother loves everyone, and if we attune to Her vibration we, too, will feel that everyone is our brother or sister. As long as humanity stays divided, it will continue to find reasons to judge and to hate one another. The desperate need of our time is to give ascendance to acceptance and friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are with others, listen and speak to them from your heart. Feel behind their words to their unspoken yearnings and needs. And let both your eyes and words radiate loving balms of kindness and support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The heart will lead us to God.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it is the heart that will lead us to God. In meditation we must go beyond thoughts to find God. As Master’s chant says: “Thee I find behind the fringe of my mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the techniques of meditation, sit quietly and feel deep devotion in your heart. Go beyond mere thoughts into the deep yearnings of your soul. When the magnet of your love is strong enough, God will no longer be able to stay hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the heart,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
