<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>duality on Ananda Email</title>
    <link>https://ananda.email/tags/duality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in duality on Ananda Email</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ananda.email/tags/duality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ups and Downs</title>
      <link>https://ananda.email/posts/ups-and-downs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ananda.email/posts/ups-and-downs/</guid>
      <description>Life is a journey of ups and downs. The immutable laws of maya (delusion) dictate that we will navigate through alternating cycles: day and night, birth and death, good and bad. Should we be surprised, then, if our spiritual life also has its peaks and troughs?
There are times when we feel energized, dedicated, and in tune. Then we can be beacons of light for those around us. Yet there are the other times when we’re faced with the challenge of running out of steam.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Life is a journey of ups and downs. The immutable laws of maya (delusion) dictate that we will navigate through alternating cycles: day and night, birth and death, good and bad. Should we be surprised, then, if our spiritual life also has its peaks and troughs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are times when we feel energized, dedicated, and in tune. Then we can be beacons of light for those around us. Yet there are the other times when we’re faced with the challenge of running out of steam. During these times, when our willpower dwindles, feelings of guilt or discouragement can creep in. It is then, especially, that we need a boost from an outside source. Devi and I have an electric vehicle, and when the battery level gets low, no amount of berating it for being lazy seems to help. We have to plug it in to a charging station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve just finished Spiritual Renewal Week at Ananda Village. Swami Kriyananda started this annual tradition at the very beginning of Ananda in 1969 as a way for people to get a big yearly boost of spiritual energy. For many years he single-handedly did everything: sadhanas, classes, kirtans, and music. Gradually, growing numbers of people—teachers, singers, sadhana leaders, and cooks—began to contribute, drawing devotees who come from all corners of the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember an amusing incident from an early Spiritual Renewal Week many years ago. Swamiji was traveling in India, so he asked me to give the classes. I chose the theme of Patanjali’s “yamas and niyamas,” the “don’ts and do’s” for spiritual aspirants. During one of the talks, on the yama of non-stealing, I must have said something that struck a nerve. In the days that followed, quite a few people returned silverware that they had taken from our group dining room. It’s never happened before or since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways that we can uplift our spirits when we feel down. The most important is attuning to God and Guru. Try to feel that He is your closest friend, waiting to help you. During the concluding night of Spiritual Renewal Week, Murali Venkatrao, a remarkable storyteller, told a supremely inspiring and entertaining story about Krishna and his best friend. Here is the link to access this delightful story. It will help reset your relationship with the Divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re tired, it is time to relax, not to push. Once, no doubt feeling a little discouraged, Swami Kriyananda asked Master, “Am I not trying hard enough?” Master replied, “You are trying too hard. It’s creating tension.” So when your spiritual battery is low, find something to do that is simple, relaxing, and enjoyable. Sing, chant, play uplifting music, or watch an inspiring talk.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ananda.email/img/ups-and-downs.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;ups and downs&#34;  class=&#34;center&#34;  style=&#34;border-radius: 7px; width: 100%;&#34;  /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We should remember that “there is a time for every season under heaven.” Down periods will inevitably pass. As Paramhansa Yogananda said, “Life will bring you many ups and downs. If you let your feelings rise and fall with the waves of consciousness, you will never attain that inner calmness which is the foundation of spiritual progress. Be careful, therefore, not to react emotionally. Rise above likes and dislikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A good rule to live by, and one that will take you sailing through many tests in life, is, under all circumstances, to remain even-minded and cheerful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When our spiritual battery is running on reserve, we can always use a little boost from our friends. And, remember, whether you are on the crest of a wave or deep in a trough, you can always look up at the stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In divine friendship,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nayaswami Jyotish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
